[
    {
        "question": "User documentation is part of your definition of \"Done.\" However, there aren't enough technical writers for all teams. Your Development Team doesn't have a technical writer. What should you do?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Wait until you have a technical writer on your Development Team to take care of this",
            "B": "Your Development Team is still responsible for creating user documentation. In this case, the Development Team members will write it",
            "C": "Let the user documentation remain undone and accumulate until after the last development Sprint It will then be done by any available technical writers",
            "D": "Form a separate team of technical writers that will work on an on demand basis for the various Product Owners. Work order will be first in, first out"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Your Development Team is still responsible for creating user documentation. In this case, the Development Team members will write it",
        "explanation": "Waiting for a Technical writer can not be an option. Also, if we keep the documentation undone it will further delay the process. Only to prepare the documentation we cannot form a new team hence we are left with only one option Your Development Team is still responsible for creating user documentation. In this case, the Development Team members will write it."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are criteria to order Product Backlog items?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Dependencies between Product Backlog items",
            "B": "Dependencies to other products",
            "C": "Value of Product Backlog items",
            "D": "The availability of the Scrum Master"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Dependencies between Product Backlog items and Value of Product Backlog items",
        "explanation": "Dependencies to other products and availability of Scrum Master are not criteria to order the items in the product backlog."
    },
    {
        "question": "In order to maximize the value of the product, a Product Owner needs awareness of the following:",
        "options": {
            "A": "Customer feedback",
            "B": "None of the above",
            "C": "Forecasting & feasibility",
            "D": "Product vision",
            "E": "Competitive research"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Customer feedback",
        "explanation": "Customer feedback is the main criteria for the Product Owner to judge over the product release and features."
    },
    {
        "question": "The \"cone of uncertainty\" can be used to do what?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Project what will be completed by a given Sprint",
            "B": "Illustrate that, as a forecast lengthens, it is increasingly less certain",
            "C": "Determine the cost of a project before it is begun",
            "D": "Determine whether to cut quality, similar to the Iron Triangle of project management"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Determine the cost of a project before it is begun",
        "explanation": "The cone of uncertainty is the unknown parameters of the project and it gets reduced as further we move towards the project end. Hence it is expected that we can use it to estimate the project cost initially."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which three of the following are feedback loops in Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Release Planning",
            "B": "Refinement Meeting",
            "C": "Sprint Retrospective",
            "D": "Sprint Review",
            "E": "Daily Scrum"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C",
            "D",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Sprint Retrospective and Sprint Review and Daily Scrum",
        "explanation": "Release Planning, and Refinement Meeting are not scrum events to get feedback. The remaining 3 are."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which two things should the Development Team do during the first Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Develop at least one piece of functionality",
            "B": "Analyze, design, and describe the complete architecture and infrastructure",
            "C": "Analyze, describe, and document the requirements for the subsequent Sprints",
            "D": "Create an Increment of potentially releasable software",
            "E": "Make up a plan for the rest of the project"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Develop at least one piece of functionality and Create an Increment of potentially releasable software",
        "explanation": "Develop at least one piece of functionality. Create an Increment of potentially releasable software. are the two things that can be done in the first sprint. For an Agile project, a complete plan is never prepared at a go. Also, analyzing and creating complete architecture for subsequent sprint or for total project is not done in the first sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which does a self-organizing Development Team choose?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Product Backlog ordering",
            "B": "When to release, based on its progress",
            "C": "How to best accomplish its work",
            "D": "Sprint length",
            "E": "Stakeholders for the Sprint Review"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "How to best accomplish its work",
        "explanation": "How to best accomplish its work because they know the best way to do their job."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Scrum Master Observes the Product Owner struggling with ordering the Product Backlog. What is an appropriate action for the Scrum Master to take?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Present the Product Owner with an ordered Product Backlog to use",
            "B": "Encourage the Product Owner to work with the Development Team to see which items technically are fastest to implement",
            "C": "Suggest the Product Owner extend the Sprint, so he can have more time to order the Product Backlog",
            "D": "Offer the Product Owner help in understanding that the goal of ordering the Product Backlog is to maximize value",
            "E": "Suggest that the Development Team does the ordering to be sure that it is a feasible ordering of work"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Offer the Product Owner help in understanding that the goal of ordering the Product Backlog is to maximize value",
        "explanation": "The Development Team cannot order the product backlog. Also, extending the sprint cannot be an option. Scrum master cannot prepare the entire Product backlog all by himself. And the objective should be to deliver the highest value item not the fastest one.\n\nHence we are left with only one option. Offer the Product Owner help in understanding that the goal of ordering the Product Backlog is to maximize value."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is a Product Owner’s responsibility that he/she might delegate?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Attending the Sprint Review",
            "B": "Representing stakeholders to the Scrum team",
            "C": "Ordering the Product Backlog",
            "D": "Writing User Stories"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Ordering the Product Backlog",
        "explanation": "The development team may need to order the product backlog as they would know the most about technical limitations, risks, or dependencies between Product Backlog Items. As User Stories is a localized practice, Scrum does not govern it or dictate the practice. How the team describes the items is up to them as long as it has enough information to be transparent and understood."
    },
    {
        "question": "A new Product Owner is hired to work on an existing product that is ongoing for five Sprints. He/she is unsure about all of the responsibilities of a Product Owner. Which of these Product Owner's activities are defined in Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Ensuring work is completed within scope and time",
            "B": "Describing features as Use Cases",
            "C": "Interacting with stakeholders and ensuring that the most valuable functionality is always produced first",
            "D": "Writing User Stories"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Interacting with stakeholders and ensuring that the most valuable functionality is always produced first",
        "explanation": "It is only the PO responsibility to talk to stakeholders and ensure that the most valuable items are selected to deliver in sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "Peter is a new Product Owner on a newly formed Scrum Team. Peter has Projected a product completion date based on an estimated velocity of 21 completed points per Sprint. After the first 3 Sprints, the team has determined that their maximum velocity is 15 point's, and they are unable to create shippable increments at the end of each Sprint. What is the best way to proceed?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Inform Peter that the projected completion date is not correct. The Development team would estimate the remaining work to produce a shippable Increment and suggest making it ‘Done” before working on new features. Based on empirical data, Peter car’ adjust the completion date and decide how to continue",
            "B": "The Sprints have failed to produce shippable Increments therefore opportunities to inspect and adapt are lost. The Scrum Master would encourage the organization to add more team members in order to increase the team’s capacity",
            "C": "The Scrum Master would coach the team on improving their estimations and commitment to completing the Sprint Backlog",
            "D": "Extend the Sprint in order to complete the Sprint Backlog items"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Inform Peter that the projected completion date is not correct. The Development team would estimate the remaining work to produce a shippable Increment and suggest making it ‘Done” before working on new features. Based on empirical data, Peter car’ adjust the completion date and decide how to continue",
        "explanation": "Inform Peter that the projected completion date is not correct. The Development team would estimate the remaining work to produce a shippable increment and suggest making it “Done” before working on new features. Based on empirical data, Peter can adjust the completion date and decide how to continue."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following might the Scrum Team discuss during a Sprint Retrospective?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Its definition of “Done.”",
            "B": "Skills needed to improve the Development Team's ability to deliver",
            "C": "Methods of communication",
            "D": "The way the Scrum Team does Sprint Planning"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "B",
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Its definition of “Done.” and Skills needed to improve the Development Team's ability to deliver and Methods of communication and The way the Scrum Team does Sprint Planning",
        "explanation": "All of the points are points to be discussed during Sprint Retrospective."
    },
    {
        "question": "Why would you expect a Product Owner to care about the Development Team adhering to its definition of \"Done\"?",
        "options": {
            "A": "To forecast the team’s productivity over time",
            "B": "The Product Owner should not care about the definition of Done”, it is the Development Teams responsibility",
            "C": "To have complete transparency into what has been done at the end of each Sprint",
            "D": "To be able to punish the team when they don’t meet their velocity goal for the Sprint",
            "E": "The definition of “Done” can affect the product’s total cost of ownership"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "To have complete transparency into what has been done at the end of each Sprint and The definition of “Done” can affect the product’s total cost of ownership",
        "explanation": "Team productivity cannot be forecasted by PO, punishing is not a valid act in Scrum, being a member of Scrum PO must be cared about definition of done."
    },
    {
        "question": "Towards the end of the Sprint, the developers and yourself are debating if some of the Sprint Backlog Items were completed or not. The Scrum Master suggests to you and the developers to refer to the Definition of Done (DoD). Who should set up the DoD?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Scrum Team unless the organization already has one. In that case, they should follow the Definition of Done as a minimum",
            "B": "The developers as they are the ones doing the actual work of converting the Sprint Backlog Items into an Increment",
            "C": "You as Product Owner have the authority to decide what is done and what is not",
            "D": "The Scrum Master as he/she knows how Scrum works and what fit best in an Agile environment"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "The Scrum Team unless the organization already has one. In that case, they should follow the Definition of Done as a minimum",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Team unless the organization already has one. In that case, they should follow the Definition of Done as a minimum. DoD is a collective process."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statements are correct about a Sprint Backlog item that was not finished until the end of the Sprint? Select all correct answers.",
        "options": {
            "A": "It won't be demonstrated at the Sprint Review meeting",
            "B": "It must be completed in the next Sprint",
            "C": "It will be moved back to the Product Backlog",
            "D": "It will be demonstrated to the stakeholders but pointed out that its not complete yet",
            "E": "The Product Owner has to extend the Sprint until the item is done"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "It won't be demonstrated at the Sprint Review meeting and It will be moved back to the Product Backlog",
        "explanation": "Only the 100% complete items are demonstrated, to avoid confusion. When something is not complete, it will be moved back to the Product Backlog. If it's still on the top of the Product Backlog, development will continue in the next Sprint (if it will be required)"
    },
    {
        "question": "The forecast is that we can't develop all items in the Sprint Backlog. Who reviews and makes decisions related to this issue?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Scrum Master",
            "B": "The Developers and the Product Owner",
            "C": "The Business Analyst",
            "D": "The whole Scrum Team",
            "E": "The Solution Architect",
            "F": "The Developers"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "The Developers and the Product Owner",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is the sole person responsible for managing the Product Backlog but always can and must consider the feedback and opinion from other stakeholders including the Developers who can influence to add new items in Product Backlog. Good requirements should be brief enough, that’s why acceptance tests can be used to express many of the details that result from the conversations between customers, users, Product Owners and Developers, including non-functional requirements. One product only has one Product Backlog."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who participates in the Sprint Review?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Product Owner",
            "B": "The Developers",
            "C": "The Scrum Master",
            "D": "Senior Management",
            "E": "The Application Manager",
            "F": "The Key Stakeholders"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "B",
            "C",
            "F"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Owner and The Developers and The Scrum Master and The Key Stakeholders",
        "explanation": "The purpose of the Sprint Review is to inspect the outcome of the Sprint and determine future adaptations. The Scrum Team presents the results of their work to key stakeholders and progress toward the Product Goal is discussed.\n\nThe Scrum Team and stakeholders review what was accomplished in the Sprint and what has changed in their environment. Based on this information, attendees collaborate on what to do next. The Product Backlog may also be adjusted to meet new opportunities. It is not just a presentation but rather it is a working session."
    },
    {
        "question": "Selena, a product owner for a scrum team, has refined the product backlog based on description, order, and size. John, a program manager with the PMO overseeing the group of projects Selena is working on & requested her to place a new item at the top of the product backlog. What should Selena do?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Selena should not be doing anything with the product backlog; this responsibility belongs to developers",
            "B": "Selena is accountable for the product backlog; so John doesn't have authority to request any new item or change the order product backlog",
            "C": "Selena must do as John has asked as John is an important stakeholder (PMO)",
            "D": "Selena may consider the request of others, but the final say as to the order is hers and hers alone"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Selena is accountable for the product backlog; so John doesn't have authority to request any new item or change the order product backlog",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is accountable for effective Product Backlog management but that doesn't mean he/she should not consider others opinions. The Product Owner may represent the needs of many stakeholders in the Product Backlog. Those wanting to change the Product Backlog can do so by trying to convince the Product Owner. So Selena should consider John's request but she has the final say to move or not the item to the top of the product backlog.\n\nProduct Backlog management, which includes:\n\n●      Developing and explicitly communicating the Product Goal;\n\n●      Creating and clearly communicating Product Backlog items;\n\n●      Ordering Product Backlog items; and\n\n●      Ensuring that the Product Backlog is transparent, visible, and understood."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Product Owner should communicate all of the marketplace knowledge & ever-changing landscape, environment to the Scrum Team. What is the best way for a Product Owner to communicate this to the Scrum Team ?",
        "options": {
            "A": "During Product Backlog Refinement",
            "B": "During Sprint Retrospectives",
            "C": "During Daily Scrums",
            "D": "During Sprint Review"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "During Product Backlog Refinement and During Sprint Review",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner communicates all of this marketplace knowledge to the Scrum Team through daily ad-hoc interactions as well as Product Backlog Refinement and in Sprint Reviews. During Product Backlog Refinement Product owner creates and clearly communicates Product Backlog items along with Product Goal. During Sprint review the Product Backlog may also be adjusted to meet new opportunities.\n\nSprint Retrospective & Daily Scrum are not the right forum to discuss this as Daily Scrum is for Developers & Sprint Retrospective is for inspecting the scrum team and creating a plan for improvements to be enacted during the next Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "Our highest priority is to satisfy the customer through early and continuous delivery of valuable software is an Agile Principle. Which scrum practice helps the most in achieving this Agile objective?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Daily Scrum",
            "B": "Sprint",
            "C": "Release Planning",
            "D": "Sprint Planning",
            "E": "Sprint Review"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Sprint",
        "explanation": "Sprint: Short Sprint Cycles. Having shorter sprints would enable teams to deliver early and the cycle of such deliveries would make it continuous delivery to the customer. Sprint planning is there irrespective of the sprint period."
    },
    {
        "question": "Mark is a product owner for a scrum team. He decides for each sprint what items will go into the sprint backlog during sprint planning. He is growing increasingly frustrated with developers not able to complete the task items he has chosen for the sprint. What should Mark do to help developers reach the sprint goal?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Mark should work with the scrum master to find a resolution to this issue",
            "B": "Mark should encourage developers to work more hours, spending weekends if necessary working towards completing the sprint goal",
            "C": "Mark should work more closely with developers; items should not be added to the sprint backlog unless developers can commit to completing the items within the sprint",
            "D": "Mark should work to find more competent developers able to deliver what he decides for each sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Mark should work more closely with developers; items should not be added to the sprint backlog unless developers can commit to completing the items within the sprint",
        "explanation": "During the Sprint no changes are made that would endanger the Sprint Goal. As developers work, it keeps the Sprint Goal in mind. In order to satisfy the Sprint Goal, it implements functionality and technology. If the work turns out to be different than developers expected, they collaborate with the Product Owner to negotiate the scope of Sprint Backlog within the Sprint. So Mark should work more closely with developers; items should not be added to the sprint backlog unless developers can commit to completing the items within the sprint"
    },
    {
        "question": "Scrum Teams are self-managed and cross-functional. How time-boxing promotes self-management?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Time-box does not allow enough time for stringent processes or meeting overhead",
            "B": "Time-box eliminates complexity due to organizational hierarchy",
            "C": "Time-box enables Scrum Team to determine the need for overtime as a percentage of the time-box",
            "D": "Time-box helps everyone to focus on the same problem at the same time",
            "E": "Time-box encourages team members who are closest to the problem to create the best possible solution in  the time allotted"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Time-box helps everyone to focus on the same problem at the same time and Time-box encourages team members who are closest to the problem to create the best possible solution in  the time allotted",
        "explanation": "Time-boxes help everyone focus on the same problem at the same time. Also, it encourages the people who are closest to the problem to create the best possible result in the time allotted, given the current context."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False, In large organizations multiple scrum teams work on the same product. In this scenario, does the Scrum Team use a single Product Backlog?",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "The Product Backlog is an emergent, ordered list of what is needed to improve the product. It is the single source of work undertaken by the Scrum Team.\n\n\n\nMultiple Scrum Teams often work together on the same product. One Product Backlog is used to describe the upcoming work on the product i.e. it is a one to one relationship between Product and Product Backlog. In this scenario, they must mutually define and comply with the same Definition of Done."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is responsible for setting the timeboxed duration of Sprints?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Product Owner",
            "B": "The Team Leader",
            "C": "The Scrum Team",
            "D": "The Development Manager",
            "E": "The Developers",
            "F": "The Solution Architect"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The Scrum Team",
        "explanation": "The only titles that we have in Scrum are Developers, Scrum Master and Product Owner. This is done by the whole Scrum Team, because they can contribute something important that leads to a better decision."
    },
    {
        "question": "After Sprint Planning, the Product Owner finds that it makes sense to develop a new functionality.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Developers will add that to the Sprint Backlog",
            "B": "Developers can review that for selection in the next Sprint",
            "C": "Developers can swap existing functionality for the new functionality",
            "D": "Developers can create a technical spike & pull this to the current sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Developers can review that for selection in the next Sprint",
        "explanation": "Product Owner can't introduce new functionality in the middle of the Sprint unless developers get more capacity to work and they mutually agree to take this in. After the Product Owner adds the new functionality and orders it to be on the top of the Product Backlog, developers can review that for selection in the next Sprint Planning."
    },
    {
        "question": "In a Retrospective, a Scrum Team decides to revise the Sprint length. Pick the statements which are correct about Sprint length.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Sprint length can extend as long as required to complete all the work identified in Sprint Backlog",
            "B": "It is better to have Sprints of consistent length through Scrum journey",
            "C": "The new Sprint length needs to be agreed by the Product Owner",
            "D": "Sprint can have a maximum duration of one month"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "It is better to have Sprints of consistent length through Scrum journey and The new Sprint length needs to be agreed by the Product Owner and Sprint can have a maximum duration of one month",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner needs to ensure that it is short enough to limit business risks and also short enough so the team can synchronize the development work with other business events. Please note that the finalized Sprint length cannot be longer than 1 calendar month."
    },
    {
        "question": "James is a product owner for a scrum team. The customer has expressed concerns about releasing new software after every sprint. What should James do?",
        "options": {
            "A": "An increment must be released after a sprint James should insist on longer sprints to meet the customers longer release cycle",
            "B": "An increment only needs to be potentially releasable, James may hold back several increments and work with the customer on a release schedule that fits their needs",
            "C": "James should ask the scrum master to put together a release planning meeting to help convince the customer of the value of incremental release",
            "D": "An increment must be released after a sprint James should explain to the customer what scrum is and how scrum handles releases"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "An increment only needs to be potentially releasable, James may hold back several increments and work with the customer on a release schedule that fits their needs",
        "explanation": "The Increment is the sum of all the Product Backlog items completed during a Sprint and the value of the increments of all previous Sprints. At the end of a Sprint, the new Increment must be \"Done,\" which means it must be in usable condition and meet the Scrum Team's definition of \"Done”. The increment must be in usable condition regardless of whether the Product Owner decides to release it."
    },
    {
        "question": "Mark is a product owner for a scrum team. He wants to get some additional product backlog items added to the current sprint backlog. Sprint planning has already happened, what should Mark do?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Mark should bring it up at a daily scrum meeting and discuss it with developers; adding additional time to the daily scrum if needed",
            "B": "Mark should hold a separate meeting with developers and discuss the options of adding some additional items; developers can consider the possibility and may be able to accommodate the additional work",
            "C": "Mark should just add the items to the sprint backlog, the self managing Developers will figure out the best way to accommodate the additional work",
            "D": "Mark should consult with the scrum master; the scrum master will make the final call as to whether the work will be added to the current sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Mark should hold a separate meeting with developers and discuss the options of adding some additional items; developers can consider the possibility and may be able to accommodate the additional work",
        "explanation": "The Sprint Backlog makes visible all the work that developers identify as necessary to meet the Sprint Goal. Developers modify the Sprint Backlog throughout the Sprint, and the Sprint Backlog emerges during the Sprint. This emergence occurs as developers work through the plan and learn more about the work needed to achieve the Sprint Goal. As new work is required, developers add it to the Sprint Backlog. As work is performed or completed, the estimated remaining work is updated. When elements of the plan are deemed unnecessary, they are removed. Only developers can change its Sprint Backlog during a Sprint. So Mark should discuss with Developers the possibility of accommodating this additional work."
    },
    {
        "question": "Each Increment is additive to all prior Increments and thoroughly verified, ensuring that all Increments work together. Who has the final deciding authority on whether to release it or not?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Developers",
            "B": "The Product Owner",
            "C": "The Scrum Master",
            "D": "The Scrum Team",
            "E": "The stakeholders"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "The Scrum Team",
        "explanation": "An Increment is a concrete stepping stone toward the Product Goal. Each Increment is additive to all prior Increments and thoroughly verified, ensuring that all Increments work together. In order to provide value, the Increment must be usable.\n\n\n\nThe Scrum Team is responsible for all product-related activities from stakeholder collaboration, verification, maintenance, operation, experimentation, research and development, and anything else that might be required. In the past, the Product Owner was the release decision-maker but now the release decision is on the whole scrum team."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Developers find out during the Sprint that they are not likely to build everything they forecast. What would you expect a Product Owner to do?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Cancel the Sprint",
            "B": "Skip Product Backlog refinement activities",
            "C": "Change the Sprint Goal",
            "D": "Renegotiate the selected Product Backlog items with the Developers",
            "E": "Inform management that more resources are needed"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Renegotiate the selected Product Backlog items with the Developers",
        "explanation": "During the Sprint. scope may be clarified and re-negotiated between the Product Owner and Developers as more is learned."
    },
    {
        "question": "When does a Developer become accountable for the value of a Product Backlog item selected for the Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Never. The entire Scrum Team is accountable for creating value every Sprint",
            "B": "During the Daily Scrum",
            "C": "Whenever a team member can accommodate more work",
            "D": "At the Sprint Planning Event"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Never. The entire Scrum Team is accountable for creating value every Sprint",
        "explanation": "All members of the Scrum Team share in the accountability for creating value every Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or false. Our velocity was 250 at the end of the 6th Sprint. It becomes 275 at the end of the 8th Sprint. Therefore, we're creating more value now compared to before.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "FALSE, There's no direct relationship between velocity (speed) and value; e.g., maybe we're working faster on less valuable items, in which case, velocity will be higher, but value may be the same, higher, or lower. Many people consider velocity as the most important criterion, but that's not true -- we should rather be focused on value, Sprint Goal, and Product Goal."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Product Owner decides not to create a Product Goal. In this case select all correct answers.",
        "options": {
            "A": "It is up to the Product Owner",
            "B": "Changing the core design or ideas of Scrum, leaving out elements, or not following the rules of Scrum, covers up problems and limits the benefits of Scrum, potentially even rendering it useless",
            "C": "The Scrum Master is helping find techniques for effective Product Goal definition and Product Backlog management",
            "D": "The Product Owner must discuss with Developers and if they are ok with it, then he or she may remove the Product Goal"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Changing the core design or ideas of Scrum, leaving out elements, or not following the rules of Scrum, covers up problems and limits the benefits of Scrum, potentially even rendering it useless and The Scrum Master is helping find techniques for effective Product Goal definition and Product Backlog management",
        "explanation": "As we know from the Scrum Guide while implementing only parts of Scrum is possible (by removing the Product Goal), the result is not Scrum. Scrum exists only in its entirety and functions well as a container for other techniques, methodologies, and practices. In this case, the best action from the Scrum Master to discuss it with the Product Owner and find techniques for effective Product Goal definition"
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The key stakeholders are expected to participate in the Sprint Review",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Team presents the results of their work to key stakeholders in the Sprint Review and progress toward the Product Goal is discussed."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the main responsibility of a tester in Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Writing the test scripts as soon as the programmers start working on the code",
            "B": "Finding bugs",
            "C": "There are no testers in Scrum",
            "D": "Verifying the work of Developers"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "There are no testers in Scrum",
        "explanation": "There are no members titled as testers, because we don't have extra accountabilities and titles in Scrum. However, there can be Developers who are experts in testing. Remember that everyone is called a Developer. When you see a statement like \"Developer with testing expertise\" in your real exam, it usually means \"tester\" as an accountability or title, rather than a person who's expert in testing."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Product Backlog is the single source of requirements for any changes to be made to the product. How should a Product Backlog item be refined when it is located at the top? Select all correct answers?",
        "options": {
            "A": "It should be clear which developer is responsible for it",
            "B": "In a way that it can be,“Done” in the timeboxed duration of one Sprint",
            "C": "In a way that's clear enough for the developers",
            "D": "All the tasks required for completing it should be identified"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "In a way that it can be,“Done” in the timeboxed duration of one Sprint and In a way that's clear enough for the developers",
        "explanation": "Items at the top of the Product Backlog should be small enough to fit in one Sprint. They should also be clear and detailed enough; but not too detailed (e.g. not with all the tasks identified), as it would be upfront planning. Tasks are created gradually during the Sprint. Product Backlog items require multiple expertise and are usually done by multiple developers. Therefore, they are not assigned. Tasks, however, are assigned to the individual developers, while everyone stays accountable."
    },
    {
        "question": "Why should there be only one Product Owner per product?",
        "options": {
            "A": "There should be one Product Owner for each team. If more than one team is working on the same product, multiple Product Owners might be needed",
            "B": "Developers know who’s responsible for prioritization",
            "C": "One person ¡s always enough for this role",
            "D": "It becomes confusing when more than one Product Owner ¡s managing the team"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Developers know who’s responsible for prioritization",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is one person, not a committee. The Product Owner may represent the desires of a committee in the Product Backlog, but those wanting to change a Product Backlog item’s priority must address the Product Owner. For the Product Owner to succeed, the entire organization must respect his or her decisions. The Product Owner’s decisions are visible in the content and ordering of the Product Backlog. No one can force Developers to work from a different set of requirements and developers know who’s responsible for prioritization."
    },
    {
        "question": "This accountability in Scrum must know the most about the product and performance of the product?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Scrum Master",
            "B": "The Scrum Team",
            "C": "The Product Owner",
            "D": "The project manager",
            "E": "The Product Master"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Owner",
        "explanation": "Measuring the release or product performance is the Product Owner's responsibility. Measuring Sprint performance is the responsibility of Developers."
    },
    {
        "question": "What of the following are key factors within the Scrum Team to organize themselves?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Having all the competencies required to accomplish the work without depending on others",
            "B": "They should be transparent to the Team Lead",
            "C": "They should be self-managed",
            "D": "They should make sure that they have frequent meetings with the software architects"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Having all the competencies required to accomplish the work without depending on others and They should be self-managed",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Team should be self-managing and cross-functional and they should find the best to accomplish their work, rather than being directed by others outside the team."
    },
    {
        "question": "The main goal for the Product Owner is to maximize the value of the product. But how should the Product Owner forecast the completion date?",
        "options": {
            "A": "By any method the PO finds appropriate",
            "B": "By dividing the remaining amount of work in the Product Backlog to the latest calculated velocity",
            "C": "By using a trend line in the burn-down chart",
            "D": "It is not the responsibility of the Product Owner. The Scrum Master must forecast the completion date"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "By any method the PO finds appropriate",
        "explanation": "Using a trend line in the burn-down chart can help (if the team is using that chart), as well as simple or complex formulas such as the one mentioned above. But all of these are just guides for the Product Owner and she should consider all factors and come up with a reliable completion date forecast."
    },
    {
        "question": "In Scrum, when a Product Backlog item or an Increment is described as \"Done\", everyone in the team must understand what \"Done\" means. From the following answers, choose the LEAST accurate statement about the Definition of \"Done\"?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Product Owner creates it",
            "B": "The Scrum Team may define it",
            "C": "It may vary depending on the product",
            "D": "It may evolve during the product life"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Owner creates it",
        "explanation": "The DoD is not created by the Product Owner. If the Definition of Done for an increment is part of the standards of the organization, all Scrum Teams must follow it as a minimum. If it is not an organizational standard, the Scrum Team must create a Definition of Done appropriately for the product."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Product Owner should be expertly aware of the marketplace for the product.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False",
            "C": "It depends"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "Product Owner should be expertly aware of the marketplace for the product. They should constantly be gathering and re-gathering information and data regarding the marketplace so that the product value is maximized. Getting out of touch with the marketplace can be a recipe for product disaster."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Product Owner is the sole person accountable for managing the Product Backlog.",
        "options": {
            "A": "False",
            "B": "True"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is accountable for effective Product Backlog management, which includes:\n\nDeveloping and explicitly communicating the Product Goal; Creating and clearly communicating Product Backlog items; Ordering Product Backlog items; and, Ensuring that the Product Backlog is transparent, visible and understood."
    },
    {
        "question": "Select 2 true statements about Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Scrum is a methodology for managing complex projects",
            "B": "Scrum is a traditional process but with Sprints and related artifacts",
            "C": "Scrum is a framework  for developing and maintaining complex products",
            "D": "Scrum is based on empirical process control theory"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Scrum is a framework  for developing and maintaining complex products and Scrum is based on empirical process control theory",
        "explanation": "Scrum is a framework, not a methodology or body of knowledge. Scrum is empirical, rather than theoretical. Scrum is more about project delivery rather than project management. Scrum is adaptive, rather than predictive (it's more than just using Sprints and related artifacts). Scrum should be used entirely (we do not tailor it)"
    },
    {
        "question": "During the Sprint Review, the Scrum Team and stakeholders collaborate about what was done in the Sprint. The stakeholders are invited to the Sprint Review in order to:",
        "options": {
            "A": "Choose only one best answer",
            "B": "Provide feedback on the team working style",
            "C": "Provide feedback on Scrum implementation",
            "D": "Provide feedback on the Increment",
            "E": "Provide feedback on design and architecture"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Provide feedback on Scrum implementation",
        "explanation": "During the Sprint Review, the Scrum Team and stakeholders collaborate about what was done in the Sprint. Based on that and any changes to the Product Backlog during the Sprint, attendees collaborate on the next things that could be done to optimize value. This is an informal meeting, not a status meeting, and the presentation of the Increment is intended to elicit feedback and foster collaboration."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Product Backlog Refinement is not a mandatory event in Scrum. However, almost all Scrum Teams are holding this event. From the following answers select all correct benefits of the Product Backlog Refinement?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Clarify Value",
            "B": "Reduce Dependencies",
            "C": "Decrease velocity",
            "D": "Improve relationship in the Scrum Team",
            "E": "Incorporate Learning"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "B",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Clarify Value and Reduce Dependencies and Incorporate Learning",
        "explanation": "In general there are 6 important benefits of the PBR. Here they are:\n\n●      Increase transparency\n\n●      Clarify value\n\n●      Break things into consumable pieces\n\n●      Reduce dependencies\n\n●      Forecasting\n\n●      Incorporate learning"
    },
    {
        "question": "A stakeholder is a person external to the Scrum Team with a specific interest in and knowledge of a product that is required for incremental discovery. Who are the typical key stakeholders in Scrum? Select all correct answers.",
        "options": {
            "A": "The people responsible for making the funding decisions for the product development effort",
            "B": "The people responsible for product marketing",
            "C": "The people who actually use the product under development",
            "D": "The people responsible for paying to use the product",
            "E": "The people responsible for product development",
            "F": "The people from the security department"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "The people responsible for making the funding decisions for the product development effort and The people who actually use the product under development and The people responsible for paying to use the product",
        "explanation": "Typical stakeholder is the man who is responsible for making the funding decisions for the product development effort, the user of the product, the man who is responsible for paying to use the product"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is the LEAST productive way for the Scrum Master to improve communication between Developers and the Product Owner?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Giving the order to all members of the team and act as a go-between for them",
            "B": "Suggest effective communication tools and techniques to the Product Owner",
            "C": "Monitor their communication performance",
            "D": "Teach them how to communicate effectively"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Giving the order to all members of the team and act as a go-between for them",
        "explanation": "Acting as a go-between weakens the team. Also, the Scrum Master is not the team leader (in people management), he or she can't manage the team and give any order. But The Scrum Master is supposed to teach and coach and be the leader in serving the team."
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the most challenging activities in Scrum is Product Backlog Refinement (although the PBR is not an event in Scrum). How should a Product Backlog item be refined before its development begins? Select all correct answers.",
        "options": {
            "A": "In a way that it's clear enough for Developers",
            "B": "It should be clear which member of the Scrum Team is responsible for it",
            "C": "In a way that it can be “Done in the time-boxed duration of one Sprint",
            "D": "All the tasks required for completing it should be identified"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "In a way that it's clear enough for Developers and In a way that it can be “Done in the time-boxed duration of one Sprint",
        "explanation": "A Product Backlog should be refined in a way that it's clear enough for Developers and it can be \"Done\" in the time-boxed duration of one Sprint"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which two statements are correct during the Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The scope may be clarified as more is learned",
            "B": "Some Sprint Backlog items will be replaced with items from the Product Backlog if the priorities change",
            "C": "The scope may be re-negotiated as more is learned",
            "D": "Some Sprint Backlog items would be moved back to the Product Backlog to be completed in future Sprints"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The scope may be clarified as more is learned and The scope may be re-negotiated as more is learned",
        "explanation": "During the Sprint: No changes are made that would endanger the Sprint Goal; Quality goals do not decrease; and, Scope may be clarified and re-negotiated between the Product Owner and Developers as more is learned."
    },
    {
        "question": "The most important stakeholder wants a new feature to be added to the current Sprint. What is the best response for Developers in this situation?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Ask the Product Owner to work with the customer",
            "B": "Reject the request",
            "C": "Add the item to the bottom of the Sprint Backlog",
            "D": "Swap the item with one of the items in the Sprint Backlog",
            "E": "Add the item to the Product Backlog"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Ask the Product Owner to work with the customer",
        "explanation": "No one can add additional items to the Product Backlog (source for development work) except the Product Owner. First stakeholder has to discuss it with the Product Owner"
    },
    {
        "question": "How many Product Goals can a Scrum team have at a moment?",
        "options": {
            "A": "No more than 3 Product Goals",
            "B": "No more than 1 Product Goal",
            "C": "Unlimited numbers of Product Goals"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No more than 1 Product Goal",
        "explanation": "You can only have one Product Goal, so when the current Product Goal is achieved a new one would be created. If there is a significant change in context and the current Product Goal has not been achieved then the Scrum Team would replace the Product Goal with a more fitting one. If the Product is no longer relevant in the market (remember floppy disks, video cassettes, etc ), then the organization would either pivot or fold."
    },
    {
        "question": "A Definition of Done drives the quality of work and is used to assess when a task has been completed. But what are the benefits of having tests in the definition of “Done”? Select all correct answers.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Increments would be closer to being potentially shippable",
            "B": "Increased transparency and the quality of the Increments",
            "C": "Increments would be more complete",
            "D": "Reporting would be easier for the project manager"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Increments would be closer to being potentially shippable and Increased transparency and the quality of the Increments and Increments would be more complete",
        "explanation": "Developers deliver an Increment of product functionality every Sprint. This Increment is usable, so a Product Owner may choose to immediately release it. If the definition of \"Done\" for an increment is part of the conventions, standards or guidelines of the development organization, all Scrum Teams must follow it as a minimum. If \"Done\" for an increment is not a convention of the development organization, Developers of the Scrum Team must define a definition of \"Done\" appropriate for the product. If there are multiple Scrum Teams working on the system or product release, Developers on all Scrum Teams must mutually define the definition of \"Done\". Each Increment is additive to all prior Increments and thoroughly tested, ensuring that all Increments work together.\n\n\n\nAs Scrum Teams mature, it is expected that their definitions of \"Done\" will expand to include more stringent criteria for higher quality. New definitions, as used, may uncover work to be done in previously “Done” increments. A product or system should have a definition of \"Done\" that is a standard for any work done on it."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Scrum Team has just finished the Sprint Planning. According to this, choose all correct statements from the following answers?",
        "options": {
            "A": "After the Sprint Planning, a Sprint cannot proceed without complete requirement specification",
            "B": "After the Sprint Planning, a Sprint cannot proceed  without a Sprint Goal",
            "C": "After the Sprint complete Sprint Planning, a Sprint can proceed without Backlog",
            "D": "After the Sprint Planning, a Sprint cannot proceed without complete design and BRD or FSD"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "After the Sprint Planning, a Sprint cannot proceed  without a Sprint Goal and After the Sprint complete Sprint Planning, a Sprint can proceed without Backlog",
        "explanation": "The Sprint Goal is an objective set for the Sprint that can be met through the implementation of Product Backlog. It provides guidance to Developers on why they are building the increment. It is created during the Sprint Planning meeting. As new work is required, Developers add it to the Sprint Backlog. As work is performed or completed, the estimated remaining work is updated. When elements of the plan are deemed unnecessary, they are removed."
    },
    {
        "question": "According to the Scrum Guide, that is the reason why the Daily Scrum should be held at the same time and the same place?",
        "options": {
            "A": "It makes easier to book the rooms",
            "B": "Because the place can be named",
            "C": "Because the Product Owner requires it",
            "D": "To reduce complexity and overheat"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "To reduce complexity and overheat",
        "explanation": "The Daily Scrum is held at the same time and place each day to reduce complexity."
    },
    {
        "question": "According to the Scrum Guide, Scrum is founded on empiricism and lean thinking. What else is true about Scrum? Select all correct answers.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Scrum is a methodology for managing complex projects",
            "B": "Scrum is a traditional process but with Sprints and related artifacts",
            "C": "Scrum is a framework for developing and maintaining complex products",
            "D": "Scrum employs an iterative, incremental approach to optimize predictability and control risk"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Scrum is a framework for developing and maintaining complex products and Scrum employs an iterative, incremental approach to optimize predictability and control risk",
        "explanation": "Scrum is a lightweight framework that helps people, teams and organizations generate value through adaptive solutions for complex problems. Scrum employs an iterative, incremental approach to optimize predictability and control risk. Scrum engages groups of people who collectively have all the skills and expertise to do the work and share or acquire such skills as needed."
    },
    {
        "question": "During a Sprint Review, stakeholders notice that the product development progress is not clearly visible and lacks transparency. Moreover, they are not able to understand the next steps. Who is responsible for this?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Developers",
            "B": "Product Owner",
            "C": "Scrum Master",
            "D": "Scrum Team"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Product Owner",
        "explanation": "The PO ensures that the Product Backlog is visible, transparent, and clear to all, and shows what the Scrum Team will work on next. The Product Owner is the Lead Facilitator of Key Stakeholder Involvement. The PO is responsible for identifying the key stakeholders for the product and involving them as necessary throughout the development effort."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Scrum Team consists of the PO, SM and Developers. One of the responsibilities of Scrum Master is to find, track and help remove different obstacles. But who supports the Scrum Master in removing obstacles?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Project Manager",
            "B": "The senior management",
            "C": "The senior Developer",
            "D": "Developers"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "The senior management and Developers",
        "explanation": "Developers can help the Scrum Master because of their understanding of how the work is done. Some impediments are rooted in external causes, and that’s why the Scrum Master might need to have the senior management's support in removing them"
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Product Backlog is baselined at the beginning of the project?",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "There is no such action in Scrum as baselining the product backlog"
    },
    {
        "question": "The role of Scrum Master in Sprint Retrospective is: Choose only one best answer.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Auditor",
            "B": "Peer Team Member",
            "C": "None of the above",
            "D": "Business analyst"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "None of the above",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Master participates as a peer team member in the meeting from the accountability over the Scrum process, As a team member, the Scrum Master (tike any other member} identifies the most helpful changes to improve the effectiveness of the Scrum Team"
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. According to the Scrum Guide, the Product Owner can transfer some of his/her accountability to Developers.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is accountable for maximizing the value of the product resulting from the work of the Scrum Team. How this is done may vary widely across organizations, Scrum Teams, and individuals. The Product Owner is also accountable for effective Product Backlog management, which includes:\n\n●      Developing and explicitly communicating the Product Goal;\n\n●      Creating and clearly communicating Product Backlog items;\n\n●      Ordering Product Backlog items;\n\n●      Ensuring that the Product Backlog is transparent, visible and understood.\n\n\n\nThe Product Owner may do the above work or may delegate the responsibility to others. Regardless, the Product Owner remains accountable."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Product Owner has some problems with managing the Product Backlog. What is the right action from the Scrum Master in this situation?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Extend the Sprint so that the Product Owner has more time to order items",
            "B": "Help the Product Owner to find techniques for effective Product Goal definition and Product Backlog management",
            "C": "Ask Developers help the Product Owner understand the dependencies among items to be used in ordering them",
            "D": "Ask the stakeholder to change the Product Owner"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Help the Product Owner to find techniques for effective Product Goal definition and Product Backlog management",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Master serves the Product Owner in several ways, including:\n\n●      Helping find techniques for effective Product Goal definition and Product Backlog management;\n\n●      Helping the Scrum Team understand the need for clear and concise Product Backlog items;\n\n●      Helping establish empirical product planning for a complex environment;\n\n●      Facilitating stakeholder collaboration as requested or needed."
    },
    {
        "question": "There are many responsibilities in Scrum for the Product Owner. From the following answers choose three of them .Choose all answers that apply.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Break down epic items into smaller ones",
            "B": "Create user stories (if the Scrum Team uses user story format as a task)",
            "C": "Prioritize the Product Backlog",
            "D": "Design Software",
            "E": "Facilitate meetings",
            "F": "Provide estimates",
            "G": "Make technical decisions"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Break down epic items into smaller ones and Create user stories (if the Scrum Team uses user story format as a task) and Prioritize the Product Backlog",
        "explanation": "Designing the software is part of the development and should be done by the developers. They make technical decisions, and volunteer for tasks (assign them to themselves). Estimation is the responsibility of the developers because they are the people who will develop the item. The rest (from the following) are done by the Product Owner."
    },
    {
        "question": "During the Sprint Review, the Scrum Team and stakeholders collaborate about what was done in the Sprint. The stakeholders are invited to the Sprint Review in order to:",
        "options": {
            "A": "Choose only one best answer",
            "B": "Provide feedback on the team working style",
            "C": "Provide feedback on Scrum implementation",
            "D": "Provide feedback on the Increment",
            "E": "Provide feedback on design and architecture"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Provide feedback on Scrum implementation",
        "explanation": "During the Sprint Review, the Scrum Team and stakeholders collaborate about what was done in the Sprint. Based on that and any changes to the Product Backlog during the Sprint, attendees collaborate on the next things that could be done to optimize value. This is an informal meeting, not a status meeting, and the presentation of the Increment is intended to elicit feedback and foster collaboration."
    },
    {
        "question": "When is an item in the Sprint Backlog considered complete?",
        "options": {
            "A": "When there’s nothing more we need to do before it can be used by end users",
            "B": "When the Sprint is over",
            "C": "When the whole Scrum Team agrees that it’s complete",
            "D": "When user acceptance tests are passed"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "When there’s nothing more we need to do before it can be used by end users",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Team can't agree that it's complete, there's a limit to self-management. It's possible to not even start working on an item before the Sprint is over, so you can't call it complete. A Product Backlog item that you have in the Sprint Backlog is Done, when it can be part of a Done Increment. Increments have to be Done based on the Definition of Done."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are needed in order to allow Sprint Planning to begin?",
        "options": {
            "A": "A fully refined Product Backlog",
            "B": "A clear cadence of when the Daily Scrum will take place",
            "C": "A Product Backlog with the most important items ready for discussion",
            "D": "Formal budget approval to conduct another Sprint",
            "E": "A Product Goal communicated by the Product Owner",
            "F": "A clear and non-negotiable Sprint Goal"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "A Product Backlog with the most important items ready for discussion and A Product Goal communicated by the Product Owner",
        "explanation": "Sprint Planning initiates the Sprint by laying out the work to be performed for the Sprint. This resulting plan is created by the collaborative work of the entire Scrum Team. The Product Owner ensures that attendees are prepared to discuss the most important Product Backlog items and how they map to the Product Goal."
    },
    {
        "question": "How important is it for a Product Owner to order Product Backlog items by using value points?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Using value points is the ultimate way for a Product Owner to predict the value that the product will provide",
            "B": "Calculating value points ¡s a predictive approach that conflicts with the empiricism of Scrum, and is therefore not acceptable",
            "C": "The Product Owner may order the Product Backlog by using value points or select another technique, the  decision is up to them"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Owner may order the Product Backlog by using value points or select another technique, the  decision is up to them",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is accountable for ordering the Product backlog, regardless of the techniques they may utilize to define that order. Indications of value on Product Backlog items may be useful but are only a prediction until validated by users and the market."
    },
    {
        "question": "When can the Product Backlog be updated?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Never, unless agreed to by the change request",
            "B": "Only after a Sprint Review if agreed to by the stakeholders",
            "C": "At any time when done by the Product Owner or a  delegate",
            "D": "Only during Product Backlog refinement sessions if the Product Owner is present"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "At any time when done by the Product Owner or a  delegate",
        "explanation": "The Product Backlog is dynamic: it constantly changes to identify what the product needs in order to be appropriate, competitive, and useful. Product Backlog items can be updated at any time by the Product Owner or a delegate. Even if the responsibility is delegated the Product Owner remains accountable for the Product Backlog."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which two statements explain why the Definition of Done is important to the Product Owner?",
        "options": {
            "A": "It identifies undone work that can be addressed in a separate Sprint",
            "B": "It creates transparency regarding progress within the  Scrum Team",
            "C": "It helps the Product Owner track the open work during a Sprint",
            "D": "It establishes the expected quality of the Increment reviewed at the Sprint Review"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "It creates transparency regarding progress within the  Scrum Team and It establishes the expected quality of the Increment reviewed at the Sprint Review",
        "explanation": "All Scrum Team members must have a shared understanding of what it means for work to be complete. to ensure transparency. This is the Definition of Done for the Scrum Team and is used to assess when work is complete on the product Increment. The Increment reviewed at the Sprint Review must meet the Definition of Done."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Product Owner's authority to change and update the Product Backlog is unlimited, except for:",
        "options": {
            "A": "Decisions by the chief program manager",
            "B": "Technical and architectural work that needs to be done first, as indicated by the chief enterprise architect",
            "C": "Decisions by the CFO, the CEO or the board of directors",
            "D": "There are no exceptions; the entire organization must respect a Product Owner's decisions",
            "E": "High impact changes that have not been approved by the change request board",
            "F": "Items the Scrum Master has identified as impediments"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "There are no exceptions; the entire organization must respect a Product Owner's decisions",
        "explanation": "Everyone in the Team and in the organization must respect PO decisions."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the principal value of releasing an Increment?",
        "options": {
            "A": "To learn about the Scrum Team’s productivity",
            "B": "To validate assumptions made when developing the product",
            "C": "To learn about the forecast of functionality that was developed"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "To validate assumptions made when developing the product",
        "explanation": "Releasing the Increment to customers/users is the only way to validate assumptions about value."
    },
    {
        "question": "How does an organization know that a product built using Scrum is successful?",
        "options": {
            "A": "By releasing frequently, and measuring the value customers/users experience",
            "B": "By measuring that velocity has increased since the last release",
            "C": "By measuring the actual time spent on development versus the time estimated for development",
            "D": "By the Product Owner and stakeholders accepting the Increment at the Sprint Review"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "By releasing frequently, and measuring the value customers/users experience",
        "explanation": "Scrum Teams deliver products iteratively and incrementally, maximizing opportunities for feedback. If a product is not released. the opportunity to capture user and market feedback is lost."
    },
    {
        "question": "What are typical activities for a Product Owner in a Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Create financial reporting upon the spent hours reported by the Scrum Team",
            "B": "Collaborate with stakeholders, user communities, and subject matter experts",
            "C": "Update the work plan for the Developers on a daily basis",
            "D": "Attend every Daily Scrum to answer functional questions on the discussed Sprint Backlog items"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Collaborate with stakeholders, user communities, and subject matter experts and Attend every Daily Scrum to answer functional questions on the discussed Sprint Backlog items",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner represents the needs of many stakeholders in the Product Backlog. This typically requires active interaction in order to be able to represent stakeholders and their needs. Product Backlog refinement is an ongoing process in which the Product Owner and the Developers may collaborate on the details of Product Backlog items."
    },
    {
        "question": "What best describes the relationship of the Product Owner and the stakeholders?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Product Owner writes the User Stories as provided by the stakeholders",
            "B": "The Product Owner provides the stakeholders with acceptance forms at the Sprint Review to record their formal agreement over the delivered software",
            "C": "The Product Owner has the final call over the requirements and should involve the stakeholders as little as possible",
            "D": "The Product Owner actively asks for stakeholder input and expectations to incorporate into the Product Backlog"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Owner actively asks for stakeholder input and expectations to incorporate into the Product Backlog",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner represents the stakeholders to the Scrum Team. which includes representing their desired requirements in the Product Backlog. The Product Owner is accountable for maximizing the value of the product resulting from the work of the Scrum Team. The Product Owner is also accountable for effective Product Backlog management."
    },
    {
        "question": "Adaptation requires regular inspection. In what ways does the Product Owner contribute to the results achieved by inspection?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Product Owner inspects the Sprint burn-down at the Daily Scrum for progress towards a complete Increment and re-planning the team's work",
            "B": "The Product Owner invites stakeholders to the Sprint Review to learn how the current state of the marketplace influences what is the most valuable thing to do next",
            "C": "The Product Owner verifies the Sprint Backlog for completeness at the end of Sprint Planning in order to allow the Sprint to start",
            "D": "The Product Owner shares the current state of Product Backlog at the Sprint Review, which, combined with the  inspection of the Increment leads to an updated Product Backlog"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Owner invites stakeholders to the Sprint Review to learn how the current state of the marketplace influences what is the most valuable thing to do next and The Product Owner shares the current state of Product Backlog at the Sprint Review, which, combined with the  inspection of the Increment leads to an updated Product Backlog",
        "explanation": "Scrum users must frequently inspect Scrum artifacts and progress to detect undesirable variances. The primary tool for the Product Owner to uphold transparency is the Product Backlog. Product Backlog is a living artifact that is actively maintained and updated to reflect reality. At the Sprint Review, attendees collaborate on the next things that could be done to optimize value. which is processed into an updated Product Backlog."
    },
    {
        "question": "To what extent does technical debt limit the value a Product Owner can get from a product?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Technical debt causes a greater percentage of the product's budget to be spent on maintenance of the product",
            "B": "The velocity at which new functionality can be created is reduced when you have technical debt",
            "C": "Technical debt is not a Product Owner concern, technical debt is only an issue for the Developers",
            "D": "Technical debt does not influence the delivery of value"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Technical debt causes a greater percentage of the product's budget to be spent on maintenance of the product and The velocity at which new functionality can be created is reduced when you have technical debt",
        "explanation": "Technical debt does influence and it is a concern of the PO."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False: A first Sprint can start before the Product Owner has a complete and exhaustive Product Backlog in place.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "A first Sprint requires no more than a Scrum Team and enough ideas to potentially complete a full Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "How do timeboxes help the Product Owner and the other members of the Scrum Team validate assumptions, adapt, and maximize the value of their product?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Timeboxes help by making sure a Sprint does not stop until all testing is done, and the work is verified by the Product Owner",
            "B": "Timeboxes assure the Product Owner that the Developers will finish all work on the Sprint Backlog by the end of the Sprint",
            "C": "At the end of each Sprint when the timebox expires a detailed report with all test cases and test results is available",
            "D": "Timeboxes help minimize risk by creating the opportunity to validate assumptions using feedback from users and the market; allowing Scrum Teams to inspect progress toward the Product Goal and decide whether to pivot or persevere"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Timeboxes help minimize risk by creating the opportunity to validate assumptions using feedback from users and the market; allowing Scrum Teams to inspect progress toward the Product Goal and decide whether to pivot or persevere",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner manages the Product Backlog against the assumption that value will be generated. This assumption remains invalidated when not checked against users and the market. When a Sprints horizon is too long. you increase the risk that what is being developed may no longer be desired. Sprints limit risk to one calendar month or less of work."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes Scrum here?",
        "options": {
            "A": "A cookbook that defines best practices for software development",
            "B": "A defined and predictive process that conforms to the principles of Scientific Management",
            "C": "A framework for creating complex products in complex environments",
            "D": "A complete methodology that defines how to develop software"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "A framework for creating complex products in complex environments",
        "explanation": "Scrum is a lightweight framework that helps people. teams and organizations generate value through adaptive solutions for complex problems."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is required to attend the Daily Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Developers",
            "B": "The Developers and Product Owner",
            "C": "The Scrum Team",
            "D": "The Scrum Master and Product Owner",
            "E": "The Developers and Scrum Master"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "The Developers",
        "explanation": "Only the people doing the work described on the Sprint Backlog need to inspect and adapt at the Daily Scrum. If the Product Owner or Scrum Master are actively working on items in the Sprint Backlog. they participate as Developers, they will need to be at the Daily Scrum."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Product Owner can also be a Developer.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "According to the Scrum Guide, one person can have more than one accountabilities. It's not recommended, but it's not forbidden either. It is acceptable because some of the small projects may need to use a few people to do multiple things, but they have to make sure that they are paying attention to all responsibilities that they have for each accountability."
    },
    {
        "question": "Select the Scrum Pillars.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Simplicity, Communication, Feedback, Respect, Courage",
            "B": "Individuals and Iteration, Working Software, Customer Collaboration, Responding to Change",
            "C": "Transparency, Inspection, Adaptation",
            "D": "Commitment, Courage, Focus, Openness, Respect"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Transparency, Inspection, Adaptation",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Theory Pillars named in the Scrum guide are Transparency, Inspection, Adaptation. The Scrum values are Commitment, Courage, Focus, Openness, Respect."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Developers should not be interrupted during the Sprint and the Sprint Goal should remain intact. These are conditions that foster creativity, quality and productivity. (Which one of the following answers is FALSE?)",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Developers may work with the Product Owner to remove or add work if it finds it has more or less capacity than it expected",
            "B": "As a decomposition of the selected Product Backlog items, the Sprint Backlog changes and may grow as the work emerges",
            "C": "The Sprint Backlog is fully formulated in the Sprint  Planning event and does not change during the Sprint",
            "D": "The Product Owner can help clarify or optimize the Sprint when asked by the Developers"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The Sprint Backlog is fully formulated in the Sprint  Planning event and does not change during the Sprint",
        "explanation": "The Sprint Backlog makes visible all of the work that the Developers identify as necessary to meet the Sprint Goal. The Developers modify the Sprint Backlog throughout the Sprint, and the Sprint Backlog emerges during the Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Developers should have all the skills needed to:",
        "options": {
            "A": "Do all of the development work, except for specialized testing that requires additional tools and environments",
            "B": "Turn the Product Backlog items they select into an Increment of useful and valuable product functionality",
            "C": "Complete the project as estimated when the date and cost are committed to the Product Owner"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Turn the Product Backlog items they select into an Increment of useful and valuable product functionality",
        "explanation": "The Developers are a group of professionals who do the work of delivering an Increment of done product at the end of each Sprint. As a team. Developers have all of the skills necessary to create a product Increment."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False: Scrum has a role called \"project manager.\"",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "A Scrum Team has a Scrum Master, a Product Owner and Developers. As a whole they have all controls needed."
    },
    {
        "question": "When should the Developers on a Scrum Team be replaced?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Every Sprint to promote shared learning",
            "B": "As needed, with no special allowance for changes in productivity",
            "C": "Never, it reduces productivity",
            "D": "As needed, while taking into account a short-term reduction in productivity"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "As needed, while taking into account a short-term reduction in productivity",
        "explanation": "Scrum Teams typically go through some steps before achieving a state of increased performance. Changing membership typically reduces cohesion, affecting performance and productivity in the short term."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the recommended size for a Scrum Team?",
        "options": {
            "A": "9",
            "B": "Minimum of 7",
            "C": "7 plus or minus 2",
            "D": "Typically 10 or fewer people"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Typically 10 or fewer people",
        "explanation": "A Scrum Team is small enough to remain nimble and large enough to complete significant work within a Sprint, typically 10 or fewer people. Generally smaller teams communicate better and are more productive"
    },
    {
        "question": "The timebox for the Sprint Planning event is?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Whenever it is done",
            "B": "4 hours",
            "C": "Monthly",
            "D": "8 hours for a monthly Sprint For shorter Sprints it is usually shorter"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "8 hours for a monthly Sprint For shorter Sprints it is usually shorter",
        "explanation": "Sprint Planning is timeboxed to a maximum of eight hours for a one-month Sprint. For shorter Sprints, the event is usually shorter."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Once the Sprint starts, the length shouldn't change.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "Once the Sprint starts, its duration is fixed and cannot change."
    },
    {
        "question": "The CEO asks the Developers to add a “very important” item to a Sprint that is in progress. What should the Developers do?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Inform the other members of the Scrum Team so the team can decide what to do",
            "B": "Add the item to the next Sprint",
            "C": "Add the item to the current Sprint and drop an item of equal size",
            "D": "Add the item to the current Sprint without any adjustments"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Inform the other members of the Scrum Team so the team can decide what to do",
        "explanation": "The items selected for a Sprint have been selected as most valuable with the Product Owner. The items serve the Sprint's goal. No changes should be made that endanger the Sprint Goal. No one external to the Scrum Team can force changes on the Developers."
    },
    {
        "question": "How much work must the Developers complete for each Product Backlog item they select for a Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "All development work and at least some testing",
            "B": "Analysis, design, programming, testing and documentation",
            "C": "Enough so that each Product Backlog item they select meets the Definition of Done",
            "D": "As much as it can fit into the Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Enough so that each Product Backlog item they select meets the Definition of Done",
        "explanation": "The purpose of each Sprint is to deliver useful and valuable Increments that adhere to the Scrum Team's current Definition of Done."
    },
    {
        "question": "During a Sprint, a Developer determines that the Scrum Team will not be able to complete the items in their forecast. Who should be present to review and adjust the Product Backlog items selected?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Product Owner and all stakeholders",
            "B": "The Scrum Master, the project manager, and the Developers",
            "C": "The Product Owner and the Developers",
            "D": "The Developers"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Owner and the Developers",
        "explanation": "During the Sprint. scope may be clarified and re-negotiated between the Product Owner and the Developers as more is learned. It is important to be transparent when challenges arise since ultimately the entire Scrum Team is accountable for creating a valuable, useful Increment."
    },
    {
        "question": "What are two ways a Scrum Master serves to enable effective Scrum Teams?",
        "options": {
            "A": "By removing impediments that hinder the Scrum Team",
            "B": "By keeping high value features high in the Product Backlog",
            "C": "By starting and ending the meetings at the proper time",
            "D": "By facilitating Developer decision-making"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "By removing impediments that hinder the Scrum Team and By facilitating Developer decision-making",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Master serves the Scrum Team in several ways. Facilitation and removing impediments are examples of ways a Scrum Master helps a team become more effective."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. It's required to use Story Points in Scrum.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "It's a good idea to use Story Points to estimate the Product Backlog items, but it's not mandatory in Scrum."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following apse might help the Product Owner minimize waste in developing and sustaining the Product Backlog?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Only fully describe Product Backlog items when it seems likely they will be implemented",
            "B": "Write every  Product Backlog item clearly and with no ambiguity",
            "C": "Hand off ownership of the Product Backlog to someone else",
            "D": "Remove items from the Product Backlog that have not been addressed in a long time"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Only fully describe Product Backlog items when it seems likely they will be implemented and Write every  Product Backlog item clearly and with no ambiguity",
        "explanation": "Hand off ownership of the Product Backlog to someone else, Remove items from the Product Backlog that have not been addressed in a long time are simply not an option and incorrect in scrum framework."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. When multiple teams are working on the same product, their Sprints should start and end at the same time.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "FALSE, it's not mandatory to start and end the Sprints at the same time; e.g., most teams have four-week Sprints, but some of them have two-week Sprints."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct about non-functional requirements?",
        "options": {
            "A": "They will be in the Sprint Backlog, but not the Product Backlog",
            "B": "They should be incorporated into every increment",
            "C": "They will be considered in Integration Sprints",
            "D": "Some of them can be added to the Definition of Done",
            "E": "They can be incorporated right before the release about functional requirements"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "B",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "They will be in the Sprint Backlog, but not the Product Backlog and They should be incorporated into every increment and Some of them can be added to the Definition of Done",
        "explanation": "There is no separate Integration sprint in Scrum and functional requirements are not released separately."
    },
    {
        "question": "From the following answers, how should developers deal with system, security or non-functional features?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Incorporate them in the hardening Sprint",
            "B": "Incorporate them into every Increment",
            "C": "Incorporate them before the release",
            "D": "Incorporate them in the integration Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Incorporate them into every Increment",
        "explanation": "Non-functional features are usually part of the Definition of Done and should be considered for every Product Backlog item and every Increment. Sometimes, some non-functional features that address a very particular part of the software can be added as separate items in the Product Backlog. All Sprints are the same. There's no Sprint zero, hardening Sprint, release Sprint, integration Sprint, etc."
    },
    {
        "question": "Developers are free to change their engineering and testing practices whenever they want?",
        "options": {
            "A": "False",
            "B": "True"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "Developers decide how to handle their development, and this decision can evolve during the project, as more is learned about the needs. This is about their development and doesn't have to be constrained by the Sprints. The elements that shouldn't be changed during the Sprint are those required for keeping them focused on their development."
    },
    {
        "question": "From the following answers, choose one which is not a prioritization technique?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Choose only ONE best answer",
            "B": "Kano analysis",
            "C": "Product Backlog ordering",
            "D": "Planning Poker",
            "E": "User Story Mapping"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Product Backlog ordering",
        "explanation": "Planning poker, also called Scrum poker, is a consensus-based, gamified technique for estimating, mostly used to estimate the effort or relative size of development goals in software development. In planning poker, members of the group make estimates by placing numbered cards face-down on the table, instead of saying them aloud. The cards are revealed, and the estimates are then discussed. By hiding the figures in this way, the group can avoid the cognitive bias of anchoring, where the first number spoken aloud sets a precedent for subsequent estimates. Planning Poker is not a prioritization technique"
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. After Scrum implementation, the Scrum Team ensures the exception of technical debt.",
        "options": {
            "A": "False",
            "B": "True"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Scrum cannot ensure the exception of technical debt."
    },
    {
        "question": "According to the Scrum Guide, the Scrum is based on: (Select all correct answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Self-organizing",
            "B": "Lean thinking",
            "C": "Transparent",
            "D": "Empirical",
            "E": "Complex"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Lean thinking and Empirical",
        "explanation": "Scrum is founded on empirical process control theory or empiricism and lean thinking. Empiricism asserts that knowledge comes from experience and making decisions based on what is known. Scrum employs an iterative, incremental approach to optimize predictability and control risk. Lean thinking reduces waste and focuses on the essentials."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who should know the most about the release and product requirements in Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Team Leader",
            "B": "The Scrum Master",
            "C": "The Product Owner",
            "D": "The Project Manager",
            "E": "The Product Leader"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Owner",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is responsible for the product, including decisions about release. The Product Owner's decisions are visible in the content and ordering of the Product Backlog. No one can force Developers to work from a different set of requirements."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Scrum is a software development methodology.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Choose only ONE best answer",
            "B": "True",
            "C": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "Scrum is a process framework that has been used to manage work on complex products since the early 1990s. Scrum is not a process, technique, or definitive method. Rather, it is a framework within which you can employ various processes and techniques. Scrum makes clear the relative efficacy of your product management and work techniques so that you can continuously improve the product, the team, and the working environment."
    },
    {
        "question": "Choose one best answer. Scrum is _____________ .",
        "options": {
            "A": "not founded on empiricism",
            "B": "not a software development process",
            "C": "not founded on lean thinking",
            "D": "not a framework"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Choose one best answer. Scrum is not a software development process",
        "explanation": "Scrum is not a software development process"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is not a pillar of Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Adaptation",
            "B": "Inspection",
            "C": "Empiricism",
            "D": "Transparency"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "B",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Adaptation and Inspection and Transparency",
        "explanation": "Three pillars uphold every implementation of empirical process control: transparency, inspection, and adaptation."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Team may decrease the technical debt by _________________.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Choose only one best answer",
            "B": "Hiring an external auditor",
            "C": "Improving the definition of ‘tone”",
            "D": "Having hardening Sprints",
            "E": "Hiring more Developers"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "The Team may decrease the technical debt by Hiring an external auditor",
        "explanation": "There’s usually room for improving the definition of “Done”. A good definition will let less technical debt pass on to the next Sprints. Technical debt is minor shortcomings in the code\n\nthat makes it less than “good enough”, and therefore creates risks in the future. It usually\n\ndecreases velocity in the future (because the team has to fix the shortcomings), and as some\n\nif the debt might remain in the final product, the maintenance cost will increase as well.\n\nAnother Agile way of reducing technical debt is continuous refactoring."
    },
    {
        "question": "The benefits of having a solid product vision are:",
        "options": {
            "A": "Choose all answers that apply",
            "B": "It gives an overall direction to the Sprints",
            "C": "It helps identify the best time for releasing the product",
            "D": "It’s a traditional concept and there are no benefits for it",
            "E": "It makes it easier to inspect the incremental progress of  the product",
            "F": "It helps the team stay focused and make better decisions"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "D",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Choose all answers that apply and It’s a traditional concept and there are no benefits for it and It makes it easier to inspect the incremental progress of  the product",
        "explanation": "Product vision is not explained in the Scrum Guide and is not a mandatory part of the framework. However, it’s recommended to have one, and use it to help align the decisions and development with the expected outcome of the project"
    },
    {
        "question": "?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Choose only one best answer",
            "B": "The process should be visible and understood by each stakeholder",
            "C": "The whole process should be visible to the Product Owner",
            "D": "Significant aspects of the process must be visible to those performing the work as well as those receiving the work",
            "E": "The whole process should be visible to stakeholders"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "From the following answers choose one. In Scrum, by transparency we mean The whole process should be visible to the Product Owner",
        "explanation": "Transparency is about visibility and doesn’t contain understanding; even though we’d better try our best to create the right understanding too, but that’s another story. The “whole process” might be too much for some stakeholders; “significant aspects” is enough, as we treat most things in Agile environments."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is correct about the Scrum Team?",
        "options": {
            "A": "All answers apply",
            "B": "The Scrum Team engages the stakeholders",
            "C": "Is responsible for maximizing the value of the product",
            "D": "The Scrum Team is responsible for measuring the performance of the project",
            "E": "None of the answers apply",
            "F": "The Scrum Team is cross-functional"
        },
        "answer": [
            "F"
        ],
        "answers": "The Scrum Team is cross-functional",
        "explanation": "The whole Scrum Team is self-managed and cross-functional, as stated in the Scrum Guide. The Product Owners measure the performance of the project to maximize the value of the product that is developed."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who creates a Sprint Goal?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Scrum Master",
            "B": "Developer",
            "C": "Scrum team",
            "D": "Product Owner"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Scrum team",
        "explanation": "The Sprint Goal is the single objective for the Sprint. Although the Sprint Goal is a commitment by the Developers, it provides flexibility in terms of the exact work needed to achieve it. The Sprint Goat also creates coherence and focus, encouraging the Scrum Team to work together rather than on separate initiatives. The whole Scrum Team collaborates at Sprint Planning events to define a Sprint Goal that communicates why the Sprint is valuable to stakeholders."
    },
    {
        "question": "How would the Product Backlog be impacted by the changes in the environment in which the product will be used?",
        "options": {
            "A": "It evolves to reflect the changes",
            "B": "The Product Backlog should be kept high-level enough to tolerate such changes",
            "C": "It is required to complete the old Product Backlog and create a new Product Backlog",
            "D": "There’s no effect on the Product Backlog",
            "E": "It is required to complete the old Product Backlog and create a new Product",
            "F": "Backlog"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "It evolves to reflect the changes",
        "explanation": "A Product Backlog is never complete. The earliest development of it lays out the initially\n\nknown and best-understood requirements. The Product Backlog evolves as the product and\n\nthe environment in which it will be used evolves"
    },
    {
        "question": "A company has three products. Which two of the following are an acceptable way of forming Scrum teams?",
        "options": {
            "A": "There must be one Product Owner for each product. It is not required to have one Product Owner for two and more teams",
            "B": "There can be one Product Owner for each product",
            "C": "There can be a single Product Owner for all products",
            "D": "There must be a single Product Owner for all products"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "There can be one Product Owner for each product and There can be a single Product Owner for all products",
        "explanation": "Maximum number of product owners for a team is 1. The minimum number of product owners for all scrum teams is also 1."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. According to the new version of the Scrum Guide, Scrum Teams are self-managing, meaning they internally decide who does what, when, and how. It means that Scrum Teams are not self- organizing.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Self-management is the minimum bar. Scrum Teams can still be self-organizing, self- designing, or even self-governing if the situation allows, and supporting such constructs can provide immense benefit. Remember, Scrum is a framework. It gives the scaffolding for people, teams, and organizations to generate value through adaptive solutions to complex problems. The Scrum Guide only states what is required for Scrum, and ideally, nothing else."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which Scrum event or artifact supports daily inspection and adaptation?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Sprint Backlog",
            "B": "Daily Scrum",
            "C": "Sprint",
            "D": "Product Backlog"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Daily Scrum",
        "explanation": "There is only one daily activity (event) is scrum: Daily Scrum"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Increment is the summation of overall backlog items finished during the Sprint and also the previous completed Sprints. But when should the Increment be shipped?",
        "options": {
            "A": "When it makes sense",
            "B": "After each Sprint",
            "C": "When the Increment is free of defects",
            "D": "When the Increment is shippable"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "When it makes sense",
        "explanation": "All Increments should be potentially releasable (shippable), but we don't have to release all of them. It depends on the project environment and the customer, and the Product Owner is supposed to decide on it"
    },
    {
        "question": "Technical debt leads to ______________?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Projects that are over-budget",
            "B": "Products that are difficult to extend and maintain",
            "C": "Processes that lack tools",
            "D": "Nowhere"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Technical debt leads to Products that are difficult to extend and maintain",
        "explanation": "Technical debt refers to quality consequences by the poor technical choices made"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does the Burn-down Chart show?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The evolution of the amount of uncertainty during a project",
            "B": "How much work remains until the end of the Sprint",
            "C": "Dependencies, start times and stop times for project tasks",
            "D": "An overview of the release progress by plotting the remaining workload"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "How much work remains until the end of the Sprint",
        "explanation": "The burn-down chart is a graphical representation of work left to do versus time. The outstanding work (or backlog) is often on the vertical axis, with time along the horizontal. That is, it is a run chart of outstanding work. It is useful for predicting when all of the work will be completed. However burn-down charts are not mandatory in Scrum"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is unrealized value in Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The organization's ability to quickly deliver new capabilities, services, or products",
            "B": "The value that the product delivers",
            "C": "The potential future value that could be realized if the organization met the needs of all potential customers or users"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The potential future value that could be realized if the organization met the needs of all potential customers or users",
        "explanation": "The potential future value that could be realized if the organization met the needs of all potential customers or users. Looking at Unrealized Value helps an organization to maximize the value that it realizes from a product or service over time. When customers, users, or clients experience a gap between their current experience and the experience that they would like to have, the difference between the two represents an opportunity; this opportunity is measured by Unrealized Value."
    },
    {
        "question": "Some of the Sprint Backlog items were not completed and some were completed during the Sprint. What should happen with completed items when the Sprint is canceled?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Such items will be reviewed, and if they are potentially releasable, the Product Owner typically accepts them",
            "B": "Such items should be moved back to the Product Backlog and would be taken care of in future Sprints",
            "C": "Such items should be moved to the next Sprint Backlog"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Such items will be reviewed, and if they are potentially releasable, the Product Owner typically accepts them",
        "explanation": "When a Sprint is canceled, any completed and \"Done\" Product Backlog items are reviewed. if part of the work is potentially releasable, the Product Owner typically accepts it. All incomplete Product Backlog items are re-estimated and put back on the Product Backlog. The work done on them depreciates quickly and must be frequently re-estimated."
    },
    {
        "question": "From the following statements choose one or more correct answers about the Daily Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Daily Scrum is time-boxed",
            "B": "Only Developers participate at this event",
            "C": "The Product Owner must provide updates to Developers at the Daily Scrum",
            "D": "The Scrum Master makes a report to the Product Owner"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "The Daily Scrum is time-boxed and Only Developers participate at this event",
        "explanation": "The Daily Scrum is a 15-minute time-boxed event for Developers. The Daily Scrum is held every day of the Sprint. At this event, Developers plan activities for the next 24 hours."
    },
    {
        "question": "What should the Product Owner do during the Sprint zero?",
        "options": {
            "A": "There’s no such event in Scrum as Sprint Zero",
            "B": "Prepare the Product Backlog for the whole project",
            "C": "Communicate with the customer and understand the requirements",
            "D": "Prepare the Product Backlog for the next few Sprints"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "There’s no such event in Scrum as Sprint Zero",
        "explanation": "There's no such event in Scrum as Sprint Zero"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are ways for stakeholders to interact with Developers? (select all correct answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "At the Sprint Planning",
            "B": "Via the Product Owner",
            "C": "At the Sprint Review",
            "D": "At the Daily Scrums",
            "E": "At the Sprint Retrospective"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Via the Product Owner and At the Sprint Review",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is one person, not a committee. The Product Owner may represent the desires of a committee in the Product Backlog, but those wanting to change a Product Backlog item's priority must address the Product Owner. During the Sprint Review, the Scrum Team and stakeholders collaborate about what was done in the Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "A new Increment of working software must be available __________________",
        "options": {
            "A": "Choose only one best answer",
            "B": "Before each planned release",
            "C": "At the end of each Sprint",
            "D": "Every 3 Sprints",
            "E": "Whenever the user acceptance testing is done",
            "F": "When the Product Owner asks for it"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "A new Increment of working software must be available Before each planned release",
        "explanation": "An Increment is a concrete stepping stone toward the Product Goal. Each Increment is additive to all prior Increments and thoroughly verified, ensuring that all Increments work together. In order to provide value, the Increment must be usable. At the end of a Sprint, the new Increment must be \"Done,\" which means it must be in usable condition and meet the Scrum Team's definition of \"Done\"."
    },
    {
        "question": "How much of the Sprint Backlog should be defined during the Sprint Planning meeting?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Choose only one best answer",
            "B": "Just enough, so Developers can forecast what it can do, and start the first several days of the Sprint",
            "C": "Just enough to understand design and architecture",
            "D": "During the Sprint Planning event, the Scrum Team selects all of the potential work",
            "E": "Just enough for the Scrum Master to be able to assign tasks to Developers The Product Owner decides it"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Choose only one best answer",
        "explanation": "The Sprint Backlog includes the items selected from the Product Backlog and the tasks created by decomposing the items. The items are completely planned in the Sprint Planning, but not all tasks are created; just enough for the first few days of development. The rest of the tasks will be created during the Sprint"
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Each Developer in the Scrum Team must be cross-functional.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "According to the Scrum Guide, Scrum Teams are cross-functional, meaning the members have all the skills necessary to create value for each Sprint. They are also self-managing, meaning they internally decide who does what, when, and how. It means they must be cross-functional as a team, but not individually"
    },
    {
        "question": "How much time should a Product Owner spend with Developers?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Choose only one best answer",
            "B": "100% of the time",
            "C": "As much as required by senior stakeholders",
            "D": "The Scrum Master defines the required time for the Product Owner to spend with Developers",
            "E": "As much as needed to maximize the value of the product"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "The Scrum Master defines the required time for the Product Owner to spend with Developers",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner needs to spend as much time with Developers as needed to make an increment"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are not mandatory in the Scrum Guide? Select all correct answers.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Having potentially releasable Increments",
            "B": "Velocity",
            "C": "Release plan",
            "D": "Product Goal",
            "E": "Product Backlog"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Velocity and Release plan",
        "explanation": "Velocity and Release Plan are not mandatory in Scrum"
    },
    {
        "question": "This Scrum event is for process improvement and the purpose of this event is to plan ways to increase quality and effectiveness?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Sprint Planning",
            "B": "Sprint Retrospective",
            "C": "Daily Scrum",
            "D": "Sprint Review"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Sprint Retrospective",
        "explanation": "The purpose of the Sprint Retrospective is to: Inspect how the last Sprint went with regards to people, relationships, process, and tools; Identify and order the major items that went well and potential improvements; and, Create a plan for implementing improvements to the way the Scrum Team does its work."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is the single source of requirements for all changes to the product?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Increment",
            "B": "The Sprint Retrospective",
            "C": "The Product Backlog",
            "D": "The Sprint Backlog",
            "E": "The product vision"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Backlog",
        "explanation": "The Product Backlog is an ordered list of everything that is known to be needed in the product. It is the single source of requirements for any changes to be made to the product. The Product Owner is responsible for the Product Backlog, including its content, availability, and ordering."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Scrum Team has just begun the Sprint Planning meeting. There are a lot of questions about the Product Backlog and in general, the Product Backlog is not clear. Due to this, what is the maximum duration of Sprint Planning?",
        "options": {
            "A": "12 hours",
            "B": "2 hours",
            "C": "8 hours",
            "D": "6 hours",
            "E": "In this case, the duration can be even more than one day"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "8 hours",
        "explanation": "Sprint Planning is time-boxed to a maximum of eight hours for a one-month Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Product Backlog Refinement is not a mandatory but very common and useful event in Scrum. When should the Product Backlog items be refined? Select all correct answers.",
        "options": {
            "A": "In so-called Sprint zero",
            "B": "During the current Sprint if they have not been refined in the previous Sprints",
            "C": "In one or two preceding Sprints",
            "D": "Only in the time between the two Sprints"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "During the current Sprint if they have not been refined in the previous Sprints and In one or two preceding Sprints",
        "explanation": "There is no Sprint 0. Also, new Sprint starts immediately after the previous"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are good ways for a Scrum Team to ensure security concerns are satisfied? Select all correct answers.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Add a Sprint to specifically resolve all security concerns",
            "B": "Postpone the work until a specialist can perform a security audit and create a list of security-related Product Backlog items",
            "C": "Delegate the work to the concerned department",
            "D": "Add security concerns to the definition of “Done”",
            "E": "Have the Scrum Team create Product Backlog items for each concern"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Add security concerns to the definition of “Done” and Have the Scrum Team create Product Backlog items for each concern",
        "explanation": "Many of the security concerns are non-functional features and therefore will be added to the Definition of Done to be applied to all Product Backlog items. Some security concerns are specific and only about a certain part of the product and they can be items in the Product Backlog."
    },
    {
        "question": "Developers are the people in the Scrum Team that are committed to creating any aspect of a usable Increment in each Sprint. Which of the following answers are the responsibilities of Developers in Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Pulling Product Backlog items for the upcoming Sprint",
            "B": "Creating new Product Backlog items",
            "C": "Estimating Sprint Backlog items",
            "D": "Creating tasks for Sprint Backlog items",
            "E": "Reordering the Product Backlog"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Pulling Product Backlog items for the upcoming Sprint and Estimating Sprint Backlog items and Creating tasks for Sprint Backlog items",
        "explanation": "According to the Scrum Guide, the specific skills needed by the Developers are often broad and will vary with the domain of work. However, the Developers are always accountable for:\n\n●      Creating a plan for the Sprint, the Sprint Backlog;\n\n●      instilling quality by adhering to a Definition of Done;\n\n●      Adapting their plan each day toward the Sprint Goal;\n\n●      Holding each other accountable as professionals."
    },
    {
        "question": "When does Cross-Team Refinement occur in Scaled Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Before the Sprint Planning",
            "B": "After the Scaled Scrum Sprint Review",
            "C": "There is no specific time during the Sprint for Cross Team Refinement",
            "D": "After the Scaled Scrum Sprint Planning"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "There is no specific time during the Sprint for Cross Team Refinement",
        "explanation": "There is no specific time during the Sprint when teams work on Refinement."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the time box for the Cross-Team Refinement meeting in Scaled Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Choose only one best answer",
            "B": "max 4 hours",
            "C": "max 8 hours",
            "D": "max 6 hours",
            "E": "There is no specific Time Box"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "max 6 hours",
        "explanation": "There is no specific time box for Cross-Team Refinement, nor is there a specific time during the Sprint when teams work on Refinement."
    },
    {
        "question": "Representatives from the Scrum Teams meet once again to discuss common issues identified in the Scrum Team Retrospectives. They agree on how to visualize and track the identified actions that will enable Scaled Scrum to learn and adapt as a whole. What part of the Scaled Scrum Sprint Retrospective is it?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Choose only one best answer",
            "B": "1",
            "C": "2",
            "D": "3",
            "E": "The process doesn’t relate to the Scaled Scrum Sprint Retrospective"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "3",
        "explanation": "There are no mandatory requirements for teams in Scaled Scrum to divide Sprint Retrospective events into 2 or more parts. It is up to the Scaled Scrum Integration Team"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the maximum number of members in the Scaled Scrum Integration Team?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Choose only one best answer",
            "B": "3 to 9",
            "C": "15",
            "D": "5 to 11",
            "E": "As many as required to develop and integrate the best solution for the product"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "5 to 11",
        "explanation": "There is no direct restriction on a number of staff in the Scaled Scrum Integration Team. Usually, there are 5-8 members but it is not mandatory"
    },
    {
        "question": "How many Product Backlogs are used in Scaled Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The number of Backlogs is equal to the number of Scrum Team in Scaled Scrum",
            "B": "One Product Backlog for the entire product",
            "C": "2 Product Backlogs (one for Scaled Scrum Team and one for all other teams)",
            "D": "None"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "One Product Backlog for the entire product",
        "explanation": "There is a single Product Backlog for the entire Scaled Scrum and all of its Scrum Teams. The Product Owner is accountable for the Product Backlog, including its content, availability, and ordering."
    },
    {
        "question": "Transitioning from Waterfall to Scrum is a very significant step for the organization. How will the organization measure the success of Scrum implementation?",
        "options": {
            "A": "By reducing costs",
            "B": "By increasing customer satisfaction",
            "C": "By delivering an increment every Sprint",
            "D": "Through frequent releases and meeting value metrics or KPIs",
            "E": "By releasing new features after each Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "By increasing customer satisfaction and Through frequent releases and meeting value metrics or KPIs",
        "explanation": "Customer and end user's satisfaction is important. It's not an abstract measure like lines of code or velocity. There can be some KPIs for measuring the value of the releases, and when improved, will show our success. Increased velocity is desired, but it's not directly connected to value and can be misleading. That's the same with production cost. It's mandatory to deliver an Increment every Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "As a Product Owner, you are responsible for stakeholder management. From the following answers choose the correct statement about the relationship between PO and the stakeholder.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Choose only one best answer",
            "B": "The stakeholder is a manager of the Product Owner and he or she creates task for the Product Backlog",
            "C": "Stakeholders are always users of the product and they can’t advise anything to the PO",
            "D": "The Product Owner represents the stakeholders to the Scrum Team, which includes representing their desired requirements in the Product Backlog",
            "E": "One of the stakeholders must be the Scrum Master"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Stakeholders are always users of the product and they can’t advise anything to the PO",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is the bridge between the team and the stakeholders. The Product Owner actively asks for stakeholder expectations to process into the Product Backlog."
    },
    {
        "question": "Every Scrum team must determine its own cadence for releasing features to customers. Some choose to release every sprint, while others after 2, 3 and even more Sprints. But who is responsible for planning releases?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Developers",
            "B": "Scrum Master",
            "C": "Product Owner",
            "D": "Project manager"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Product Owner",
        "explanation": "Release Planning is the Responsibility of the Product Owner."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Product Owner ensures enough items are selected from the Product Backlog in the Sprint Planning meeting to satisfy the stakeholders.",
        "options": {
            "A": "False",
            "B": "True"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "It's only up to the developers to decide how many items they will select from the top of the Product Backlog. The Product Owner only orders the items."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Product Owner decides not to create a Product Goal. In this case (select all correct answers).",
        "options": {
            "A": "It is up to the Product Owner",
            "B": "Changing the core design or ideas of Scrum, leaving out elements, or not following the rules of Scrum, covers up problems and limits the benefits of Scrum, potentially even rendering it useless",
            "C": "The Scrum Master is helping find techniques for effective Product Goal definition and Product Backlog management",
            "D": "The Product Owner must discuss with Developers and if they are ok with it, then he or she may remove the Product Goal"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Changing the core design or ideas of Scrum, leaving out elements, or not following the rules of Scrum, covers up problems and limits the benefits of Scrum, potentially even rendering it useless and The Scrum Master is helping find techniques for effective Product Goal definition and Product Backlog management",
        "explanation": "As we know from the Scrum Guide while implementing only parts of Scrum is possible (by removing the Product Goal), the result is not Scrum. Scrum exists only in its entirety and functions well as a container for other techniques, methodologies, and practices. In this case, the best action from the Scrum Master to discuss it with the Product Owner and find techniques for effective Product Goal definition"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is the chief product visionary?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Scrum Master",
            "B": "The Chief Executive Officer (CEO)",
            "C": "The Chief Marketing Officer (CMO)",
            "D": "The Product Owner",
            "E": "The manager of the team"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Owner",
        "explanation": "One of the product owner's responsibilities is to have a vision of what he or she wishes to build and convey that vision to the scrum team. This is key to successfully starting any agile software development"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who creates the Sprint Goal?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Scrum Master",
            "B": "Developers",
            "C": "The Scrum Team",
            "D": "The Product Owner"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The Scrum Team",
        "explanation": "The Sprint Goal is the single objective for the Sprint. Although the Sprint Goal is a commitment by the Developers, it provides flexibility in terms of the exact work needed to achieve it. The Sprint Goal also creates coherence and focus, encouraging the Scrum Team to work together rather than on separate initiatives. The whole Scrum Team collaborates at Sprint Planning events to define a Sprint Goal that communicates why the Sprint is valuable to stakeholders."
    },
    {
        "question": "During the Daily Scrum, a team member says he does not know when his task will be complete",
        "options": {
            "A": "It is acceptable as the sprint review date is far away",
            "B": "Replace the team member with a new team member",
            "C": "Developers should collaborate to plan alternative steps such as pairing with someone else, etc to eliminate the  risk of not meeting the Sprint Goal",
            "D": "Scrum Master should mentor the team member on how to test. the task"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Developers should collaborate to plan alternative steps such as pairing with someone else, etc to eliminate the  risk of not meeting the Sprint Goal",
        "explanation": "Scrum Teams are self-managing and cross-functional. Self-managing teams choose how best to accomplish their work, rather than being directed by others outside the team. Cross-functional teams have all competencies needed to accomplish the work without depending on others not part of the team. So the dev team should collaborate to plan alternative steps such as pairing with someone else, etc. to eliminate the risk of not meeting the Sprint Goal."
    },
    {
        "question": "In the middle of the Sprint, Developers find that they have more room for additional work. They decided to change the Sprint Backlog by adding a few more backlog items from the Product Backlog. Who should be present to decide the additional work and accordingly modify the Sprint Backlog?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Senior members of developers",
            "B": "Scrum Master",
            "C": "Developers",
            "D": "Product Owner",
            "E": "Scrum Team"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Developers and Product Owner",
        "explanation": "Nobody can change the Sprint Backlog other than developers. So Developers should be present. Product Owner is responsible for optimizing the value of developers' work and is needed to explain the content of the Product Backlog, and give mutual consent on the next work. Product Owner is accountable for Product Backlog and prioritizing product backlog items. So the Product Owner also needs to be present."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Product Owner should communicate all of the marketplace knowledge & ever-changing landscape/environment to the Scrum Team. Who should do the preliminary work of gathering the marketplace data for the Product Owner?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Scrum  Master",
            "B": "It does not matter who does the preliminary work",
            "C": "The Key Stakeholders",
            "D": "The Product Owner"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "It does not matter who does the preliminary work",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner may or may not be the one doing the legwork of gathering the marketplace data, he/she may delegate the responsibility to others but the Product Owner should definitely be aware of said data/research."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is \"Progressive Elaboration\"?",
        "options": {
            "A": "In the pre-project stage. it is the act of working to understand requirements of the product",
            "B": "The act of waiting for details to randomly emerge and completing the tasks once that occurs",
            "C": "Shu-Ha-Ri is in the Shu stage when one is just beginning to learn something new; over time they progressively learn and understand more",
            "D": "As the project progresses, details will emerge in greater and greater clarity until they are able to be understood to a sufficient level to complete the needed work"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "As the project progresses, details will emerge in greater and greater clarity until they are able to be understood to a sufficient level to complete the needed work",
        "explanation": "As the project progresses, details will emerge in greater and greater clarity until they are able to be understood to a sufficient level to complete the needed work"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement can be considered an Increment?",
        "options": {
            "A": "A UML diagram that describes the functionalities in the future Sprints",
            "B": "A user interface layout designed for the software",
            "C": "The sum of all the Product Backlog items completed during the Sprint and the value of the increments of all  previous Sprints",
            "D": "The sum of all the Product Backlog items completed during the Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The sum of all the Product Backlog items completed during the Sprint and the value of the increments of all  previous Sprints",
        "explanation": "An Increment is a concrete stepping stone toward the Product Goal. Each Increment is additive to all prior Increments and thoroughly verified, ensuring that all Increments work together. In order to provide value, the Increment must be usable.\n\n\n\nThe user interface layout/UML diagram evolves throughout the project, as the database architecture and other similar things. They are all part of functional features, rather than separate ones. The increment is current and additive to all prior Increments."
    },
    {
        "question": "Non-functional requirements of the product such as performance, security, etc., can be captured by:",
        "options": {
            "A": "Writing a separate document capturing the requirements and adding as appendix to Product Backlog",
            "B": "Adding them to the Product Backlog with Product Owners  consent and collaborating to estimate and order them",
            "C": "Adding them to the Definition of “Done” and making the  Product Owner aware of them",
            "D": "Waiting until the decision of the Product Owner to release the Increment. Then, build the non-functional requirements for stabilization"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Adding them to the Product Backlog with Product Owners  consent and collaborating to estimate and order them and Adding them to the Definition of “Done” and making the  Product Owner aware of them",
        "explanation": "Adding them to Product Backlog with Product Owner's consent and collaborating to estimate and order them & Adding them to Definition of \"Done\" and make the Product Owner aware of them."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Product Backlog is an emergent, ordered list of what is needed to improve the product. Which of the following statements are related to Product Backlog Refinement.",
        "options": {
            "A": "It guides the team on how & what work needs be to delivered to build a potentially shippable Increment",
            "B": "It is an ongoing process",
            "C": "Is time-boxed to a maximum of 4 hours for a 30 days sprint",
            "D": "It adds details, estimates, and order as per product Owner prioritization to Product Backlog items",
            "E": "The Product Owner may delegate this responsibility to others but he/she still remains accountable",
            "F": "It provides a formal description of the state of the Increment when it meets the quality measures required for the product"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "D",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "It is an ongoing process and It adds details, estimates, and order as per product Owner prioritization to Product Backlog items and The Product Owner may delegate this responsibility to others but he/she still remains accountable",
        "explanation": "Product Backlog refinement is the act of adding detail, estimates, and order to items in the Product Backlog. This is an ongoing process in which the Product Owner and the Developers collaborate on the details of Product Backlog items. It includes:\n\n●      Developing and explicitly communicating the Product Goal;\n\n●      Creating and clearly communicating Product Backlog items;\n\n●      Ordering Product Backlog items; and,\n\n●      Ensuring that the Product Backlog is transparent, visible, and understood.\n\n\n\nThe Product Owner may do the above work or may delegate the responsibility to others. Regardless, the Product Owner remains accountable."
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the important characteristics of a good Product Backlog item which can be considered as \"Ready\" for Sprint Planning?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Product Backlog items which are sufficiently refined & clearly expressed",
            "B": "Product Backlog item which can be developed within one Sprint even if tested in another Sprint",
            "C": "Product Backlog item which will be finished as per Definition of Done within one Sprint",
            "D": "Product Backlog items which are at or towards the bottom of the Product Backlog",
            "E": "Product Backlog item which is at the top of the  Product Backlog"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Product Backlog items which are sufficiently refined & clearly expressed and Product Backlog item which will be finished as per Definition of Done within one Sprint and Product Backlog item which is at the top of the  Product Backlog",
        "explanation": "The Product Backlog is an emergent, ordered list of what is needed to improve the product. It is the single source of work undertaken by the Scrum Team.\n\nProduct Backlog items that will occupy developers for the upcoming Sprint are sufficiently refined so that any one item can reasonably be \"Done\" within the Sprint time-box. Product Backlog items that can be \"Done\" by developers within one Sprint are deemed \"Ready\" for selection in a Sprint Planning.\n\n\n\nHigher ordered Product Backlog items are usually clearer and more detailed than lower ordered ones. More precise estimates are made based on the greater clarity and increased detail; the lower the order, the less detail.\n\n\n\nRest two options are incorrect as Product Backlog items that are at or towards the bottom of the Product Backlog are not clear enough to pick up in a sprint. Development & testing of the product is considered in the same sprint as the team has to deliver a working & usable increment which complies with Definition of Done. Without testing, the team can't consider an increment as done."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes a Product Owner's responsibility?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Keep stakeholders from distracting the Developers",
            "B": "Optimizing the value of the work the Scrum Team does",
            "C": "Managing the project and ensuring that the work meets the commitments to the stakeholders",
            "D": "Directing the Developers"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Optimizing the value of the work the Scrum Team does",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is accountable for maximizing the value of the product and the work of the Scrum Team."
    },
    {
        "question": "When many Scrum Teams are working on a single product, what best describes the Definition of Done?",
        "options": {
            "A": "It depends",
            "B": "Each Scrum Team uses its own, but must make their definition clear to all other teams so the differences are known",
            "C": "All Scrum Teams must have a Definition of Done that makes their combined Increment valuable and useful"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "All Scrum Teams must have a Definition of Done that makes their combined Increment valuable and useful",
        "explanation": "The Increment must be valuable and useful. This means that when many Scrum Teams are working on a single product, they are expected to adhere to a single Definition of Done for the Increment."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Developers should not be interrupted during the Sprint and the Sprint Goal should remain intact. These are conditions that foster creativity, quality and productivity. Which one of the following answers is FALSE?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Developers may work with the Product Owner to remove or add work if it finds it has more or less capacity than it expected",
            "B": "As a decomposition of the selected Product Backlog items, the Sprint Backlog changes and may grow as the work emerges",
            "C": "The Sprint Backlog is fully formulated in the Sprint  Planning event and does not change during the Sprint",
            "D": "The Product Owner can help clarify or optimize the Sprint when asked by the Developers"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The Sprint Backlog is fully formulated in the Sprint  Planning event and does not change during the Sprint",
        "explanation": "The Sprint Backlog makes visible all of the work that the Developers identify as necessary to meet the Sprint Goal. The Developers modify the Sprint Backlog throughout the Sprint, and the Sprint Backlog emerges during the Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "When does a Developer become the sole owner of an item or task on the Sprint Backlog?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Whenever a team member can accommodate more work",
            "B": "During the Daily Scrum",
            "C": "At the Sprint Planning event",
            "D": "Never. All Sprint Backlog items are “owned” by the Developers on the Scrum Team"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Never. All Sprint Backlog items are “owned” by the Developers on the Scrum Team",
        "explanation": "The entire Scrum Team is accountable for creating a valuable, useful Increment every Sprint, and the set of Product Backlog items selected for the Sprint are collectively owned by the Developers. No individual Developer can claim ownership over an item as this would block communication and collaboration. The Sprint Backlog is updated by the Developers throughout the Sprint as more is learned."
    },
    {
        "question": "A Scrum Team consists of the following:",
        "options": {
            "A": "Customers",
            "B": "Developers",
            "C": "Users",
            "D": "Scrum Master",
            "E": "Product Owner"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "D",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Developers and Scrum Master and Product Owner",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Team consists of one Scrum Master, one Product Owner. and Developers."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who should know the most about the progress toward a business objective or a release, and be able to explain the alternatives most clearly?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Developers",
            "B": "The Product Owner",
            "C": "The Scrum Master",
            "D": "The Project Manager"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Owner",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is the sole person responsible for ordering the Product Backlog. Their responsibilities include making the Product Backlog visible, transparent, and clear to all."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best describes transparency?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The process should be visible, and understood by key stakeholders",
            "B": "Significant aspects of the process must be visible to those responsible for the outcome",
            "C": "The whole process should be visible to stakeholders",
            "D": "The whole process should be visible to everyone"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Significant aspects of the process must be visible to those responsible for the outcome",
        "explanation": "Significant aspects means not all the details. Process means the way we work. Those responsible for the outcome means not all people in the world."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Velocity of Scrum Teams should be normalized, so that management can measure and compare their performance.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Progress measurements are done internally, not by external managers. Also, comparing the velocity dependent on estimates of two different teams is never reliable, and it's not productive even if it were reliable. Different Scrum Teams can point differently."
    },
    {
        "question": "How does the Product Owner determine the number of items for the Sprint Backlog?",
        "options": {
            "A": "They don’t do it",
            "B": "Based on velocity",
            "C": "In a way that maximizes the value of the Increment",
            "D": "Based on a combination of velocity and team capacity"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "They don’t do it",
        "explanation": "It's only up to the self-managing Developers to decide how many items they will select for the Sprint Backlog."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are pillars of Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Sustainable pace",
            "B": "Value optimization",
            "C": "Adaptation",
            "D": "Transparency",
            "E": "Inspection"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C",
            "D",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Adaptation and Transparency and Inspection",
        "explanation": "Pillars are transparency, inspection, and adaptation. Make sure you're not confusing these pillars with the Scrum values (commitment, courage, focus, openness, and respect)."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is the least productive way for the Scrum Master to improve the Developers' communications with the Product Owner?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Teach them how to effectively communicate",
            "B": "Monitor their communication performance",
            "C": "Suggest effective communication tools and techniques to the Product Owner",
            "D": "Act as a go-between for them"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Act as a go-between for them",
        "explanation": "Acting as a proxy doesn't work at all. Teaching and monitoring the communication is the right way to fix the problem. Make sure you have noticed the word \"least\"."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The whole Sprint Backlog is defined in the Sprint Planning meeting.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "There are two elements in the Sprint Backlog: items selected from the Product Backlog and tasks created by decomposing those items. Sprint Backlog items could change as more is learnt, so it could change from the Developers."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Sprint Review is an informal meeting.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Guide states the word \"formal\" in two different ways. First, all events are \"formal opportunities\" for inspecting and adapting, which basically means a serious opportunity. So, if the question is \"... is a formal opportunity for...\", it would be a correct statement. The second usage is \"formal meeting\", which means a meeting where people approve something and exchange signatures. In that sense, none of the events are formal meetings. In the Sprint Review meeting, for example, the goal is creating feedback and adapting, not contract negotiations and exchanging signatures. So, if the statement is \"... is a formal meeting\", then it would be an incorrect statement. The Scrum Guide states: \"Events are used in Scrum to create regularity and to minimize the need for meetings not defined in Scrum.\""
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. It's required to use User Stories in Scrum.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "It's a good idea to use User Stories to form the Product Backlog items, but it's not mandatory in Scrum."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best describes the Sprint Review event?",
        "options": {
            "A": "A demo at the end of the Sprint for everyone in the organization to see the Increment",
            "B": "It’s a controlling mechanism for evaluating the work of Developers",
            "C": "It’s a celebration at the end of the Sprint to appreciate the work of Developers",
            "D": "An inspection of the Increment to collect feedback and see what to do in the next Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "An inspection of the Increment to collect feedback and see what to do in the next Sprint",
        "explanation": "As stated in the Scrum Guide the purpose of the Sprint Review is to inspect the outcome of the Sprint and determine future adaptations. The Scrum Team presents the results of their work to key stakeholders and progress toward the Product Goal is discussed."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Scrum Master could never order the Product Backlog items.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner may order the Product Backlog or may delegate the responsibility to others. Regardless, the Product Owner remains accountable."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. A Scrum Team's velocity was 250 at the end of the 6th Sprint. It became 275 at the end of the 8th Sprint. Therefore, they are creating more value now compared to before.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "There's no direct relationship between velocity and value, maybe they're working faster on less valuable items, in which case, velocity will be higher, but value may be the same, higher, or lower. Many people consider velocity as the most important criterion, but that's not true -- they should rather be focused on value, Sprint Goal, and Product Goal."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are required by Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Definition of Ready",
            "B": "Having timeboxed events",
            "C": "User Stories",
            "D": "Scrum Events",
            "E": "Test-Driven Development",
            "F": "Definition of Done"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "D",
            "F"
        ],
        "answers": "Having timeboxed events and Scrum Events and Definition of Done",
        "explanation": "There are no Definition of Ready, TDD or User Stories in Scrum, they can be used, but they are not mandatory."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Each Increment must be released.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Each Increment must be potentially releasable, but you don't have to release them."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Scrum Team should have a Team Leader to improve communications and collaboration.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "It's not allowed to introduce new accountabilities or titles such as \"Team Leader\" in Scrum."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Adding new Developers to the team may cause a short-term decrease in productivity.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "When more Developers are added to the team, there's usually a short-term decrease in productivity because other members have to spend time and effort familiarizing the new members with the development environment of the project. After a while, the existence of new members may increase productivity, but even if it does, it's usually not a linear increase because, for example, having more people increases communication channels, which consumes some of the capacity."
    },
    {
        "question": "Harry is a Scrum Master of a new Scrum Team with six Developers. He is trying to make sure that all the accountabilities are understood by the Scrum Team. Which of the following statements are correct about the Developers? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "They prioritize tasks in the Sprint Backlog",
            "B": "They participate in the Daily Serum meeting",
            "C": "Thay are responsible for engaging the stakeholders",
            "D": "They prioritize the Product Backlog items",
            "E": "They cause the removal of impediments"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "They prioritize tasks in the Sprint Backlog and They participate in the Daily Serum meeting",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is responsible for engaging the stakeholders. Developers are responsible for the Sprint Backlog and they must participate in Daily Scrum, others can attend as listeners. Removing impediments happens from everyone not only the Developers and they are all coached from the Scrum Master on how to do it. The Product Owner is the one who orders the items in the Product Backlog."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. All teams should be cross-functional in scaled Scrum.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "It's one of the basic concepts in Scrum to have cross-functional, self-managing teams."
    },
    {
        "question": "Three Scrum Teams are currently building a single product and pulling work from the same Product Backlog. All three teams have identified that they will need Dmytro, a database specialist, to work full time in their team for the next several Sprints. What should Steven, the Scrum Master, do to solve this potential problem?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Ask Dmytro to work with the HR department to recruit and hire additional database specialists. In the meantime, have the Product Owner move items that do not depend on Dmytro to the top of the Product Backlog",
            "B": "Coach the Scrum Teams to self-manage this issue and help them implement their preferred solution",
            "C": "Assign Dmytro to the team with the most urgent tasks first and then move him to the next team and so on until the required support is completed",
            "D": "Manage the items in the Sprint Backlogs so that Dmytro can be utilized evenly for each team"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Coach the Scrum Teams to self-manage this issue and help them implement their preferred solution",
        "explanation": "If requested, the Scrum Master can even facilitate conversations through open ended questions in order to help the team members make the best possible decisions according to what is known at the time. He/she does not approve or reject team decisions but ensures the team stays within the boundaries of the Scrum framework."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who's responsible for quality?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Team Leaders",
            "B": "Developers",
            "C": "Testers"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Developers",
        "explanation": "There are no Testers or Team Leaders in Scrum. There are only Developers, because we don't have extra accountabilities and titles in Scrum. However, there can be Developers who are experts in testing. Remember that everyone is called a Developer."
    },
    {
        "question": "At the end of the Sprint, all items are done except for one that is almost done. What should be done with this item?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Put it in the next Sprint Backlog",
            "B": "The Sprint will be extended until we complete the item",
            "C": "It can be added to the Increment if the user acceptance tests are done",
            "D": "Move it back to the Product Backlog",
            "E": "It should not be included in the Increment"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Move it back to the Product Backlog and It should not be included in the Increment",
        "explanation": "It shouldn't be moved to the next Sprint Backlog. It has to go to the Product Backlog and let the Product Owner decide what is going to happen. If the item is still at the top, it will be selected in the next Sprint Planning meeting. The Increment contains only items that meet the DoD. Sprints are timeboxed, meaning that we don't extend their duration."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are misleading about non-functional requirements? (Select the best three answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Some of them can be added to the Definition of Done",
            "B": "They will be in the Sprint Backlog, but not the Product Backlog",
            "C": "They will be reflected in the Sprint Goal",
            "D": "Scrum is all about functional requirements",
            "E": "They should be incorporated into every Increment",
            "F": "Some of them can be added to the Product Backlog or as per Acceptance Criteria of Product Backlog items"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "They will be in the Sprint Backlog, but not the Product Backlog and They will be reflected in the Sprint Goal and Scrum is all about functional requirements",
        "explanation": "Non-functional features are about the way functional features work, not about the goals for Sprints. All items in the Sprint Backlog come from the Product Backlog, except for process improvement items (if the team decides it) that are generated in Sprint Retrospectives. There are non-functional requirements like security, scalability, maintainability, performance."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best describe the Product Backlog? (Select the best three answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "It’s used to create the project plan",
            "B": "The Product Owner is accountable for it",
            "C": "It may change anytime, and it is never complete",
            "D": "It changes as we learn more about the project",
            "E": "Provides just enough information to enable the Developers to design the whole product"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Owner is accountable for it and It may change anytime, and it is never complete and It changes as we learn more about the project",
        "explanation": "It describes everything that is needed in the product. There's no \"project plan\" in Scrum. Product Backlog is the closest thing to a project plan that we have in Scrum."
    },
    {
        "question": "An organization has just hired you as a new Scrum Master to help them transform their teams from their current traditional process to Scrum. The teams are currently structured to specialize in a single function, which is also known as component teams where a team would only address a single layer (i.e. front-end, back-end, testing, etc.). You’ve introduced the concept of cross-functional teams where all the skills needed to produce business functionality, from end to end, are inside of a single team. What should you keep in mind when transitioning from siloed teams to cross-functional teams? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "It is easier to compare the performance between cross-functional teams in order to identify which teams to assign tasks to and which teams need additional coaching",
            "B": "Without feature teams, you cannot do Scrum. Postpone Scrum adoption until the teams are reorganized in feature teams",
            "C": "People from the different layers and components will need time to become accustomed to working and delivering unified functionality together as one Scrum Team thus productivity may suffer",
            "D": "Newly formed teams will need time to stabilize before reaching their peak performance. During the initial stages of forming, performance will suffer and productivity may be low, although even then delivery of business value is still likely to increase"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "People from the different layers and components will need time to become accustomed to working and delivering unified functionality together as one Scrum Team thus productivity may suffer and Newly formed teams will need time to stabilize before reaching their peak performance. During the initial stages of forming, performance will suffer and productivity may be low, although even then delivery of business value is still likely to increase",
        "explanation": "Forming a team takes time, and members often go through recognizable stages as they change from being a group of individuals to a team with common goals. Forming, Storming, Norming, and Performing model describes these stages by Bruce Tuckman. When you understand it, you can help your new team become effective more quickly."
    },
    {
        "question": "What do we do with Done items when the Sprint is canceled?",
        "options": {
            "A": "They should be moved back to the Product Backlog, and will be taken care of in future Sprints",
            "B": "They should be moved to the next Sprint Backlog",
            "C": "They will be reviewed, and if they are potentially releasable, the Product Owner typically accepts them"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "They will be reviewed, and if they are potentially releasable, the Product Owner typically accepts them",
        "explanation": "They are Done, so we shouldn't move them back to the Product Backlog? Items in the Sprint Backlog come from the Product Backlog. So, if it's supposed to be done, we will move them back to the Product Backlog, and if they are still on the top of the Product Backlog, they will be picked for the next Sprint. However, this question is about items that are Done, and there's no reason to move them back."
    },
    {
        "question": "According to Scrum Theory, how should a group of fifty Developers be divided into multiple teams?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Allow the team leads to divide and select teams",
            "B": "Understanding the product, the product vision and the Scrum framework, the group self-manages into teams",
            "C": "The teams will rotate members every Sprint to spread knowledge",
            "D": "Create a skills matrix, identify their levels, and years of experience to assign people to teams"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Understanding the product, the product vision and the Scrum framework, the group self-manages into teams",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Team needs to be self-managing. The Scrum Master should coach them when needed or requested."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who owns the Product Backlog?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Developers",
            "B": "The whole Scrum Team",
            "C": "The Product Owner",
            "D": "The Serum Master"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Owner",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is accountable for it, as stated in the Scrum Guide: \"The Product Owner is also accountable for effective Product Backlog management\""
    },
    {
        "question": "How do changes in the project environment impact the Product Backlog?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Product Backlog should be kept high-level enough to tolerate such changes",
            "B": "It evolves to reflect the changes (Correct)",
            "C": "The old baselined Product Backlog would be saved, and a new one would be created for the rest of the project",
            "D": "There’s no effect on the Product Backlog"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "It evolves to reflect the changes (Correct)",
        "explanation": "The Product Backlog is not baselined. New changes should be investigated and create new items that cover it and maybe also change some of the existing items. The Product Backlog has \"just enough\" details, but it's not so high-level that it can tolerate all changes."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are feedback loops in Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Release Planning",
            "B": "Sprint Review",
            "C": "Burn-down chart",
            "D": "Sprint Planning"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Sprint Review and Sprint Planning",
        "explanation": "Releases are also feedback loops, but release planning has feedback elements in it, however, none of these are formal events in Scrum. This is an optional concept, and may facilitate the generation of some types of feedback, but it's not a \"feedback loop\". Sprint Planning, Daily Scrum, Sprint Review, and Sprint Retrospective are \"formal opportunities for inspecting and adapting\", and are considered to be \"feedback loops\". Note that being a \"formal opportunity\" doesn't mean that any signatures will be exchanged in those events, nor anything else that may turn them into \"gates\". The main purpose is to enable adaptation."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct about the Product Backlog?",
        "options": {
            "A": "It has all the details",
            "B": "It has just enough details",
            "C": "It has no details"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "It has just enough details",
        "explanation": "Both Sprint Backlog and Product Backlog evolve during their lives, and the amount of information grows as time passes. So, at each point in time, they don't have as much detail as they will probably have in the future. On the other hand, we never add all the details there. For example, it's common to say that a User Story doesn't provide all the information, but is an excuse for the people involved in the project to have communications around a certain topic. The details are in those communications and are not completely captured in the backlog."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is correct about the Developers?",
        "options": {
            "A": "None of the answers apply",
            "B": "They order the Product Backlog items",
            "C": "They participate in the Daily Scrum meeting",
            "D": "They are responsible for measuring the performance of the project",
            "E": "They decide when to release the product"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "They participate in the Daily Scrum meeting",
        "explanation": "Releasing the product, measuring the performance of the project and ordering the Product Backlog are the Product Owner's responsibility. Developers must participate in Daily Scrum. Others can attend as listeners."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Sprint Backlog makes visible all the work that the _____ identify/identifies as necessary to meet the Sprint Goal.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Scrum Master",
            "B": "Scrum Team",
            "C": "Product Owner",
            "D": "Developers"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "The Sprint Backlog makes visible all the work that the Developers",
        "explanation": "Developers are accountable for the Sprint Backlog and Sprint Goal is their commitment."
    },
    {
        "question": "What's the main reason for the Product Owner to be at the Daily Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "To assign tasks to Developers",
            "B": "To track changes to the Sprint Backlog",
            "C": "To tell Developers what to do",
            "D": "It’s not necessary for them to be in the meeting",
            "E": "To order the Sprint Backlog"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "It’s not necessary for them to be in the meeting",
        "explanation": "Developers are self-managed and take care of their commitment.In general, Daily Scrum is for the Developers, which means that the Developers must participate. Others can attend as listeners. The Product Owner can attend if necessary to answer questions."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of those statements are misleading about Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Scrum is like traditional processes but with self-management to replace Project Managers",
            "B": "Scrum is a framework for developing and sustaining complex products",
            "C": "Scrum is a methodology where you can pick and choose which parts of Scrum you think will work for your environment",
            "D": "Scrum is based on empirical process control theory",
            "E": "Scrum is a framework that eliminates complexity",
            "F": "Each component of Scrum serves a specific purpose and is essential to your ability to use Scrum to develop complex products"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Scrum is like traditional processes but with self-management to replace Project Managers and Scrum is a methodology where you can pick and choose which parts of Scrum you think will work for your environment and Scrum is a framework that eliminates complexity",
        "explanation": "Scrum is meant to be implemented as prescribed in the Scrum Guide, the five Scrum Events are mandatory and each one has a specific purpose. Scrum does not eliminate the complexity that is inherent in delivering a product in today’s world, instead it offers a framework for dealing with complexity. By regularly delivering Increments of value teams gain the ability to inspect and rapidly adapt based on the feedback received. Project Managers are not simply replaced by self-managing teams. Scrum is a framework for optimizing decision making based on the knowledge and experience of the entire team."
    },
    {
        "question": "When does a customer cancel a Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "When the Sprint Goal becomes obsolete",
            "B": "The customer doesn’t have the authority to cancel the Sprint",
            "C": "When not enough information is available for the items in the Sprint Backlog",
            "D": "When not enough resources are available for the project"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "The customer doesn’t have the authority to cancel the Sprint",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner has the authority to cancel the Sprint. The customer isn't allowed to do so."
    },
    {
        "question": "How many members are there in a Scrum Team?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Typically 10 or fewer",
            "B": "3 to 12",
            "C": "5 to 12",
            "D": "3 to 9",
            "E": "2 to 8"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Typically 10 or fewer",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Team is small enough to remain nimble and large enough to complete significant work within a Sprint, typically 10 or fewer people. In general, we have found that smaller teams communicate better and are more productive."
    },
    {
        "question": "An organization is using Scrum to build five new products. What would be the best options for the number of Product Owners the organization should have? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "There is one Product Owner responsible for all five products. In order to scale his/her accountability, he/she can delegate some of the individual Product Owner responsibilities to others within each product but would still remain accountable for the value of the work produced",
            "B": "Enough Product Owners to delegate as much work needed to maximize utilization of all Developers",
            "C": "There is one Product Owner responsible for all five products. This person is not allowed to delegate any of the Product Owner responsibilities as he/she is accountable for the success of each product",
            "D": "There is one Product Owner for each product. Each Product Owner may delegate, share and align work within their individual Product Backlog"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "There is one Product Owner responsible for all five products. In order to scale his/her accountability, he/she can delegate some of the individual Product Owner responsibilities to others within each product but would still remain accountable for the value of the work produced and There is one Product Owner for each product. Each Product Owner may delegate, share and align work within their individual Product Backlog",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is the sole person responsible for maximizing the value of the product through the ordering and management of the Product Backlog. This reduces complexity in communication and understanding who to go to when there are questions about the product. The Product Owner may delegate his/her responsibilities but still remains accountable for the outcome of those responsibilities."
    },
    {
        "question": "In Scrum, how would budgeting and financial forecasting be performed? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Budgeting is not necessary as the only funding necessary is the operational costs of the Scrum Teams",
            "B": "A single release may be funded with several Sprints where every Sprint is producing shippable Increments",
            "C": "Frequently inspect the outcomes of the delivered Sprint Increments to understand how much value is being produced per investment spent",
            "D": "Fixed budgets are not allowed in Scrum"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "A single release may be funded with several Sprints where every Sprint is producing shippable Increments and Frequently inspect the outcomes of the delivered Sprint Increments to understand how much value is being produced per investment spent",
        "explanation": "The cost of developing, delivering, and sustaining products can impact how the flow of value is managed throughout the life of a product. Each Sprint is an opportunity to inspect the investment (financial, time, effort, etc.) against the returned value (customer satisfaction, revenue, etc.) of the work that has been delivered. The team can then decide on what it should do next to maximize the value of the investment."
    },
    {
        "question": "What's the role of a Scrum Master during Sprint Retrospectives?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Participating as a Scrum Team member",
            "B": "Summarizing and report the results of the meeting to stakeholders",
            "C": "Capturing process improvement ideas for the next Sprint Backlog",
            "D": "They should not participate in this meeting"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Participating as a Scrum Team member",
        "explanation": "The whole Scrum Team participates in the Sprint Retrospective, and they work together to see how they can improve the way they work in the next Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Scrum Master can also be the Product Owner.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "According to Scrum Guide, one person can have more than one accountabilities. It's not recommended, but it's not forbidden either. They don't forbid it because some of the small projects may need to use a few people to do multiple things. When doing that, the person must make sure that they are paying attention to all responsibilities that they have for each role, which is not easy."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following contribute the most to the Scrum value \"focus\"? (Select the best three answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Product Backlog refinement",
            "B": "Product Goal",
            "C": "Timeboxing",
            "D": "Sprint Review",
            "E": "Sprint Goal"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Product Goal and Timeboxing and Sprint Goal",
        "explanation": "Helps you focus on the outcome that is expected from the Sprint. Helps you focus on the most valuable aspects of items selected for the Sprint, rather than making those items fancies, because time is not unlimited. Scrum values are commitment, courage, focus, openness, and respect."
    },
    {
        "question": "What's the role of a Project Management Office (PMO) in an organization that only uses Scrum for project delivery?",
        "options": {
            "A": "There’s no place for a PMO in such an organization",
            "B": "Manages portfolios and programs and facilitates the application",
            "C": "of techniques that complement Scrum",
            "D": "The PMO should manage and help Scrum Masters",
            "E": "The PMO should manage and help Product Owners"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Manages portfolios and programs and facilitates the application",
        "explanation": "There are limits to the self-management of the team, and the important thing is to have the power within the borders of the project. However, each project is run in a wider organization with multiple levels of management impacting the project, and it's not possible or even acceptable to reject that structure, as long as it doesn't block the internal self-management of the team and the fundamental adaptive approach of the project."
    },
    {
        "question": "How many hours per day should a Developer work?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Depends on the Product Owners pressure from stakeholders",
            "B": "At a constant pace",
            "C": "At least 6 ideal man-hours",
            "D": "As much as needed for realizing the Sprint Backlog items by the end of the Sprint",
            "E": "Normally, 40 hours a week"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "At a constant pace",
        "explanation": "This is one of the Agile principles. The Sprint Backlog is just a rough estimate of what we can do. We will have a constant pace and deliver as much as we can, within the defined quality, and nothing bad happens if all items are not delivered."
    },
    {
        "question": "What happens between two Sprints?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Refactoring the previous Increment",
            "B": "Product Backlog refinement",
            "C": "Nothing",
            "D": "Getting customer approval for the previous Increment"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Nothing",
        "explanation": "Sprints are happening continuously. Refactoring is done during the Sprints. Each Sprint starts immediately after the previous one, there's no space between the two."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are misleading about the length of Sprints? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Sprint length is set during Sprint Planning, and is long enough to develop all items in the Sprint Backlog",
            "B": "Sprint length is set during Sprint Planning, and is long enough for programming and testing all items, but not for integrating them",
            "C": "It’s preferred to have Sprints with the same length",
            "D": "The longer the Sprint the higher the risk",
            "E": "All Sprints must be one month or less"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Sprint length is set during Sprint Planning, and is long enough to develop all items in the Sprint Backlog and Sprint length is set during Sprint Planning, and is long enough for programming and testing all items, but not for integrating them",
        "explanation": "One month is the maximum timeboxed duration for Sprints in Scrum. We can't change the timeboxed duration of Sprints on an ad hoc basis. The length of the Sprint has to do with the risk as well. Shorter Sprints can be employed to generate more learning cycles and limit risk of cost and effort to a smaller time frame."
    },
    {
        "question": "On average, items on the Product Backlog tend to be _______________",
        "options": {
            "A": "Smaller than those on the Sprint Backlog",
            "B": "Larger than those on the Sprint Backlog",
            "C": "The same size as those on the Sprint Backlog"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "On average, items on the Product Backlog tend to be Larger than those on the Sprint Backlog",
        "explanation": "Product Backlog has larger items that usually needs to be broken down into very small and clear items, because it's a form of upfront planning. Some of them may be very large. When you order the items, if they are on the top of the list, you have to make them clear, and make sure they can fit into one Sprint; therefore, you will break them down into smaller items."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Product Owner is the main person responsible for engaging the stakeholders.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "Engagement of stakeholders is mostly about and around the Product Backlog items, and at least indirectly, about the value created in the project. That's why this is mainly the responsibility of the Product Owner to keep them engaged. Others may contribute as well like the Scrum Master may remove impediments related to engaging stakeholders and Developers may find ways to facilitate it. Nevertheless, the main person responsible for engaging stakeholders is the Product Owner."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. It's up to the self-managing team to decide which Scrum artifacts are needed in the project.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Self-management is not unlimited, the Scrum Team should follow the Scrum framework."
    },
    {
        "question": "During Sprint Planning, the Definition of Done will help the Scrum Team forecast the amount of work, selected from the Product Backlog, deemed feasible to meet the \"Done\" by the end of the Sprint. Which two items best describe what \"Done\" means? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "All the work needed to prepare the Increment for Integration Testing",
            "B": "All the work completed within the current skills and expertise in the Scrum Team",
            "C": "Having an Increment of working software that is potentially releasable to the end users",
            "D": "All the work performed as defined in the Definition of Done",
            "E": "All the work needed to prepare the Increment for User Acceptance Testing"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Having an Increment of working software that is potentially releasable to the end users and All the work performed as defined in the Definition of Done",
        "explanation": "When a Product Backlog item or an Increment is described as ‘Done’, everyone must understand what ‘Done’ means. Although this may vary significantly per Scrum Team, members must have a shared understanding of what it means for work to be complete, to ensure transparency. This is the Definition of Done for the Scrum Team and is used to assess when work is complete on the product Increment. The purpose of each Sprint is to deliver Increments of potentially releasable functionality that adhere to the Scrum Team’s current Definition of Done."
    },
    {
        "question": "What's the normal timeboxed duration of Sprint Review when there are 6 Developers in the team and Sprints are two weeks long?",
        "options": {
            "A": "4 hours",
            "B": "2 hours",
            "C": "8 hours",
            "D": "3 hours"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "2 hours",
        "explanation": "As stated in the Scrum Guide the timebox of Sprint Review is 4 hours in a one-month Sprint and normally shorter for shorter Sprints."
    },
    {
        "question": "The timebox of this Scrum Event should be no more than four hours.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Sprint Review",
            "B": "Release Sprint",
            "C": "Sprint Retrospective",
            "D": "Release Planning",
            "E": "Sprint",
            "F": "Sprint Planning"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Sprint Review",
        "explanation": "The Sprint Review is the second to last event of the Sprint and is timeboxed to a maximum of four hours for a one-month Sprint. For shorter Sprints, the event is usually shorter."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following elements are attributes of Product Backlog items?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Owner",
            "B": "Description",
            "C": "Estimate",
            "D": "Order"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Description and Estimate and Order",
        "explanation": "Product Backlog refinement is the act of breaking down and further defining Product Backlog items into smaller more precise items. This is an ongoing activity to add details, such as a description, order, and size. Attributes often vary with the domain of work."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is least likely to be used by a Scrum Team?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Digital camera, task board",
            "B": "Gantt Chart",
            "C": "Wiki, online forum",
            "D": "Large screen, Planning Poker cards"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Gantt Chart",
        "explanation": "Note the word \"least\" in the question. WBS and Gantt Chart are mainly used in planning predictive (plan-based) projects rather than adaptive (Agile) ones."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements show the result of changing Scrum terminology while implementing it in the organization? (Select the best three answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "They will get better results adopting Scrum this way",
            "B": "The change might not be obvious to everyone, and therefore very little change actually happens",
            "C": "The change might not be obvious to everyone! and some benefits may be lost",
            "D": "It’s necessary to tailor Scrum to suit the project",
            "E": "Management may feel less enthusiastic about the change"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "The change might not be obvious to everyone, and therefore very little change actually happens and The change might not be obvious to everyone! and some benefits may be lost and Management may feel less enthusiastic about the change",
        "explanation": "Scrum is a simple framework rather than a comprehensive methodology, and it contains only the necessary minimums that you need in every project. So, instead of normal tailoring (adjusting the existing elements), you will follow everything that is described in Scrum, and suit it to your project by the practices and techniques that you add; e.g. Planning Poker, Pair-Programming, and Test-Driven Development. When it comes to the terminology, Scrum Guide believes that it's better if you don't change it."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best describe Sprint Planning? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "What was the feedback and how should we adapt the Product Backlog?",
            "B": "How are we going to do what we have decided to do in the Sprint?",
            "C": "Who will be in the team this Sprint?",
            "D": "What are we going to do during the Sprint?",
            "E": "What went wrong in the last Sprint and what to do about it?"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "How are we going to do what we have decided to do in the Sprint? and What are we going to do during the Sprint?",
        "explanation": "What went wrong in the last Sprint would be discussed in the previous Sprint Retrospective. Sprint Planning has to do with the work for the next Sprint and has to cover three topics, Why is this Sprint valuable? What can be Done this Sprint? and How will the chosen work get done?"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who can attend the Daily Scrum meeting?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Anyone",
            "B": "The Developers and the Product Owner",
            "C": "The Developers",
            "D": "The Developers and the Scrum Master"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Anyone",
        "explanation": "Daily Scrum is for the Developers who must participate. However, others can attend as listeners, there is nothing that prohibits this."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Scrum Master should ask each Developer to answer the three standard questions at the Daily Scrum.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "It's a good idea to go over the three questions, but not mandatory. Also, the meeting is managed by the Developers and the Scrum Master helps only when requested or required, it's not even mandatory to be there."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Vicky is a Scrum Master of a 13-member Scrum Team (including her). Because of the team size it is mandatory to divide the Scrum Team.",
        "options": {
            "A": "This is false as it is not required from Scrum to divide the Scrum Team if there are more than 10 members in the Scrum Team",
            "B": "This is true as the maximum size of a Scrum Team must be 10 or fewer"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "This is false as it is not required from Scrum to divide the Scrum Team if there are more than 10 members in the Scrum Team",
        "explanation": "The word mandatory is key here. The Scrum Guide 2020 doesn't state anywhere that it is mandatory to divide teams. It's true that smaller teams communicate better but not necessarily. As stated in the Scrum Guide the Scrum Team is small enough to remain nimble and large enough to complete significant work within a Sprint, typically 10 or fewer people."
    },
    {
        "question": "What would be two boundaries, defined in Scrum, that give guidance for teams to effectively self-manage? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Clearly defined functional teams within the Scrum Team to define handoff phases during development",
            "B": "Timeboxing the events in Scrum to allow for regular inspection and adaptation creating opportunities to adjust course in any given path",
            "C": "Having a mixture of different levels of skills and experience to promote domain knowledge sharing",
            "D": "Creating an integrated and potentially shippable Increment by the end of each Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Timeboxing the events in Scrum to allow for regular inspection and adaptation creating opportunities to adjust course in any given path and Creating an integrated and potentially shippable Increment by the end of each Sprint",
        "explanation": "Timeboxing promotes regularity and focus for self-managed teams. Having shippable Increments allows teams to collaboratively make decisions on what needs to be done next."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Product Owner is not collaborating with the Developers during the Sprint. Which of the following actions would you choose as the Scrum Master? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Coach the Product Owner to understand why collaboration is important in Scrum and how it can affect the value of the product",
            "B": "Nominate someone else as the proxy Product Owner",
            "C": "Talk to the functional manager of the Product Owner",
            "D": "Cancel the Sprint and start training the Product Owner",
            "E": "Bring up the issue in the next Sprint Retrospective"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Coach the Product Owner to understand why collaboration is important in Scrum and how it can affect the value of the product and Bring up the issue in the next Sprint Retrospective",
        "explanation": "Canceling the Sprint and starting training the Product Owner is not a valid reason for canceling the Sprint, and also, only the Product Owner can cancel Sprints. Talking to the functional manager of the Product Owner is not right, it's best to resolve issues internally. There's no proxy Product Owner in Scrum."
    },
    {
        "question": "According to the values of Scrum, which is the best way to create teams of developers?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Work with the leadership team to allocate members according to skills, seniority and experience to ensure that all Scrum Teams are balanced fairly",
            "B": "Provide boundaries to the Developers and allow them to self manage into teams",
            "C": "The Product Owner will create a skills matrix according to what is needed for the project and work with the technical leads to allocate resources to the team",
            "D": "None of the above"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Provide boundaries to the Developers and allow them to self manage into teams",
        "explanation": "When the values of commitment, courage, focus, openness and respect are embodied and lived by the Scrum Team, the Scrum pillars of transparency, inspection, and adaptation come to life and build trust for everyone and self- organizing teams will be enabled to choose how best to accomplish their work."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best explain the benefits of having tests in the Definition of Done? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Increments would be closer to potentially releasable",
            "B": "It makes reporting easier for the Project Manager",
            "C": "Increases transparency of the Increments",
            "D": "It defines when the Increment should be released"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Increments would be closer to potentially releasable and Increases transparency of the Increments",
        "explanation": "You can't release it unless you've tested the output and are sure it won't create problems in production, so if you add tests in the DoD, you will prevent issues from happening and transparency of the quality of the Increment."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are timeboxed?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Sprint",
            "B": "Release Retrospective",
            "C": "Sprint Retrospective",
            "D": "Sprint Review",
            "E": "Product Backlog refinement",
            "F": "Sprint testing"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Sprint and Sprint Retrospective and Sprint Review",
        "explanation": "There's no release Retrospective event in Scrum. It's done frequently, and it's not timeboxed. Testing is done continuously. The Scrum Events are timeboxed."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best describes the Scrum Pillar of Adaptation.",
        "options": {
            "A": "None of the answers apply",
            "B": "If any aspects of a process deviate outside acceptable limits or if the resulting product is unacceptable, the process being applied or the materials being produced must be adjusted",
            "C": "The Scrum artifacts and the progress toward agreed goals must be inspected frequently and diligently to detect potentially undesirable variances or problems",
            "D": "The emergent process and work must be visible to those performing the work as well as those receiving the work"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "If any aspects of a process deviate outside acceptable limits or if the resulting product is unacceptable, the process being applied or the materials being produced must be adjusted",
        "explanation": "As stated in the Scrum Guide: \"If any aspects of a process deviate outside acceptable limits or if the resulting product is unacceptable, the process being applied or the materials being produced must be adjusted. The adjustment must be made as soon as possible to minimize further deviation.\""
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Product Owner and Scrum Master are not allowed to be part of the Developers.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "According to the Scrum Guide, one person can have more than one accountabilities. It's not recommended, but it's not forbidden either. They don't forbid it because some of the small projects may need to use a few people to do multiple things, they just need to make sure that they are paying attention to all responsibilities that they have."
    },
    {
        "question": "Why are Daily Scrums held at the same time and same place?",
        "options": {
            "A": "To make sure everyone has to be there",
            "B": "To be able to book rooms upfront",
            "C": "So that everyone will know where and when to find the Developers",
            "D": "To reduce complexity and wasted time"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "To reduce complexity and wasted time",
        "explanation": "Consider having to spend some time every day, arranging the next Daily Scrum, it would be painful. It’s just too much waste, and it’s much easier to keep it simple and have the meetings at the same time and the same place every day."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is not mandatory in Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Inspect Progress",
            "B": "Timeboxing the events",
            "C": "Sprint Planning",
            "D": "Story Points",
            "E": "Pair-Programming",
            "F": "Measure Velocity"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D",
            "E",
            "F"
        ],
        "answers": "Story Points and Pair-Programming and Measure Velocity",
        "explanation": "Only the accountabilities, events, and artifacts are mandatory as well as the Definition of Done and progress measurement of course."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is not required by Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Test-Driven Development",
            "B": "None of the answers apply",
            "C": "Definition of Done",
            "D": "Sprint Retrospectives",
            "E": "All answers apply",
            "F": "Having timeboxed events"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Test-Driven Development",
        "explanation": "TDD is not required, the rest are mandatory in Scrum."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Cross-functional teams are optimized in a technical layer of a system.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "A cross-functional team is one that has all types of expertise that is required to develop the product. Note that this is about the team as a whole, not individual team members. Being cross-functional means that you can work (as a team) comfortably on all technical layers of the system."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the main reason for the Scrum Master to be at the Daily Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Developers have asked the Scrum Master to facilitate their Daily Scrum",
            "B": "To make sure that every Developer answers the three questions",
            "C": "To assign tasks to Developers",
            "D": "To get a report on progress of the Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "The Developers have asked the Scrum Master to facilitate their Daily Scrum",
        "explanation": "Developers are self-managed and take care of their work and progress. The Scrum Master is focused on the context, not content. In general, Daily Scrum is for the Developers, which means that only the Developers participate. Others can attend as listeners. Well, unless it's about a Scrum Master facilitating the meeting (not so common), in which case \"listeners\" might talk. Listeners can be the Product Owner or even stakeholders, there is nothing that prohibits this."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following actions may a Scrum Master take in starting up a project?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Ask the Product Owner to explain the project, its business needs, history, goals, and context",
            "B": "Ask the development managers to introduce their departments and capabilities",
            "C": "Ask the team to work together and prepare a complete Product Backlog",
            "D": "Ensure that there’s a clear understanding of the whole scope of the project",
            "E": "None of the answers apply",
            "F": "All answers apply"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Ask the Product Owner to explain the project, its business needs, history, goals, and context",
        "explanation": "We don't know the whole scope of the project in the beginning, so we will keep learning from Sprint to Sprint. Product Backlog is never complete and it's Product Owners responsibility not the Scrum Master. It has to be about the project and people internal to it, not the external departments. Remember that the team is cross-functional and does everything needed for the project, without outside help."
    },
    {
        "question": "What type of test should be done during the Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "All tests, except for integration tests",
            "B": "All tests, except for user acceptance tests",
            "C": "Unit tests",
            "D": "Every type of test"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Every type of test",
        "explanation": "Remember that the Increment has to be \"Done\", and potentially releasable. It means that all tests should be done."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who resolves team conflicts within the Developers?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Scrum Master",
            "B": "The Team Leader",
            "C": "The Developers",
            "D": "Stakeholders",
            "E": "The whole Scrum Team",
            "F": "The customer"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The Developers",
        "explanation": "The Developers should be able to resolve internal conflicts. If they can't succeed, they should ask the Scrum Master for help."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. If you do Scrum you must release your software at the end of each Sprint.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Multiple Increments may be created within a Sprint, but it's up to the Product Owner to decide if it will be released."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following should not change during the Sprint? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Sprint Backlog",
            "B": "Sprint Goal",
            "C": "Definition of Done",
            "D": "Product Backlog"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Sprint Goal and Definition of Done",
        "explanation": "Sprint Goal and Definition of Done should remain the same. Sprint Backlog can change from the Developers during the Sprint. Product Owner can keep adding items in the Product Backlog, during the Sprint, this doesn't change Developers' work."
    },
    {
        "question": "When is the Sprint over?",
        "options": {
            "A": "When the Sprint Backlog tasks are done",
            "B": "When all Sprint Backlog items are done",
            "C": "When the Scrum Master announces the end of the Sprint",
            "D": "When the Product Owner cancels the Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "When the Product Owner cancels the Sprint",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner has the authority to cancel a Sprint. If there was an option about timebox, it's true that the Sprint is over when the timebox expires."
    },
    {
        "question": "When is a Product Backlog item ready?",
        "options": {
            "A": "When it doesn’t take more than one week to be developed",
            "B": "When the Product Owner is happy with it",
            "C": "When all tasks and acceptance criteria required for its completion are identified",
            "D": "When it can be Done within one Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "When it can be Done within one Sprint",
        "explanation": "There is no Definition of Ready in Scrum, however the Scrum Guide states \"Product Backlog items that can be Done by the Scrum Team within one Sprint are deemed ready for selection in a Sprint Planning event.\""
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following may not be done in the Sprint Retrospective meeting?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Discuss the Product Backlog items for the next Sprint",
            "B": "Discuss the Definition of Done",
            "C": "Calculate Velocity",
            "D": "Refining the Product Backlog",
            "E": "Improve the way that they communicate"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Discuss the Product Backlog items for the next Sprint and Calculate Velocity and Refining the Product Backlog",
        "explanation": "Sprint Retrospective is about the way they work. It's about the things that affect the product, but they don't discuss the product directly. In general, it's about the context, not the content. For example, they talk about the way Product Backlog is refined, but they won't refine the Product Backlog in the Sprint Retrospective meeting."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following may not be done when the team becomes mature enough during the project? (Select the best three answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "They may end up improving their Definition of Done",
            "B": "They might be more productive",
            "C": "They can release every Sprint",
            "D": "They may not need a Scrum Master anymore",
            "E": "They will need longer Sprint Retrospectives"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C",
            "D",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "They can release every Sprint and They may not need a Scrum Master anymore and They will need longer Sprint Retrospectives",
        "explanation": "They can be more productive as they know more about the product and the team members. The Definition of Done shouldn't change in the middle of the Sprint, but they might end up updating it, in their Retrospective. After all, Increments are always potentially releasable, even if the team is not mature enough."
    },
    {
        "question": "A Developer has notified the Scrum Master of a potential data security risk. What action should the Scrum Master take?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Ask the Developer to share the issue with the team as soon as possible",
            "B": "Notify the test team",
            "C": "Add a Product Backlog item to address the security issue",
            "D": "Wait until the Sprint Retrospective to add security to the Definition of Done"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Ask the Developer to share the issue with the team as soon as possible",
        "explanation": "It is best to coach the Developers to collaborate on issues regardless of severity. They may consult the Scrum Master of Product Owner if needed. They need to have the courage to raise this."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who may add new work to the Sprint Backlog during the Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Stakeholders",
            "B": "The whole Scrum Team",
            "C": "The Scrum Master",
            "D": "The Developers",
            "E": "The Business Analyst",
            "F": "The Project Manager"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "The Developers",
        "explanation": "There's no separate Business Analyst accountability in Scrum. There's no project manager in Scrum. The Developers own the Sprint Backlog and if they finish early enough and they decide they can bring items from the top of the Product Backlog (self-managed).\n\nChapter 5: PSPOTM I Full Mock Test 4\nTime Limit: 60 minutes        No. of Questions: 80."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Scrum Teams should normalize their estimations, so that management can measure and compare their performance.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Progress measurements are done internally, not by external managers. Also, comparing the velocity dependent on the estimates of two different teams is never reliable, and it's not productive."
    },
    {
        "question": "A Scrum Master is working with Developers in different geographical locations. The Developers meet in a variety of meeting rooms and have much to do logistically (for example, set up conference calls, book the place) before the Daily Scrum. What action should the Scrum Master take in this situation?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Scrum Master should set up a meeting and announce them how it will be addressed",
            "B": "Ask the Developers to alternate who is responsible for the meeting setup. This will make them accountable",
            "C": "Ask the development manager to solve it as it is an impediment",
            "D": "Allow the Developers to self-manage and determine by themselves what to do. This will make the team more self-managing"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Allow the Developers to self-manage and determine by themselves what to do. This will make the team more self-managing",
        "explanation": "Scrum Teams are structured and empowered by the organization to organize and manage their own work. This includes deciding how to form teams when multiple teams are needed. The resulting synergy optimizes the teams overall efficiency and effectiveness. They are self-managing. No one (not even the Scrum Master) tells the Developers how to turn Product Backlog into Increments of potentially releasable functionality."
    },
    {
        "question": "Commitment is one of the Scrum values. Which of the following statements best describes it?",
        "options": {
            "A": "It’s about delivering all the items in the Sprint Backlog",
            "B": "It’s about dedication, and the intent and effort put into work",
            "C": "It’s about achieving the result that you have committed to"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "It’s about dedication, and the intent and effort put into work",
        "explanation": "The Scrum values are commitment, courage, focus, openness, and respect. The Scrum Theory Pillars are Transparency, Inspection, Adaptation."
    },
    {
        "question": "What should the Developers do when they face issues delivering an item because they don't understand it?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Complete as much of the item as possible, and use it in the Sprint Review meeting",
            "B": "Ask the Scrum Master to help with this impediment",
            "C": "All answers apply",
            "D": "Move the item back to the Product Backlog",
            "E": "Create a better understanding of what is needed",
            "F": "Collaborate with the Product Owner to see what’s possible and desirable"
        },
        "answer": [
            "F"
        ],
        "answers": "Collaborate with the Product Owner to see what’s possible and desirable",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is responsible for explaining the items. Developers should try to understand and develop the item instead of sending it back and they should go with their best guess because this may create a lot of rework, it should be well defined and has all the functional requirements."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement does not explain when an item is considered complete?",
        "options": {
            "A": "None of the answers apply",
            "B": "All answers apply",
            "C": "The item has all the quality requirements defined by the Product Owner",
            "D": "When it’s potentially usable for the end users, if it becomes part of the Increment",
            "E": "When everything is done based on the Definition of Done",
            "F": "When it can be part of a potentially releasable Increment"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The item has all the quality requirements defined by the Product Owner",
        "explanation": "It doesn't mean that it's done if the item satisfies the customer and end users. A Product Backlog item that you have in the Sprint Backlog is Done, when it can be part of the Increment, which means that reflects the Definition of Done. Make sure you have noticed the word \"not\" in the question."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following actions may a Scrum Master take in starting up a project? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Ask the Developers to introduce themselves to each other and tell about their skills and background",
            "B": "Ask the Product Owner to explain the project, its business needs, history, goals, and context",
            "C": "Ask the development managers to introduce their departments and capabilities",
            "D": "Ask the team to work together and prepare a complete Product Backlog",
            "E": "Ensure that team members have clear accountabilities and responsibilities"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Ask the Developers to introduce themselves to each other and tell about their skills and background and Ask the Product Owner to explain the project, its business needs, history, goals, and context",
        "explanation": "They share accountability, and they do not have different accountabilities and responsibilities. It has to be about the project and people internal to it, not the external departments. Remember that the team is cross-functional and does everything needed for the project, without outside help. Product Backlog is never complete."
    },
    {
        "question": "The timebox of this Scrum Event should be no more than eight hours.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Release Planning",
            "B": "Sprint",
            "C": "Release Sprint",
            "D": "Sprint Planning",
            "E": "Sprint Retrospective",
            "F": "Sprint Review"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Sprint Planning",
        "explanation": "Sprint Planning is timeboxed to a maximum of eight hours for a one-month Sprint. For shorter Sprints, the event is usually shorter."
    },
    {
        "question": "How much time does the Product Owner spend on Product Backlog refinement?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Not more than 30% of their time",
            "B": "Usually not more than 5% of their time",
            "C": "Usually not more than 20% of their time",
            "D": "As much as needed"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "As much as needed",
        "explanation": "It's an ongoing activity to add details, such as a description, order, and size. Developers usually assist with this."
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose decision is it to establish the tasks to be performed during the Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Team Leader",
            "B": "None of the answers apply",
            "C": "The Developers",
            "D": "The Scrum Master",
            "E": "The Product Owner",
            "F": "All answers apply"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The Developers",
        "explanation": "The Developers are self-managed, hence its members decide on the way they work and on the technical approach of the project."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following best describes the way a Product Owner can order the items in the Product Backlog?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Based on risk, riskier items on the top",
            "B": "Based on risk, safer items on the top",
            "C": "Based on size, larger items on the top",
            "D": "Based on value, more valuable items on the top"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Based on value, more valuable items on the top",
        "explanation": "Product Owner's responsibility is to maximize the value of the Product Backlog, so items are ordered accordingly."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is required to attend the Daily Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Developers and the Scrum Master",
            "B": "The Developers and the Product Owner",
            "C": "The Developers",
            "D": "The whole Scrum Team"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The Developers",
        "explanation": "Daily Scrum is mandatory for the Developers only they can participate and talk. However others can join as listeners. There is nothing in the Scrum Guide that prohibits this."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following has the most to do with capturing and using lessons learned?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Product Backlog refinement",
            "B": "Sprint Review",
            "C": "Sprint Retrospective",
            "D": "Sprint Planning"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Sprint Retrospective",
        "explanation": "Sprint Retrospective is about discussing the way work was done and finding ways to improve it next time; this is mainly about lessons learned."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Each item in the Sprint Backlog is owned by one or a pair of Developers.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "All Developers share ownership and stay accountable for the whole Sprint Backlog."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Sprint Review should be done before the Sprint Retrospective.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "As stated in the Scrum Guide: The Sprint Review is the second to last event of the Sprint. This is useful to discuss in the Sprint Retrospective potential feedback from the Sprint Review."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Some items in Sprint Backlogs are not directly about the features and functions of the product.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "It is true as you can have non-functional requirements in the Sprint Backlog."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Scrum Team is self-managed, therefore, they can decide to drop Daily Scrums.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "They are self-managed but they can not change the Scrum framework. It is not acceptable to drop Daily Scrum."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements can be considered real outputs of a Sprint? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "A plan for the next Sprints",
            "B": "A potentially releasable piece of software",
            "C": "An Increment of working software",
            "D": "An Increment of software with minor known bugs in it"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "A potentially releasable piece of software and An Increment of working software",
        "explanation": "If you know that there's a bug, you should fix it before calling it \"Done\". The real output is the Increment: a piece of working software that meets the Definition of Done. From a wider perspective, you can also consider the feedback that is generated by the customer and the improvements you plan in the Sprint Retrospective as real outputs, but a question like this is focused on the product, and on checking if you can distinguish DONE items from technical tasks; the former is valuable for us, but the latter is just the means to an end."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following describes the relationship between the Product Backlog and changes in the project environment?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The old baselined Product Backlog would be saved, and a new one would be created for the rest of the project",
            "B": "The Product Backlog should be kept high-level enough to tolerate such changes",
            "C": "It evolves to reflect the changes",
            "D": "There’s no effect on the Product Backlog"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "It evolves to reflect the changes",
        "explanation": "If there's a new regulation, and you have to comply with it in your software. You investigate the regulation and create new items that cover it, and you may also change some of the existing items. The Product Backlog is not baselined, it has just enough details, but not so high-level that can tolerate all changes."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is not correct about the Scrum Master accountability?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Makes sure that the Developers have Daily Scrums",
            "B": "Estimates the value of Product Backlog items",
            "C": "Causing the removal of impediments",
            "D": "Helps the organization implement Scrum",
            "E": "All answers apply",
            "F": "None of the answers apply"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Estimates the value of Product Backlog items",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is responsible for the Product Backlog management. The rest of the options are Scrum Master's accountability."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are not allowed in Scrum? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Integration Sprints",
            "B": "Release Sprints",
            "C": "Release Planning",
            "D": "Using User Stories",
            "E": "Using Planning Poker"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Integration Sprints and Release Sprints",
        "explanation": "As stated in the Scrum Guide \"A new Sprint starts immediately after the conclusion of the previous Sprint.\" If something is not mentioned in the Scrum Guide it is not mandatory, but also not prohibited, like User Stories, Planning Poker, Release Planning."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Developers realize that they have over-committed themselves for the Sprint. How should they review and adjust the work?",
        "options": {
            "A": "They shouldn’t make any changes to the Sprint Backlog",
            "B": "They should ask the Product Owner to cancel the Sprint",
            "C": "They can get help from the Product Owner to adjust the Sprint Backlog",
            "D": "They can make any adjustments by themselves, because they own the Sprint Backlog"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "They can get help from the Product Owner to adjust the Sprint Backlog",
        "explanation": "They should be open and speak to the Product Owner about it. They can negotiate with the Product Owner about the items. The Sprint is cancelled when the Sprint Goal becomes obsolete, not when we see that we can't deliver all items. Nothing bad happens if you don't deliver everything."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following can be considered a real output of a Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "A document that describes the architecture of the software and can be used by the Developers in the rest of the project",
            "B": "A set of tests designed to be used in the next Sprint",
            "C": "An Increment of software with minor known bugs in it",
            "D": "A potentially releasable piece of software"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "A potentially releasable piece of software",
        "explanation": "If we are aware of a bug, we should fix it before calling it \"Done\". Increment is a piece of working software that meets the Definition of Done."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is responsible for engaging stakeholders?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Product Owner",
            "B": "The Project Manager",
            "C": "The Developers",
            "D": "The Scrum Master"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Owner",
        "explanation": "Engagement of stakeholders is mostly about and around the Product Backlog items. The Product Owner is responsible for the Product Backlog, so she/he has to create items that reflect maximum value. That's why this is mainly the responsibility of the Product Owner to keep them engaged. The rest of them can help in different ways, but it is mainly the Product Owner."
    },
    {
        "question": "You are the Scrum Master for a Scrum Team. One of the Developers approaches you and tells you that during the Sprint they don't complete full regression testing for all of the selected Product Backlog Items. Regression testing is part of the agreed Definition of Done. The Developers have discussed with the Product Owner and decided to change the Definition of Done (DoD) to remove regression testing. Which actions are most inappropriate? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Ask the team coaching questions. Eg. ask the Developers and the Product Owner what problem they will be solving by removing regression testing from the Definition of Done. Will this raise transparency or improve the quality of the Increment?",
            "B": "Agree with altering the Definition of Done as the Developers and Product Owner agree. We need to make our Scrum Team self-managing",
            "C": "Disagree with the Developers decision and tell them that having a better Definition of Done is important for the quality of the product, and they should follow it",
            "D": "Ask the team some powerful questions. Eg. ask the Developers and Product Owner, “Will removing regression testing from the Definition of Done allow the team to produce potentially releasable Increments at the end of every Sprint?"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Agree with altering the Definition of Done as the Developers and Product Owner agree. We need to make our Scrum Team self-managing and Disagree with the Developers decision and tell them that having a better Definition of Done is important for the quality of the product, and they should follow it",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Master serves the Scrum Team in several ways, including coaching the team members in self-management and cross-functionality. Helping the Scrum Team focus on creating high-value Increments that meet the Definition of Done. Causing the removal of impediments to the Scrum Team’s progress. Ensuring that all Scrum events take place and are positive, productive, and kept within the timebox."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. When multiple teams are working on the same product, their Sprints should start and end at the same date.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "It's not mandatory in the Scrum Guide to start and end the Sprints at the same time. That makes it much more difficult to manage the whole project. However It's not mandatory for many teams to be aligned on this, because you may need it in certain cases: maybe some teams are working on parts of the project that need longer Sprints, while others need shorter ones."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements could be outputs of the Sprint Planning meeting? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Items selected from the Product Backlog",
            "B": "Order of items in the Product Backlog",
            "C": "Estimations for the sizes of items",
            "D": "Tasks",
            "E": "Resource assignment"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Items selected from the Product Backlog and Tasks",
        "explanation": "Sprint Planning is an event that answers three questions: \"Why is this Sprint valuable?\", \"What can be Done this Sprint?\" and \"How will the chosen work get done?\" Tasks and Items from Product Backlog are the only options that can be obtained from these questions of the Sprint Planning event."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements describe something that may be done in the Sprint Retrospective meeting? (Select the best three answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Calculate Velocity",
            "B": "Discuss techniques used to facilitate the Sprint Retrospective meeting",
            "C": "Discuss the composition of the team",
            "D": "Refining the Product Backlog",
            "E": "Discuss the Product Backlog items for the next Sprint",
            "F": "Discuss tools used to communicate with remote team members"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C",
            "F"
        ],
        "answers": "Discuss techniques used to facilitate the Sprint Retrospective meeting and Discuss the composition of the team and Discuss tools used to communicate with remote team members",
        "explanation": "Calculate Velocity is usually something that you do before Sprint Review meetings. Refinement is done continuously during the Sprint. Product Backlog items for the next Sprint is not something to discuss during Sprint Retrospectives, Sprint Review could be a better place. Sprint Retrospective is about the way we work. It's about the things that affect the product, but we don't discuss the product directly. It's about the context, not the content."
    },
    {
        "question": "What would likely happen if management only changed the organization’s current terminology to fit Scrum without the proper understanding and support of Scrum as defined in the Scrum Guide?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The organization may not realize the real benefits of Scrum as there would be no real change on the way the teams work",
            "B": "Organizations may feel less stressed as the behaviors would remain familiar to management",
            "C": "None of the answers apply",
            "D": "Very little change will happen as the vocabulary in Scrum is specifically defined for implementing Serum",
            "E": "All answers apply"
        },
        "answer": [
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "All answers apply",
        "explanation": "The defined terminology in Scrum was selected, designed, and defined specifically for supporting the Scrum Framework. Understanding the differences between traditional methods and the Scrum Framework will help move teams in the right direction in Scrum adoption."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are Scrum Pillars?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Courage",
            "B": "Inspection",
            "C": "Creativity",
            "D": "Adaptation",
            "E": "Transparency",
            "F": "Commitment"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "D",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Inspection and Adaptation and Transparency",
        "explanation": "Pillars are transparency, inspection, and adaptation. Make sure you're not confusing these pillars with the Scrum values commitment, courage, focus, openness and respect."
    },
    {
        "question": "If a Scrum Team has one week Sprints, when should we have a potentially releasable product?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Often during the Sprint",
            "B": "When the Product Owner finds it necessary",
            "C": "Every 3 to 5 Sprints",
            "D": "After each Hardening Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Often during the Sprint",
        "explanation": "There are no hardening Sprints. There should be at least one Increment at the end of each Sprint that is potentially releasable. The shorter the feedback loop the better."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct when four teams are working on a product? (Select the best three answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "There can be multiple Scrum Masters",
            "B": "There can be multiple Product Owners",
            "C": "There is only one Product Backlog",
            "D": "There can be multiple Product Backlogs",
            "E": "There are multiple Sprint Backlogs each Sprint",
            "F": "There is only one Sprint Backlog each Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "There can be multiple Scrum Masters and There is only one Product Backlog and There are multiple Sprint Backlogs each Sprint",
        "explanation": "Product Owners is one person not a committee and he/she owns one single Product Backlog. Each team has separate Sprint Backlog and Scrum Events and the Product Owner assists each one of them."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is responsible for explaining the Product Backlog items?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Scrum Master",
            "B": "Customer",
            "C": "Product Owner",
            "D": "The Developers are self-managed and have to talk to anyone necessary, and find out the meanings of items",
            "E": "User representatives"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Product Owner",
        "explanation": "It's one of the responsibilities of the Product Owner to explain what each item in the Product Backlog means and make sure that everyone has the right understanding. This is done when the item is first defined, and also during the Sprint and/or refinement when the Developers are working on the item and may have doubts."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Developers should be cross-functional",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "The whole Scrum Team is cross-functional, meaning the members have all the skills necessary to create value each Sprint, as stated in the Scrum Guide (not just the Developers)."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Time can be allocated between two Sprints for integration.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Each Sprint starts immediately after the previous one. There's nothing between the two Sprints. It should be continuous integration. Something is not Done unless it's integrated and it is released in the Sprint. There are no Integration Sprints."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is correct about the Sprint Backlog?",
        "options": {
            "A": "It has just enough details",
            "B": "It has no details",
            "C": "It has all the details"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "It has just enough details",
        "explanation": "Both Sprint Backlog and Product Backlog evolve more information as time passes, so they have just enough information to move to the next stage e.g. during refinement, Sprint Planning etc."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Developers have realized that one of the planned tasks in the Sprint Backlog is not needed anymore. What should they do?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Inform the Product Owner, so that he/she can cancel the Sprint",
            "B": "Remove it if it’s OK with the Product Owner",
            "C": "Keep it, but inform the Product Owner",
            "D": "Ask the Product Owner to remove it"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Remove it if it’s OK with the Product Owner",
        "explanation": "The Developers own the Sprint Backlog, and they make changes to it. They don't even have to ask the Product Owner, if it's about a non-functional requirement. Product Owner's consultation is needed when it's about functions/features. Sprints are cancelled when the Sprint Goal becomes obsolete, it's not the case here."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is not a feedback loop in Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Sprint Review",
            "B": "All answers apply",
            "C": "None of the answers apply",
            "D": "Sprint Planning",
            "E": "Sprint Retrospective",
            "F": "Product Backlog refinement"
        },
        "answer": [
            "F"
        ],
        "answers": "Product Backlog refinement",
        "explanation": "Sprint Planning, Daily Scrum, Sprint Review, and Sprint Retrospective are formal opportunities for inspecting and adapting, and are considered \"feedback loops\"."
    },
    {
        "question": "What's the role of a Product Owner during Sprint Retrospectives?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Summarizing and report the results of the meeting to stakeholders",
            "B": "Participating as a Scrum Team member",
            "C": "None of the answers apply",
            "D": "They should not participate in this meeting",
            "E": "Capturing requirements for the Product Backlog",
            "F": "All answers apply"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Participating as a Scrum Team member",
        "explanation": "The whole Scrum Team can participate in the Sprint Retrospective and they work together to see how they can improve the way they work in the next Sprint. There is no difference between PRoduct Owner, Developer or Scrum Master."
    },
    {
        "question": "What should be the timebox of Sprint Retrospective when there are 6 Developers in the team and Sprints are two weeks long?",
        "options": {
            "A": "4 hours",
            "B": "3 hours",
            "C": "8 hours",
            "D": "1.5 hours"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "3 hours",
        "explanation": "The Sprint Retrospective is timeboxed to a maximum of three hours for a one-month Sprint. For shorter Sprints, the event is usually shorter. Note that the duration of events is not dependent on the number of Developers."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who should know the least about the progress toward a business objective or a release, and be able to explain the alternatives most clearly?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Project Manager",
            "B": "The Developers",
            "C": "The Product Owner",
            "D": "The Scrum Master"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "B",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "The Project Manager and The Developers and The Scrum Master",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is the sole person responsible for managing the Product Backlog, which includes that the Product Backlog is visible, transparent, and clear to all, and shows what the Scrum Team will work on next. Make sure you have noticed the word \"least\" in the question."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which are two good approaches for the Developers to make non-functional requirements visible?",
        "options": {
            "A": "QA must run integration and regression tests before the end of the Sprint",
            "B": "Add them to the Product Backlog and keep the Product Owner informed of the estimated effort",
            "C": "Create one special Product Backlog only for these requirements",
            "D": "Add them to the acceptance criteria as part of the Definition of Done"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Add them to the Product Backlog and keep the Product Owner informed of the estimated effort and Add them to the acceptance criteria as part of the Definition of Done",
        "explanation": "Non-functional requirements should be visible to the Product Owner. The Product Owner is the sole person responsible for managing the Product Backlog but always can and must consider the feedback and opinion from other stakeholders including the Developers who can influence to add new items in Product Backlog."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who tracks the remaining work of a current Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Developers",
            "B": "The Project Manager",
            "C": "The Product Owner",
            "D": "Stakeholders",
            "E": "The Solution Architect",
            "F": "The Team Leader"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "The Developers",
        "explanation": "Developers should be able to self-manage their work, they own the Sprint Backlog."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following best describes Sprint Planning?",
        "options": {
            "A": "What to do and who will do it?",
            "B": "What can be done and how to do it?",
            "C": "What went wrong in the last Sprint and what to do about it?",
            "D": "Who will be in the team this Sprint?"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "What can be done and how to do it?",
        "explanation": "Sprint Planning is about three topics: Why is this Sprint valuable?, What can be Done this Sprint? and How will the chosen work get done?"
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Having the team members and a complete Product Backlog are the only things needed to start the project.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "The Product Backlog is never complete. It's always evolving in adaptive methods."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. All Developers should be cross-functional.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "The whole Scrum Team has to be cross-functional, not the individuals inside the team."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Product Backlog only contains functional features.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Product Backlog can also have non-functional features and the Product Owner is still accountable for them."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is correct about the length of Sprints?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Sprint length is set during Sprint Planning, and is long enough for programming and testing all items, but not for integrating them",
            "B": "All Sprints must be one month or less",
            "C": "The length can change as part of self-managing Scrum Teams, depending on the DevOps Team",
            "D": "Sprint length is set during Sprint Planning, and is long enough to develop all items in the Sprint Backlog"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "All Sprints must be one month or less",
        "explanation": "One month is the maximum timeboxed duration for Sprints in the Scrum Guide."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Besides the normal items that are about the features of the product, each Sprint Backlog can contain one item about improving the way Developers work.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "They can add an item if they think it's necessary but it's not mandatory. However if the team finds it useful they can add it, there is nothing in the Scrum Guide that prohibits this."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct about Product Backlog refinement? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "It should be done right before Sprint Planning",
            "B": "It can be an ongoing process if Developers need more time to know more",
            "C": "It can be part of Retrospective",
            "D": "Multiple teams may participate in it",
            "E": "The Scrum Master should facilitate it",
            "F": "Normally, it doesn’t take more than 10% of the Product Owner’s time"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "It can be an ongoing process if Developers need more time to know more and Multiple teams may participate in it",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Master facilitates as requested or required, not by default, but the Product Owner is more likely to facilitate this meeting, since he/she knows more about the Product Backlog items. As stated in the Scrum Guide \"Product Backlog refinement is the act of breaking down and further defining Product Backlog items into smaller more precise items. This is an ongoing activity to add details, such as a description, order, and size.\""
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. When the team becomes mature enough in using Scrum, they won't need a Scrum Master anymore.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "A Scrum Master is always needed, maybe he will contribute less but he is still needed."
    },
    {
        "question": "A Scrum project is supposed to have two releases one in the middle and the other at the end of the project. Which of the following statements is correct?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Increments are created for investigation and adaptation; they don’t have to be releasable",
            "B": "Having releasable Increments depends on the operations’ preference",
            "C": "Increments that are created before each release should be releasable",
            "D": "All Increments should be releasable"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "All Increments should be releasable",
        "explanation": "All Increments must be potentially releasable to enable usable feedback, regardless of the actual releases we may have."
    },
    {
        "question": "During the Sprint Review, one of the stakeholders announces that due to recent market changes, there is risk that funding might be reduced for the project. This triggers tensions to rise and arguments to break out between members. As a Scrum Master, what would be the best two actions to take? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Inform everyone that the team needs to stay busy until the information is formally announced",
            "B": "Avoid getting involved as it is the Product Owner’s responsibility to manage stakeholder expectations",
            "C": "Defend the original budget and request the stakeholders to adhere to the original agreed funding for the product",
            "D": "Be objective and request for a short break for people to calm down",
            "E": "Encourage the stakeholders and Product Owner to focus on delivering the highest value items for the next Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Be objective and request for a short break for people to calm down and Encourage the stakeholders and Product Owner to focus on delivering the highest value items for the next Sprint",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Master is responsible for promoting and supporting Scrum by helping everyone embody the values of commitment, courage, focus, openness and respect."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. It's allowed to have Team Leaders when many Developers are working on a complex project with multiple Scrum Teams.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "It's not allowed to introduce new accountabilities or titles such as \"Team Leader\" in Scrum."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Each Sprint Backlog may contain an item about improving the way we work.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "It is not mandatory in the Scrum, but if the Scrum Team finds it useful they can do it, it's not prohibited."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Developers are responsible for composing the Definition of Ready.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "There is no official Definition of Ready in the Scrum Guide. However there is a part in the guide that mentions the meaning of a \"ready\" item, but not such a definition as Definition of Ready. The Scrum Guide states \"Product Backlog items that can be Done by the Scrum Team within one Sprint are deemed ready for selection in a Sprint Planning event.\""
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The first Sprint can start as soon as the Product Backlog is complete.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "The Product Backlog is never complete. It's always evolving in adaptive methods."
    },
    {
        "question": "The customer goes to the Developers in the middle of a Sprint and asks them to add an important item to the Sprint Backlog. What should they do?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Refer the customer to the Product Owner",
            "B": "Add the item to the current Sprint Backlog",
            "C": "Replace one of the existing items in the Sprint Backlog with the new one",
            "D": "Reject the request"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Refer the customer to the Product Owner",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is the only person responsible for the items and the order in which they are developed."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is not correct about the Product Owner accountability?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Is cross-functional",
            "B": "Is responsible for maximizing the value of the product",
            "C": "Answers questions about the items in the Sprint Backlog",
            "D": "Explains the Product Backlog items"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Is cross-functional",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner explains the Product Backlog items The whole Scrum Team is cross-functional, not the Product Owner by herself/himself. The primary responsibility of the Product Owner is to maximize the value of the product that is developed. Make sure that you have noticed the word \"not\" in the question."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following limits work in progress?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Using timeboxes",
            "B": "Having Sprint Retrospectives",
            "C": "Using Product Backlogs",
            "D": "Having Sprint Reviews"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Using timeboxes",
        "explanation": "When using timeboxes, you have a rather small and relatively clear scope for the timebox, and your goal is to complete as many items as possible. This limits the amount of work you can have in progress."
    },
    {
        "question": "When is it time to integrate the code?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Frequently, during the Sprint",
            "B": "At the end of the project",
            "C": "Before each release",
            "D": "At the end of each Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Frequently, during the Sprint",
        "explanation": "You can't know if the code will work properly, unless you integrate it with the rest of the code. That's why we have continuous integration."
    },
    {
        "question": "How would you know if Developers are cross-functional?",
        "options": {
            "A": "They can create releasable Increments each Sprint",
            "B": "They can do Test Driven Development if they decide to",
            "C": "They can do Pair-Programming if they decide to",
            "D": "Each Developer is expert in all technical layers of the system"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "They can create releasable Increments each Sprint",
        "explanation": "Cross-functional Developers must have all skills needed to create a releasable Increments every Sprint. A cross-functional Scrum Team is one that has all types of expertise that is required to develop the product. Note that the whole Scrum Team should be cross-functional, not individual team members. e.g. in this scenario here we could assume that Product Owner and Scrum Master are Developers as well."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is correct about the Scrum Team?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Engages the stakeholders",
            "B": "Is responsible for measuring the performance of the project",
            "C": "All answers apply",
            "D": "Is self-managed",
            "E": "None of the answers apply",
            "F": "Is responsible for maximizing the value of the product"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Is self-managed",
        "explanation": "The whole Scrum Team is self-managed, as stated in the Scrum Guide. The Product Owners measure the performance of the project to maximize the value of the product that is developed."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Inspection is a Scrum Value.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Pillars are transparency, inspection, and adaptation. Make sure you're not mixing them with the Scrum Values commitment, courage, focus, openness, and respect."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who can decide to add more work to the Sprint Backlog during the Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Management",
            "B": "The Developers",
            "C": "The Scrum Master",
            "D": "The Product Owner",
            "E": "The Scrum Team"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "The Developers",
        "explanation": "After the Sprint Planning the items pulled from Product Backlog, they can’t change. However in the Sprint Backlog the broken down tasks created by the Developers to complete the work are always changing and adapting according to their practices, techniques, and knowledge."
    },
    {
        "question": "What happens between a Sprint Retrospective and the next Sprint Planning meeting?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Getting customer approval for the previous Increment",
            "B": "A lot of events could happen, depending of what has been agreed from the Scrum Team, since they are self-managed",
            "C": "Nothing",
            "D": "Product Backlog refinement",
            "E": "Refactoring the previous Increment"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Nothing",
        "explanation": "Refinement is an ongoing process. Refactoring is done during the Sprints; we can't revisit the previous ones. Each Sprint starts immediately after the previous one, there's no space between the two."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best describes good ways to address security concerns? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Add them to the Product Backlog",
            "B": "Add them to the Definition of Done",
            "C": "Get help from responsible departments to ensure those concerns",
            "D": "Have special Sprints that ensure those concerns"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Add them to the Product Backlog and Add them to the Definition of Done",
        "explanation": "Add them in the Product Backlog if it's about the performance of an existing function. If it's something that applies to many items and determines the way functional features work it would be a good choice to add them in the Definition of Done. There are no \"special\" Sprints such as hardening Sprints or integration Sprints."
    },
    {
        "question": "When does a Product Owner cancel a Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "When not enough information is available for the items in the Sprint Backlog",
            "B": "When the Sprint Goal becomes obsolete",
            "C": "When there’s an unsolved technical dependency",
            "D": "When not enough resources are available for the project"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "When the Sprint Goal becomes obsolete",
        "explanation": "As stated in the Scrum Guide \"A Sprint could be cancelled if the Sprint Goal becomes obsolete. Only the Product Owner has the authority to cancel the Sprint.\""
    },
    {
        "question": "What does a burn-down chart measure?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Work remaining across time",
            "B": "The amount of business value delivered to the customer",
            "C": "Work that is done based on the Definition of Done",
            "D": "Cost of the project across time"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Work remaining across time",
        "explanation": "A burndown chart is a graphic representation of how quickly the team is working through Sprint Backlog across time."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are formal opportunities for inspecting and adapting? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Burn-down chart",
            "B": "Daily Scrum",
            "C": "Sprint Retrospective",
            "D": "Product Backlog refinement"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Daily Scrum and Sprint Retrospective",
        "explanation": "Sprint Planning, Daily Scrum, Sprint Review, and Sprint Retrospective are formal opportunities for inspecting and adapting and considered \"feedback loops\"."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Product Owner is not getting well with the Developers. Developers are not happy with the Product Owner for changing the requirements all the time and not being available to answer their questions and provide clarifications. The Product Owner is too upset with the Developers for changing requirements during the implementation process. What does the Scrum Master do?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Check with each person’s functional manager to suggest to their employees that they should collaborate in a better way and if they don’t they might be removed from the team",
            "B": "Scrum Master’s accountability is to protect the Developers all the time. Ask for a project manager or another external instance to interfere and possibly temporarily take over from the Product Owner his job",
            "C": "None of the answers apply",
            "D": "Try to address why requirements change in the Sprint Retrospective. Ask the Developers and the Product Owner to talk about why and consider the impact of the changes on value. This will also make the team cohesive",
            "E": "Take everyone to a 1-day offsite event to relax, re-align and resolve the conflict",
            "F": "All answers apply"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Try to address why requirements change in the Sprint Retrospective. Ask the Developers and the Product Owner to talk about why and consider the impact of the changes on value. This will also make the team cohesive",
        "explanation": "Try to address why requirements change in the Sprint Retrospective. Ask the Developers and the Product Owner to talk about why and consider the impact of the changes on value. Coach the team to resolve these issues amongst themselves and facilitate if necessary."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best describes the Scrum Pillar of Inspection.",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Scrum artifacts and the progress toward agreed goals must be inspected frequently and diligently to detect potentially undesirable variances or problems",
            "B": "If any aspects of a process deviate outside acceptable limits or if the resulting product is unacceptable, the process being applied or the materials being produced must be adjusted",
            "C": "The emergent process and work must be visible to those performing the work as well as those receiving the work",
            "D": "None of the answers apply"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "The Scrum artifacts and the progress toward agreed goals must be inspected frequently and diligently to detect potentially undesirable variances or problems",
        "explanation": "As stated in the Scrum Guide: \"The Scrum artifacts and the progress toward agreed goals must be inspected frequently and diligently to detect potentially undesirable variances or problems. To help with inspection, Scrum provides cadence in the form of its five events. Inspection enables adaptation. Inspection without adaptation is considered pointless. Scrum events are designed to provoke change.\""
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. It's up to the self-managing team to decide which Scrum events are needed in the project.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Self-management is not unlimited, they should follow the Scrum framework."
    },
    {
        "question": "The performance of the Sprint should be measured at least _____________",
        "options": {
            "A": "Once a week",
            "B": "Before or after each release",
            "C": "Once a day",
            "D": "Once a Sprint",
            "E": "Before and after each release"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The performance of the Sprint should be measured at least Once a day",
        "explanation": "The performance of the project should be measured at least once per Sprint by the Product Owner, and the Sprint performance should be measured daily by the Developers."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is not correct about the Developers?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Can make changes to the Sprint Backlog",
            "B": "Can be cross-functional",
            "C": "Prioritizes tasks in the Sprint Backlog",
            "D": "Manage the Product Backlog"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Manage the Product Backlog",
        "explanation": "Both the Developers and the whole Scrum Team are cross-functional, but of course you can have Developers playing the Product Owner and Scrum Master accountability, so Developers can be cross-functional. The Product Backlog is owned and managed by the Product Owner. Developers own the Sprint Backlog, and are the only accountability that can make changes to it."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Since the Product Owner is accountable for the value of the product, they have the final say over the Definition of Done.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "The whole Scrum Team is responsible for the Definition of Done not the Product Owner."
    },
    {
        "question": "A company that is mature in using Scrum and also has a PMO. What should be the accountability of the PMO?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Manages portfolios and programs and facilitates the application of techniques that complement Serum",
            "B": "There’s no place for a PMO in such an organization",
            "C": "The PMO should manage and help Scrum Masters",
            "D": "The PMO will be responsible for making higher level decisions in the project"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Manages portfolios and programs and facilitates the application of techniques that complement Serum",
        "explanation": "Remember that there are limits to the self-management of the team and the important thing is to have the power within the borders of the project. However, each project is run in a wider organization with multiple levels of management impacting the project, and it's not possible or even acceptable to reject that structure, as long as it doesn't block internal self-management of the team and the fundamental adaptive approach of the project."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Daily Scrums are held at the same time and same place every day.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "As stated in the Scrum Guide \"To reduce complexity, it is held at the same time and place every working day of the Sprint.\""
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is a formal opportunity for inspecting and adapting?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Product Backlog refinement",
            "B": "Sprint Review",
            "C": "Release Planning",
            "D": "Burn-down chart"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Sprint Review",
        "explanation": "Sprint Planning, Daily Scrum, Sprint Review, and Sprint Retrospective are formal opportunities for inspecting and adapting and they are considered feedback loops."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. When multiple teams are working on one product, they should select work from the same Product Backlog.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "When there are multiple teams on the same product it should be only one Product Backlog and one Product Owner to make decisions for it."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Scrum Master shouldn't allow the Developers to start working without having the tasks identified and assigned to themselves.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Scrum Master doesn't order people to do something, he/she should teach them and coach them to understand how it should work and convince them to do the right thing. The Product Owner can't order Developers to do things either. Second, most of the tasks are identified and assigned gradually during the Sprint. Developers own the Sprint Backlog and they should do it by themselves.\n\nChapter 6: PSPOTM I Full Mock Test 5\nTime Limit: 60 minutes        No. of Questions: 80."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The purpose of each Sprint is to release a piece of working software.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "The purpose is to create a potentially releasable piece of software. It doesn't have to be released, it's an Increment."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following services are appropriate for a Scrum Master in regard to the Daily Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Lead the discussions of the Developers",
            "B": "Ensure that all 3 questions have been answered",
            "C": "All answers apply",
            "D": "Teach the Developers to keep the Daily Scrum within the 15 minute timebox",
            "E": "Facilitate in a way that ensures each team member has a chance to speak",
            "F": "None of the answers apply"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Teach the Developers to keep the Daily Scrum within the 15 minute timebox",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Master ensures that the Developers have the meeting, but they are responsible for conducting the Daily Scrum. The Scrum Master teaches the Developers to keep the Daily Scrum within the 15-minute timebox. The Scrum Master enforces the rule that only Developers participate in the Daily Scrum."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Scrum does not scale to large teams",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Scrum can be applied to multiple teams, known as Scaled Scrum."
    },
    {
        "question": "The CEO asks the Developers to add a \"very important\" item to a Sprint that is in progress. What should the Developers do?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Add the item to the current Sprint and drop an item of equal size",
            "B": "Add the item to the next Sprint",
            "C": "Add the item to the current Sprint without any adjustments",
            "D": "Inform the Product Owner so he/she can work with the CEO"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Inform the Product Owner so he/she can work with the CEO",
        "explanation": "The items selected for a Sprint have been selected as most valuable with the Product Owner. The items serve the Sprint's goal. No changes should be made that endanger the Sprint Goal. No one external to the Scrum Team can force changes on the Developers."
    },
    {
        "question": "How much work must Developers do to a Product Backlog item they select for a Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "As much as they have been told by the Product Owner will be done for every Product Backlog item they select in conformance with the Definition of Done",
            "B": "All development work and at least some testing",
            "C": "As much as they can fit into the Sprint",
            "D": "Analysis, design, programming, testing and documentation"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "As much as they have been told by the Product Owner will be done for every Product Backlog item they select in conformance with the Definition of Done",
        "explanation": "The purpose of each Sprint is to deliver Increments of potentially releasable functionality that adhere to the Scrum Team's current definition of \"Done\"."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The purpose of all Sprints is to create an Increment of work that meets the Definition of Done, a piece of working software usable and potentially releasable, however team doesn't need release every Sprint, but eventually, the team must release its work.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "The purpose of all Sprints is to create an Increment of Done work, a piece of working software usable and potentially releasable. However, the team doesn't need to release every Sprint, but eventually the team must release its work otherwise there is no point in doing the work for something that will never be released."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Product Owner should determine how many items should be selected for the Sprint Backlog in the Sprint.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "It's only up to the self-managing Scrum Team to decide how many items they will select for the Sprint Backlog, not the Product Owner by himself/herself."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Product Owner has some concerns about the Definition of Done. What should they do?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Adjust the Definition of Done immediately",
            "B": "Discuss it in the next Sprint Retrospective meeting",
            "C": "None of the answers apply",
            "D": "Have the team adjust it at the end of the Sprint",
            "E": "Adjust the Definition of Done at the end of the Sprint",
            "F": "All answers apply"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Discuss it in the next Sprint Retrospective meeting",
        "explanation": "It's better to wait until the end of the Sprint before changing the Definition of Done. The Product Owner can present ideas, opinions, and arguments about the change, but the decision belongs to the whole Scrum Team."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes the Sprint Review?",
        "options": {
            "A": "It is when the Scrum Team and stakeholders inspect the outcome of a Sprint and figure out what to do next",
            "B": "It is a demo at the end of the Sprint for everyone in the organization to check on the work done",
            "C": "It is a mechanism to control the Developers’ activities during a Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "It is when the Scrum Team and stakeholders inspect the outcome of a Sprint and figure out what to do next",
        "explanation": "Scrum Events in Scrum are opportunities to inspect and adapt."
    },
    {
        "question": "Select the Scrum Values:",
        "options": {
            "A": "Commitment, Courage, Focus, Openness, Respect",
            "B": "Individuals and Iteration, Working Software, Customer Collaboration, Responding to Change",
            "C": "Simplicity, Communication, Feedback, Respect, Courage",
            "D": "Transparency, Inspection, Adaptation"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Commitment, Courage, Focus, Openness, Respect",
        "explanation": "The Scrum values named in the Scrum guide are Commitment, Courage, Focus, Openness, Respect. The Scrum Theory Pillars are Transparency, Inspection, Adaptation."
    },
    {
        "question": "When does Product Backlog refinement occur?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Between Sprints",
            "B": "During Sprint Planning",
            "C": "During the Sprint, in preparation for the next Sprint(s)",
            "D": "During Sprint 0"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "During the Sprint, in preparation for the next Sprint(s)",
        "explanation": "Product Backlog refinement is the act of breaking down and further defining Product Backlog items into smaller more precise items. This is an ongoing activity to add details, such as a description, order, and size. Attributes often vary with the domain of work."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "A cookbook that defines best practices for software development",
            "B": "Scrum is a lightweight framework that helps people, teams and",
            "C": "organizations generate value through adaptive solutions for complex problems",
            "D": "A defined and predictive process that conforms to the principles of Scientific Management",
            "E": "A complete methodology that defines how to develop software"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Scrum is a lightweight framework that helps people, teams and",
        "explanation": "Scrum is not a process or a technique for building products, it is a framework within which you can employ various processes and techniques. As stated in the Scrum Guide \"Scrum is a lightweight framework that helps people, teams and organizations generate value through adaptive solutions for complex problems.\""
    },
    {
        "question": "If you are trying to find a \"formal opportunity to inspect and adapt\" in Scrum, which of the following would you consider? (Select the best three answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Release Planning",
            "B": "Sprint Planning",
            "C": "Product Backlog refinement",
            "D": "Sprint Review",
            "E": "Sprint Retrospective"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "D",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Sprint Planning and Sprint Review and Sprint Retrospective",
        "explanation": "Sprint Planning, Daily Scrum, Sprint Review, and Sprint Retrospective are \"formal opportunities for inspecting and adapting\", and are considered \"feedback loops\". Note that \"formal opportunity\" means \"serious opportunity\" or \"important opportunity\" here, and those are not \"formal meetings\", meaning that we don't exchange signatures and worry about contractual aspects during them."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The purpose of a Sprint is to produce an Increment of working software.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "The heart of Scrum is a Sprint, a timebox of one month or less during which a \"Done\", usable, and potentially releasable product Increment should be created."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following actions do not occur during the first Sprint? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Finalize the complete Product Backlog",
            "B": "Create potentially releasable software",
            "C": "Develop something of value to the customer",
            "D": "Define the complete architecture"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Finalize the complete Product Backlog and Define the complete architecture",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Team should develop at least one Increment that could potentially be released. Make sure you have noticed the word \"not\" in the question."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Developers should have all the skills needed to __________",
        "options": {
            "A": "Complete the project as estimated when the date and cost are committed to the Product Owner",
            "B": "Turn the Product Backlog items it selects into an Increment of potentially releasable product functionality",
            "C": "Do all of the development work, except for specialized testing that requires additional tools and environments"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "The Developers should have all the skills needed to Turn the Product Backlog items it selects into an Increment of potentially releasable product functionality",
        "explanation": "The Developers consist of professionals who do the work of delivering a potentially releasable Increment that meet the Definition of Done. Scrum Teams are cross-functional, with all of the skills as a team necessary to create a product Increment."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Sprint Review can impact the Sprint Planning meeting.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "It's true because in the Sprint Review the Scrum Team and stakeholders review what was accomplished in the Sprint and what has changed in their environment. Based on this information, attendees collaborate on what to do next, which is something that is planned during Sprint Planning."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Scrum Team should choose at least one high priority process improvement, identified during the Sprint Retrospective, and place it in the Product Backlog.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "False, this used to be true with the previous version of the Scrum Guide. However we should underline that if the team finds it useful they can do it, it's not prohibited."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct about the Definition of Done? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "It helps the Product Owner measure the progress of the Sprint work",
            "B": "Can be improved during the project",
            "C": "There should be one Definition of Done when multiple teams are working on the same project",
            "D": "Describes the purpose of each Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Can be improved during the project and There should be one Definition of Done when multiple teams are working on the same project",
        "explanation": "If there are multiple Scrum Teams working together on a product, they must mutually define and comply with the same Definition of Done and of course they can improve it as they learn more."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Developers are ready to start the first Sprint, but the Product Backlog is not ready yet. What should the Product Owner do?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Ask the Developers to help refine the Product Backlog instead of starting the first Sprint",
            "B": "Let the Sprint begin, but only with the goal of completing the Product Backlog",
            "C": "Let the team start the first Sprint, and continue refining the Product Backlog"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Let the team start the first Sprint, and continue refining the Product Backlog",
        "explanation": "First, remember that the Product Backlog is never complete, and you don't have to wait until you have everything in the Product Backlog to start the first Sprint. However, this question says that the backlog is not ready, which probably means that the items at the top are too large and/or unclear. Again, having unready items is not a reason to wait, it's undesirable though, but you can refine them during the Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "Developers should not be interrupted during the Sprint. The Sprint Goal should remain intact. These are conditions that foster creativity, quality and productivity. Based on this, which of the following is not right.",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Product Owner can help clarify or optimize the Sprint when asked by the Developers",
            "B": "The Developers may work with the Product Owner to remove or add work if it finds it has more or less capacity than it expected",
            "C": "The Sprint Backlog is fully formulated in the Sprint Planning meeting and does not change during the Sprint",
            "D": "As a decomposition of the selected Product Backlog Items, the Sprint Backlog changes and may grow as the work emerges"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The Sprint Backlog is fully formulated in the Sprint Planning meeting and does not change during the Sprint",
        "explanation": "Sprint Backlog can change only from the Developers as more is learnt during the Sprint. Only the Developers can change it, not someone externally. Make sure you have noticed the word \"not\" in the question."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is responsible for managing the progress of work during a Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The most junior member of the Team",
            "B": "The Scrum Master",
            "C": "The Developers",
            "D": "The Product Owner"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The Developers",
        "explanation": "The Developers use the Daily Scrum to inspect progress toward the Sprint Goal and to inspect how progress is trending toward completing the work in the Sprint Backlog and they are responsible for it."
    },
    {
        "question": "Select the most appropriate ways that the Product Owner can use to inspect the Increment. (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "By reviewing the Product Backlog during refinement",
            "B": "By inviting stakeholders to give feedback in the Sprint review",
            "C": "By presenting the status of the Product Backlog during the Sprint Review",
            "D": "By attending the Sprint Retrospective"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "By inviting stakeholders to give feedback in the Sprint review and By presenting the status of the Product Backlog during the Sprint Review",
        "explanation": "At the Sprint Review the Product Owner shares the current state of Product Backlog, which, combined with the inspection of the Increment. This leads to an updated Product Backlog."
    },
    {
        "question": "The timebox of this Scrum Event should be no more than three hours.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Sprint Review",
            "B": "Sprint Planning",
            "C": "Sprint Retrospective",
            "D": "Release Planning",
            "E": "Release Sprint",
            "F": "Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Sprint Retrospective",
        "explanation": "The Sprint Retrospective concludes the Sprint. It is timeboxed to a maximum of three hours for a one-month Sprint. For shorter Sprints, the event is usually shorter."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Only the Scrum Team is allowed to attend the Sprint Planning.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Sprint Planning is attended by the entire Scrum Team. Stakeholders may attend by invitation of the team, it is not prohibited."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Sprint Goal and the Sprint Backlog are the outputs of the Sprint Planning meeting.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "The whole Scrum Team then collaborates to define a Sprint Goal that communicates why the Sprint is valuable to stakeholders. The Sprint Goal must be finalized prior to the end of Sprint Planning. Sprint Backlog should be determined as well."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is responsible for maximizing the value of Product Backlog?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The customer",
            "B": "The Scrum Master",
            "C": "The Product Owner",
            "D": "The Scrum Team",
            "E": "The stakeholders"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Owner",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner manages the Product Backlog, so it's up to her/him to decide the order. She/He should do it based on the value of the Items, remember the PO is also known as value maximizer."
    },
    {
        "question": "In the middle of a Sprint, the customer asks for two important new features. Which of the following statements are inappropriate actions the Product Owner can take? (Select the best three answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Ask the Scrum Master to add the items to the Sprint Backlog",
            "B": "Add the items to the Product Backlog",
            "C": "Reject the request, because it’s in the middle of the Sprint",
            "D": "Ask the Developers if they can add them to the current Sprint Backlog",
            "E": "Assign those items to Developers in the next Daily Scrum"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Ask the Scrum Master to add the items to the Sprint Backlog and Reject the request, because it’s in the middle of the Sprint and Assign those items to Developers in the next Daily Scrum",
        "explanation": "Only the Developers assign work to themselves, and their work items come from the Sprint Backlog. Only the Developers make changes to the Sprint Backlog."
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the classic questions of Daily Scrums, if you decide to go through them? (Select the best three answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "What work am I going to do today to help the team achieve its goal?",
            "B": "What problems did I have yesterday?",
            "C": "What impediments are in my way or in the way of the team?",
            "D": "How many hours did I spend on the project yesterday?",
            "E": "What work did I do yesterday to help the team achieve its goal?",
            "F": "Are we able to deliver all Sprint Backlog items by the end of the Sprint?"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "What work am I going to do today to help the team achieve its goal? and What impediments are in my way or in the way of the team? and What work did I do yesterday to help the team achieve its goal?",
        "explanation": "It's not mandatory to use these questions, but very common and recommended."
    },
    {
        "question": "Raffaele is a Scrum Master helping an organization to establish five Scrum Teams that will be developing a product. Raffaele discusses with the teams the high level of integration that the product Increment will require by the end of their first Sprint. It is a highly anticipated product, both by consumers and by the organization. Of the options raised by the future team members, which option should Raffaele encourage?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Each Scrum Team delivers done Increments in its own area of responsibility. Upon functional acceptance at the Sprint Review, the code is isolated for future stabilization. The release date is adjusted according to the expected work and time of such integration phase",
            "B": "Each team provides a separate Increment with the functionality added by the individual team. The Sprint Review is used to identify the work needed to integrate with the other teams. This work is then added to the Product Backlog",
            "C": "In the first Sprint, integration ¡s less important. The goal is to deliver business value. Functionality that is not integrated with the work of other Scrum Teams by the end of a Sprint is still reviewed to assess its potential business value. It can still be released at the Product Owner’s discretion, and silent consent of the stakeholders",
            "D": "All Scrum Teams agree on a shared Definition of Done describing all work needed to deliver an Increment for review that is the integrated sum of the work of all Scrum Teams on the initiative"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "All Scrum Teams agree on a shared Definition of Done describing all work needed to deliver an Increment for review that is the integrated sum of the work of all Scrum Teams on the initiative",
        "explanation": "As stated in the Scrum Guide \"If there are multiple Scrum Teams working together on a product, they must mutually define and comply with the same Definition of Done.\""
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct about the number of Product Owners when there are three products being developed using Scrum? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "There can be a different Product Owner for each product",
            "B": "Each product should have a separate Product Owner",
            "C": "There can be a single Product Owner for all products",
            "D": "There should be only one Product Owner working with a Development manager for both products"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "There can be a different Product Owner for each product and There can be a single Product Owner for all products",
        "explanation": "It is not mandatory to have exactly 3 people as Product Owners. Each Product should have a single Product Owner. You can also have two Product Owners for three products and one of them has to manage two products, that's why we have to be careful in the wording of the options."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is accountable to know the most about the progress toward a business objective or a release, and be able to explain clearly the alternatives?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Release Manager",
            "B": "The Scrum Master",
            "C": "The Delivery Manager",
            "D": "The Development Manager",
            "E": "The Developers",
            "F": "The Product Owner"
        },
        "answer": [
            "F"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Owner",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner needs to make sure that he keeps the Developers updated with what the clients & stakeholders need. The Scrum Master is there to coach him/her on how to do it."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following should not change during the Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Definition of Done",
            "B": "Product Backlog",
            "C": "Sprint Backlog",
            "D": "Minimum level of quality"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Minimum level of quality",
        "explanation": "Product Backlog may change at any time. The level of expected quality shouldn't decrease during the Sprint. The tasks in the Sprint Backlog are always changing as more is learnt. Also, The Scrum Guide is not against changing the \"items\" in the Sprint Backlog either. Those that stay fixed during the Sprint are needed to avoid distractions, and create a more productive environment. After all, Sprints are not so long that they create problems."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has the final say on the order of the Product Backlog?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Developers",
            "B": "The Scrum Master",
            "C": "All answers apply",
            "D": "The Stakeholders",
            "E": "The Product Owner",
            "F": "The CEO"
        },
        "answer": [
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Owner",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is the sole person responsible for managing the Product Backlog."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who must do the work required for Product Backlog items, in order to create a potentially releasable Increment?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Scrum Team",
            "B": "The Developers",
            "C": "The Scrum Master",
            "D": "The Product Owner"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "The Developers",
        "explanation": "Developers are the people in the Scrum Team that are committed to creating any aspect of a usable Increment each Sprint, as stated in the Scrum Guide."
    },
    {
        "question": "Upon what type of process control is Scrum based?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Complex",
            "B": "Hybrid",
            "C": "Empirical",
            "D": "Defined"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Empirical",
        "explanation": "Scrum is founded on empirical process control theory, or empiricism. Empiricism asserts that knowledge comes from experience and making decisions based on what is known."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. It is mandatory that the product Increment be released to production at the end of each Sprint.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "The product Increment should be usable and releasable at the end of every Sprint, but it does not have to be released. It's the Product Owner's decision to release it."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Scrum Values promote Scrum Teams to be cross-functional and have all the skills needed to build a product within the team. While starting Scrum, what would be the advantages of keeping the existing component teams (e.g. design, database, back-end, front-end)?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Component teams generally have all the skills needed to deliver shippable Increments that add business value",
            "B": "There is less communication overhead than working in feature teams",
            "C": "Component teams would have all the skills needed to focus on their specific technical layer",
            "D": "Because their productivity is already predictable, they can deliver shippable Increments more quickly than a newly formed team",
            "E": "Because they have been working together for some time, there will be less initial disruption than a newly formed team. As they begin working, they will discover what works best and how to move towards cross-functional teams"
        },
        "answer": [
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Because they have been working together for some time, there will be less initial disruption than a newly formed team. As they begin working, they will discover what works best and how to move towards cross-functional teams",
        "explanation": "The ones that will be doing the work are the best ones to decide on what Scrum Team structures work best."
    },
    {
        "question": "When does the next Sprint begin?",
        "options": {
            "A": "When the Product Owner is ready",
            "B": "Next Monday",
            "C": "Immediately following the next Sprint Planning",
            "D": "Immediately after the conclusion of the previous Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Immediately after the conclusion of the previous Sprint",
        "explanation": "A new Sprint starts immediately after the conclusion of the previous Sprint. There is no gap between them."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Each increment is independent from the previous one",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Each Increment is additive to all prior Increments and thoroughly verified, ensuring that all Increments work together. In order to provide value, the Increment must be usable."
    },
    {
        "question": "What's the commitment of the Increment?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Definition of Done",
            "B": "Sprint Goal",
            "C": "Definition of Ready",
            "D": "Product Goal"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Definition of Done",
        "explanation": "An Increment is a concrete stepping stone toward the Product Goal. Work cannot be considered part of an Increment unless it meets the Definition of Done."
    },
    {
        "question": "How does the Product Owner manage the value of the product?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Product Backlog Order",
            "B": "User Acceptance Testing",
            "C": "MoSCow Analysis",
            "D": "Customer feedback via frequent releases"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Product Backlog Order and Customer feedback via frequent releases",
        "explanation": "Product Owner's responsibility is to manage the Product Backlog, so that maximum value can be delivered. He/She can achieve this via frequent releases so that the feedback loop is as short as possible."
    },
    {
        "question": "How should a Scrum Master respond if the Product Owner plans the first Sprint to only focus on setting up the infrastructure and architecture in order to work on functionality in a subsequent Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Support the Product Owner’s decision as he/she is accountable for maximizing the value of the work that the Developers do",
            "B": "Help the Product Owner understand the value of including business functionality into every Sprint and explain to him/her that the best architecture and infrastructure emerge alongside the development of the functionality",
            "C": "Explain that one Sprint may be too short to finish the architecture and he should pre-allocate subsequent Sprints just in case",
            "D": "Add at least one technical architect to the Scrum Team to ensure the architecture can be completed in the first Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Help the Product Owner understand the value of including business functionality into every Sprint and explain to him/her that the best architecture and infrastructure emerge alongside the development of the functionality",
        "explanation": "Improving communications with the customers and stakeholders is a crucial activity in Scrum. It reduces waste from building items that add no value. Saying that, the best architectures, requirements, and designs emerge from self-managing teams."
    },
    {
        "question": "You are the Scrum Master for four Scrum Teams working on one product. Several of the Developers notify you that their teams will need full-time help from an external technical specialist Helen in the upcoming two Sprints. What key concerns should the Scrum Master take into account?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Maintaining a consistent velocity",
            "B": "The benefit of teams solving the problem themselves and the",
            "C": "ability to produce integrated Increments",
            "D": "Hiring additional resources to fill the void in the skill set",
            "E": "Having enough work for all team members"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "The benefit of teams solving the problem themselves and the",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Master needs to coach the Developers to work in a way that they don't depend on Helen and they can take ownership of this issue by themselves."
    },
    {
        "question": "Veronica is a Scrum Master of a new team that is going to start a new Project. Which of the following actions may Veronica take in starting up the Project? (Select the best three answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Ask the Developers to discuss and identify the way they are going to develop the product",
            "B": "Ensure that a bonus system is in place for the top performance of individuals",
            "C": "Ask the Developers to introduce themselves to each other and describe their skills and background",
            "D": "Ask the Product Owner to explain the project, its business needs, history, goals, and context",
            "E": "Ask the development managers to introduce their departments and capabilities",
            "F": "Ensure that team members have clear roles and responsibilities"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Ask the Developers to discuss and identify the way they are going to develop the product and Ask the Developers to introduce themselves to each other and describe their skills and background and Ask the Product Owner to explain the project, its business needs, history, goals, and context",
        "explanation": "The rest are wrong because: Having a reward system is harmful to the unity of the team. Members share accountability, and they do not have different roles and responsibilities. It has to be about the project and the people internal to it, not the external departments. Remember that the team is cross-functional and does everything needed for the project, without outside help."
    },
    {
        "question": "John is the Product Owner of two Scrum Teams. Which of the following statements are true? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Optimizing the value of the work the Developers perform",
            "B": "Is another name for the Project Manager",
            "C": "All his time must be dedicated to a single project",
            "D": "Ordering the items in the Product Backlog to best achieve goals and missions"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Optimizing the value of the work the Developers perform and Ordering the items in the Product Backlog to best achieve goals and missions",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is responsible for maximizing the value of the product resulting from work of the Developers and prioritize the Product Backlog items accordingly. There is no accountability of Project Manager or equivalent in the Scrum framework."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Developers are trying to convince Alexander the Product Owner that the Sprint should be cancelled with no obvious reason. What's the right response from Nina the Scrum Master to do?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Nina should tell the Developers that it is okay. The Product Owner knows more about it",
            "B": "Nina should encourage Alexander to discuss it with the customer first",
            "C": "Nina should be involved in making this decision",
            "D": "Nina should stop this, because the Developers do not have the authority to influence Sprint cancellation"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Nina should tell the Developers that it is okay. The Product Owner knows more about it",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is the only person who can cancel the Sprint. Developers can raise concerns but not without any specific reason. Product Owners receive input from everyone who's involved in the project when they are making their decisions and they know more about it."
    },
    {
        "question": "During a Sprint, a Scrum Team determines that it will not be able to finish the complete forecast. Who should be present to review and adjust the Sprint work selected?",
        "options": {
            "A": "None of the answers apply",
            "B": "All answers apply",
            "C": "The Product Owner and the Developers",
            "D": "The Developers",
            "E": "The Scrum Master, the project manager and the Developers",
            "F": "The Product Owner and all stakeholders"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Owner and the Developers",
        "explanation": "During the Sprint, scope may be clarified and re-negotiated between the Product Owner and Developers as more is learned."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following do the Developers do during the first Sprint? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Develop a plan for the rest of the release",
            "B": "Determine the complete architecture and infrastructure for the product",
            "C": "Deliver an Increment of potentially releasable software",
            "D": "Create the complete Product Backlog to be developed in subsequent Sprints",
            "E": "Develop and deliver at least one piece of functionality"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Deliver an Increment of potentially releasable software and Develop and deliver at least one piece of functionality",
        "explanation": "The core of Scrum is a Sprint, a timebox of one month or less during which a \"Done\", usable, and potentially releasable product Increment is created. This applies to every Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "At the beginning of the Sprint, the Developers don't have the tools and infrastructure needed to complete the current Sprint Backlog Items. What of the following statements are least appropriate for the Scrum Master to do? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Increment for current Sprint will focus on delivering infrastructure and tool acquisition",
            "B": "Improve communication between the Product Owner and Developers in order to establish a plausible Sprint Goal and a proper Definition of Done",
            "C": "Talk with the Product Owner in order to accept partially done Increments",
            "D": "Help the Developers to get tools and improve infrastructure while Definition of Done is adapted accordingly"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The Increment for current Sprint will focus on delivering infrastructure and tool acquisition and Talk with the Product Owner in order to accept partially done Increments",
        "explanation": "Infrastructure and tools are not prepared upfront, because it requires a complete understanding of the whole project and product, which is usually not the case, so we need to hold on to the adaptation pillar. The required infrastructure and tools will be prepared gradually through the project because they depend on the product we’re going to create, which in turn is defined through the project. Make sure you have noticed the \"least appropriate\" in the question."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who keeps track of the remaining work in the Product Backlog?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Product Owner",
            "B": "The Developers",
            "C": "Senior Executives",
            "D": "The Scrum Team",
            "E": "The Scrum Master",
            "F": "The CEO"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Owner",
        "explanation": "Product Owner's responsibility is to manage the Product Backlog, so that maximum value can be delivered. He/She is the one who knows more about it."
    },
    {
        "question": "You are a Scrum Master and were asked to conduct an interview by management for a new team member. Which characteristics would you look for in the candidate?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Experience as Team Leader",
            "B": "Skilled Tester",
            "C": "Team Player",
            "D": "Generalizing Specialist"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Generalizing Specialist",
        "explanation": "Generalizing Specialists are most preferred in a Scrum Team. They can perform more than one role/accountability."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the below are accountabilities on a Scrum Team?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Developers",
            "B": "Users",
            "C": "Scrum Master",
            "D": "Product Owner",
            "E": "Customers"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Developers and Scrum Master and Product Owner",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Team consists of a Product Owner, the Developers, and a Scrum Master."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the main reason for the Scrum Master to be at the Daily Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "He or she does not have to be there; he or she only has to ensure the Developers have a Daily Scrum",
            "B": "To gather status and progress information to report to management",
            "C": "To make sure every team member answers the three questions",
            "D": "To write down any changes to the Sprint Backlog, including adding new items, and tracking progress on the burn-down"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "He or she does not have to be there; he or she only has to ensure the Developers have a Daily Scrum",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Master enforces the rule that only Developers participate in the Daily Scrum. Others can join as listeners though."
    },
    {
        "question": "What represents the trend line in a burndown chart, through a Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The changes of the cost through the current Sprint",
            "B": "The amount of remaining technical debt",
            "C": "The remaining work to be completed if nothing changes on the",
            "D": "Sprint Backlog or the Scrum Team",
            "E": "The date when the Scrum Team can be released for other work"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The remaining work to be completed if nothing changes on the",
        "explanation": "The trend line gives us visibility about the forecast for the finishing date, considering a constant Scrum Team capacity for the Sprint Backlog."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Product Backlog is ordered by _________",
        "options": {
            "A": "Whatever is deemed most appropriate by the Product Owner",
            "B": "Items are randomly arranged",
            "C": "Risk, where safer items are at the top, and riskier items are at the bottom",
            "D": "Size, where small items are at the top and large items are at the bottom",
            "E": "Least valuable items at the top to most valuable at the bottom"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Backlog is ordered by Whatever is deemed most appropriate by the Product Owner",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner decides what makes the most sense to optimize the value of the work being done by the Developers."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Product Owner is not working with the Developers during the Sprint. What would you do as a Scrum Master?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Talk to the functional manager of the Product Owner",
            "B": "Cancel the Sprint and start training the Product Owner",
            "C": "Nominate someone else as the proxy Product Owner",
            "D": "Bring up the issue in the next Sprint Retrospective"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Bring up the issue in the next Sprint Retrospective",
        "explanation": "There's no proxy Product Owner in Scrum. It's best to resolve issues internally, without managers. This is not a valid reason for canceling a Sprint, and if it was only the Product Owner can cancel the Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are optional in Scrum? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Velocity",
            "B": "Backlog",
            "C": "Burndown",
            "D": "Increment",
            "E": "Definition of Done"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Velocity and Burndown",
        "explanation": "Burndown and Velocity are not mentioned in the Scrum Guide, however they are useful and they are mostly used by the Scrum Teams."
    },
    {
        "question": "From the following options, what is the best way a Scrum Master can increase the team productivity?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Breaking down the most valued Product Backlog items",
            "B": "Causing the removal of impediments and facilitating Scrum events if requested",
            "C": "Implementing a control change board",
            "D": "Assigning tasks to Developers"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Causing the removal of impediments and facilitating Scrum events if requested",
        "explanation": "Causing the removal of impediments and facilitating the Scrum events as requested or needed are the kind of things expected from the Scrum Master. The Scrum Team is self-managed, the Scrum Master must ensure the Product Owner knows how to prioritize the Product Backlog to maximize its value, but the Scrum Master is not responsible for doing so."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements do not explain when a Product Backlog item is considered complete? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "The item is ready for user acceptance testing",
            "B": "When the customer approves its completeness",
            "C": "When everything is done based on the Definition of Done",
            "D": "When there’s nothing more we need to do before it can be used by end users"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "The item is ready for user acceptance testing and When the customer approves its completeness",
        "explanation": "We can't consider it Done when user acceptance testing is not done. If we are aware of something that it's missing we should implement it, before considering it Done. A Product Backlog item that you have in the Sprint Backlog is Done, when it can be part of a Done Increment. Increments have to be Done based on the Definition of Done."
    },
    {
        "question": "A baselined Product Backlog is called __________",
        "options": {
            "A": "Release Plan",
            "B": "Ready",
            "C": "Sprint Backlog",
            "D": "Product Road map",
            "E": "It is never baselined, ¡t is a living artifact",
            "F": "All answers apply"
        },
        "answer": [
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "A baselined Product Backlog is called It is never baselined, ¡t is a living artifact",
        "explanation": "The product backlog is often called a living artifact, since it is continuously updated to reflect changes in the project and customer feedback."
    },
    {
        "question": "The timebox for a Daily Scrum is ________",
        "options": {
            "A": "15 minutes for a 4 week Sprint. For shorter Sprints it is usually shorter",
            "B": "15 minutes",
            "C": "Two minutes per person",
            "D": "The same time of day every day",
            "E": "4 hours"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "The timebox for a Daily Scrum is 15 minutes",
        "explanation": "The Daily Scrum is timeboxed at 15 minutes, it does not change depending on the length of a Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement best describes a Product Owner's responsibility?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Optimizing the value of the work the Developers do",
            "B": "Directing the Developers",
            "C": "Keep stakeholders from distracting the Developers",
            "D": "Managing the project and ensuring that the work meets the commitments to the stakeholders"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Optimizing the value of the work the Developers do",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is responsible for maximizing the value of the product and the work of the Developers and making sure that the Product Backlog reflects maximum value towards the Product Goal."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Work that does not meet the Definition of Done should be completed in the next Sprint.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "It should be moved in the Product Backlog and let the Product Owner decide what to do with it."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Multiple Scrum Teams should use the Definition of Ready to normalize estimations. This way it will be easier to measure and compare their performance",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "There are no comparable estimation units between the Scrum Teams, each team is different. Definition of Ready is a common practice, but is not mandatory in Scrum. The purpose of DoR is not normalizing estimations or performance measuring anyway."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Scrum does not have an accountability called Project Manager.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "A Scrum Team has a Scrum Master, a Product Owner and Developers. As a whole they have all controls needed and Project Manager is not an accountability in Scrum."
    },
    {
        "question": "A new Developer has just joined an existing team that has been together for several Sprints. During the Sprint, the individual has been trying to share his ideas and viewpoints but is continuously ignored by the rest of the Developers. Which Scrum Values has the Scrum Team been neglecting? (Select the best three answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Commitment",
            "B": "Openness",
            "C": "Courage",
            "D": "Respect",
            "E": "Focus",
            "F": "Transparency"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Openness and Courage and Respect",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Team members have courage to do the right thing and work on challenging problems. The Scrum Team agrees to be open to discuss all the work and the challenges with performing the work. Scrum Team members respect each other’s skills, experience and opinions."
    },
    {
        "question": "When does a Developer become the sole owner of a Sprint Backlog item?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Never. All Sprint Backlog Items are “owned” by all Developers, even though each one may be implemented by an individual member",
            "B": "Whenever a team member can accommodate more work",
            "C": "During the Daily Scrum",
            "D": "At the Sprint planning meeting"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Never. All Sprint Backlog Items are “owned” by all Developers, even though each one may be implemented by an individual member",
        "explanation": "Sprint Backlog and all of its items are collectively owned by the Developers. No individual Developer can claim ownership over an item as this would block communication and collaboration."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Stakeholders are prohibited to be present in the Daily Scrum",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Stakeholders can be in Daily Scrum as listeners, however only the Developers must participate and talk."
    },
    {
        "question": "An organization has decided to adopt Scrum, but management wants to change the terminology to fit with terminology already used. What will likely happen if this is done?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Management may feel less anxious",
            "B": "The organization may not understand what has changed with Scrum and the benefits of Scrum may be lost",
            "C": "All answers apply",
            "D": "Without a new vocabulary as a reminder of the change, very little change may actually happen",
            "E": "None of the answers apply"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "All answers apply",
        "explanation": "It's not easy to transform an organization that is new to Scrum, it will take time to see the benefit of it. Forming the organization takes time, and members often go through recognizable stages as they change from being a group of individuals to a team with common goals. Forming, Storming, Norming, and Performing model describes these stages by Bruce Tuckman. When you understand it, you can help your new team become effective more quickly."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the timebox for a Sprint Planning meeting?",
        "options": {
            "A": "8 hours for a monthly Sprint. For shorter Sprints it is usually shorter",
            "B": "4 hours",
            "C": "Monthly",
            "D": "Whenever it is done"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "8 hours for a monthly Sprint. For shorter Sprints it is usually shorter",
        "explanation": "Sprint Planning is timeboxed to a maximum of eight hours for a one-month Sprint. For shorter Sprints, the event is usually shorter."
    },
    {
        "question": "What should be the duration of a Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Short enough to be able to synchronize the development work with other business processes",
            "B": "Sufficiently short to maintain acceptable business risks for the product owner",
            "C": "None of the answers apply",
            "D": "No more than one month",
            "E": "All of the answers apply"
        },
        "answer": [
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "All of the answers apply",
        "explanation": "All these choices are correct criteria in deciding the duration of a Sprint. When a Sprint’s horizon is too long the Sprint Goal may become invalid, complexity may rise, and risk may increase. Shorter Sprints can be employed to generate more learning cycles and limit risk of cost and effort to a smaller time frame."
    },
    {
        "question": "Stakeholders joined the Daily Scrum of a Scrum Team to add a really urgent Bug in the Sprint Backlog. Developers immediately understood that they have to fix it as soon as possible, so they added it into the Sprint Backlog. Which of the following statements is wrong?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The fact that stakeholders joined the Daily Scrum",
            "B": "The fact that the Developers accepted work from stakeholders",
            "C": "The fact that the Developers didn’t redirect the stakeholders to the Product Owner",
            "D": "The fact that stakeholders spoke in the Daily Scrum"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "The fact that the Developers accepted work from stakeholders and The fact that the Developers didn’t redirect the stakeholders to the Product Owner and The fact that stakeholders spoke in the Daily Scrum",
        "explanation": "It is acceptable for the stakeholders to join the Daily Scrum, but they can only be there as listeners, they shouldn't interrupt the Developers. Even if stakeholders approach the Developers directly, they should be redirected to the Product Owner and if it is really urgent, PO could even cancel the Sprint, depending on what is going on with the Bug."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who creates the Definition of Done?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The organization (or the Scrum Team if none is available from the organization)",
            "B": "The Scrum Master as he/she is responsible for the Developers’ productivity",
            "C": "The Product Owner as he/she is responsible for the product’s success",
            "D": "The Developers"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "The organization (or the Scrum Team if none is available from the organization)",
        "explanation": "Note that it was the responsibility of the Developer to create the Definition of Done in the previous versions of the Scrum Guide, but it's the whole Scrum Team now. As stated in the Scrum Guide \"The Scrum Team must create a Definition of Done appropriate for the product.\""
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. A 2x increase in the number of Developers will double productivity.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "When more Developers are added to the team, there's usually a short-term decrease in productivity because other members have to spend time and effort familiarizing the new members with the solution and the environment of the project. After a while, the existence of new members may increase productivity, but even if it does, it's usually not a linear increase because, for example, having more people increases communication channels, which consumes some of the capacity."
    },
    {
        "question": "At the end of the Sprint the Developers have agreed to release the increment even if there is a part of it that doesn't meet the Definition of Done. The Product Owner said that it is alright, because they did Manual Testing instead of Test Automation. What shouldn't happen in this case?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Developers shouldn’t tell the Product Owner that they should do Test Automation",
            "B": "They should discuss this in the Sprint Retrospective",
            "C": "The Serum Master shouldn’t be involved. Quality is not her/his responsibility",
            "D": "The Serum Master should ask coaching questions like “Do you think that the increment will give the same value with the missing testing?”",
            "E": "They should extend the Sprint until they finish Test Automation",
            "F": "They should add the Test Automation in the Product Backlog to avoid Technical Debt"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "The Developers shouldn’t tell the Product Owner that they should do Test Automation and The Serum Master shouldn’t be involved. Quality is not her/his responsibility and They should extend the Sprint until they finish Test Automation",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Master should ask coaching questions when something is not properly followed (DoD). They shouldn't extend the Sprint, they should either exclude it from the increment or add it in the Product Backlog to avoid Technical Debt."
    },
    {
        "question": "When is a Sprint over?",
        "options": {
            "A": "When the Product Owner says it is done",
            "B": "When all Product Backlog items meet their Definition of Done",
            "C": "When the timebox expires",
            "D": "When all the tasks are completed"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "When the timebox expires",
        "explanation": "The duration of a Sprint is fixed and cannot be shortened or lengthened. A Sprint starts immediately after the end of the previous one."
    },
    {
        "question": "During a Sprint, the customer complains that a critical functionality is missing. Which Scrum Events they might have to attend to provide feedback about the expected features?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Daily Scrum",
            "B": "Sprint Review",
            "C": "Sprint Planning",
            "D": "Sprint Retrospective",
            "E": "Product Backlog refinement"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Sprint Review",
        "explanation": "During Sprint Review, the Scrum Team and stakeholders review what was accomplished in the Sprint and what has changed in their environment. Based on this information, attendees collaborate on what to do next, so the customers could be there to provide feedback. The Product Backlog may also be adjusted to meet new opportunities."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which artifact contains a plan for making visible the Sprint Goal?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Product Backlog",
            "B": "Increment",
            "C": "Sprint Backlog"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Sprint Backlog",
        "explanation": "The Sprint Backlog is composed of the Sprint Goal. Sprint Goal is the commitment. The Sprint Goal is the single objective for the Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the accountability of Management in Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Support the Product Owner with insights and information into high value product and system capabilities. Support the Scrum Master to cause organizational change that fosters empiricism, self-management, bottom-up intelligence, and intelligent release of software",
            "B": "Monitor the Developers’ productivity",
            "C": "Identity and remove people that aren’t working hard enough",
            "D": "Continually monitor staffing levels of the Developers"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Support the Product Owner with insights and information into high value product and system capabilities. Support the Scrum Master to cause organizational change that fosters empiricism, self-management, bottom-up intelligence, and intelligent release of software",
        "explanation": "Management has no active accountability in the actual product development through Scrum. However, management external to the Scrum Team is incredibly important in setting the vision and strategy to guide the overall direction of the organization."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Product Owner can allow the Developers to create and add items to the Product Backlog.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "Product Owners are allowed to delegate some of their responsibilities to other team members. The Product Owner is still staying accountable for it."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. If stakeholders want to add a new item in the Product Backlog, they have to convince the Product Owner.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "For Product Owners to succeed, the entire organization must respect their decisions. Those wanting to change the Product Backlog can do so by trying to convince the Product Owner."
    },
    {
        "question": "A key stakeholder tells the Developers to cancel the current Sprint as the customer that requested this work has left the company, so the Sprint Goal is obsolete now. What should happen in this case?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Cancel the Sprint, as it is really obvious the Sprint Goal is obsolete",
            "B": "The Scrum Master should coach the stakeholders for ways to raise their concerns",
            "C": "Developers should refer the key stakeholder to the Product Owner and let him decide if the Sprint Goal is obsolete",
            "D": "The Scrum Master should coach the stakeholders that they should never speak to the Developers directly, they should go through the Product Owner",
            "E": "This is the only case that stakeholders could cancel a Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The Scrum Master should coach the stakeholders for ways to raise their concerns and Developers should refer the key stakeholder to the Product Owner and let him decide if the Sprint Goal is obsolete",
        "explanation": "Only the Product Owner has the right to cancel a Sprint, no matter what's the reason behind it. Stakeholders can talk directly to the Developers, they should collaborate if needed. The Scrum Master should always be there to coach when needed."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best describe Lean thinking in Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Focuses on the essentials",
            "B": "Improves quality",
            "C": "Reduces waste",
            "D": "Limits the work in progress"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Focuses on the essentials and Reduces waste",
        "explanation": "As stated in the Scrum Guide \"Scrum is founded on empiricism and lean thinking. Empiricism asserts that knowledge comes from experience and making decisions based on what is observed. Lean thinking reduces waste and focuses on the essentials.\""
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Always must be a Release after each Sprint.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "The main purpose of the Sprint is to create an Increment of usable, and potentially releasable “Done” product. It's up to the Product Owner if it will be released."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the level of definition needed for the Sprint Backlog through the Sprint Planning?",
        "options": {
            "A": "None of the answers apply",
            "B": "The entire Sprint Backlog work must be identified and estimated by the end of the Sprint Planning",
            "C": "Enough to disaggregate tasks for the Scrum Team to establish the whole Sprint effort",
            "D": "Enough to allow the Developers to create their best forecast about what they can do as a result of the incoming Sprint, and to start the first several days of the Sprint",
            "E": "All answers apply",
            "F": "Enough to understand infrastructure requirements"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Enough to allow the Developers to create their best forecast about what they can do as a result of the incoming Sprint, and to start the first several days of the Sprint",
        "explanation": "The Sprint Planning priority is covering three topics: Why is this Sprint valuable? What can be Done this Sprint? & How will the chosen work get done? The team doesn’t need to get all the details about every task as long as these questions are answered and the pending definition can be completed as soon as possible in refinement activities."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Product Owner says that the customer has security concerns. Where can these concerns be addressed in Scrum? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Can be added to the Product Backlog",
            "B": "Can be handled in a special dedicated Sprint",
            "C": "Can be handled by security experts contractors in some moment",
            "D": "Can be handled in the Definition of Done"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Can be added to the Product Backlog and Can be handled in the Definition of Done",
        "explanation": "Many non-functional features, like security, can be added as acceptance criteria and tests in the Definition of Done to be applied to all or some Product Backlog items. We can have some specific security concerns that can be items in the Product Backlog. The Developers are cross-functional and self-sufficient, and should be capable of taking care of every aspect of the product, including security."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is a requirement before starting a Sprint Planning event?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Having the requirements specified and completely reflected in the Product Backlog",
            "B": "Having the Product Backlog items clearly described and assigned to developers",
            "C": "None of the answers apply",
            "D": "Having the items at the top of the Product Backlog small enough to fit into one Sprint",
            "E": "All answers apply"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "None of the answers apply",
        "explanation": "Each Sprint Planning starts immediately after the Sprint Retrospective of the previous Sprint, which means there's nothing happening before the Sprint Planning. There is nothing that could stop the Developers from starting the Sprint. Even if they haven't done refinement they should start the Sprint and they will split the items as more is learnt."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Product Owner can delegate some of their responsibilities to the Developers.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "Product Owners are allowed to delegate some of their responsibilities to other team members. If they do, the Product Owner stays accountable. Note: \"responsible\" is the person who's doing the task and \"accountable\" is the person who supervises it and is ultimately answerable for the task. The Product Owner is always accountable for the Product Backlog; they are also responsible unless they delegate this responsibility. These two words are often mixed though, so don't be shocked if you see that \"responsible\" is used to mean \"accountable\" sometimes."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is misleading about the Increment?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Multiple Increments may be created within a Sprint",
            "B": "Each Increment is not additive to all prior Increments",
            "C": "It may be delivered to stakeholders prior to the end of the Sprint",
            "D": "It is a concrete stepping stone toward the Sprint Goal"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Each Increment is not additive to all prior Increments and It is a concrete stepping stone toward the Sprint Goal",
        "explanation": "An Increment is a concrete stepping stone toward the Product Goal. Each Increment is additive to all prior Increments and thoroughly verified, ensuring that all Increments work together. Multiple Increments may be created within a Sprint and may be delivered to stakeholders prior to the end of the Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "What does a trend line through a release burndown chart indicate?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The budgeted cost of the project",
            "B": "When the remaining work ¡s supposed to be finished",
            "C": "When the remaining work will likely be completed if nothing changes in the Product Backlog or the Scrum Team",
            "D": "When the project will likely finish, if the team develops with a speed equal to the last Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "When the remaining work will likely be completed if nothing changes in the Product Backlog or the Scrum Team",
        "explanation": "During a release, a product is transferred from the development team to the customer. The release burndown chart shows the team progress towards the release date by plotting the remaining effort against the ideal effort. If the remaining effort line or bar is above the ideal effort, the team is behind the schedule."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Definition of Done can change during the project.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "Yes, it can be improved during the project. However, it doesn't change in the middle of a Sprint. During each Retrospective the Scrum Team could improve it if necessary."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Sprint Review is a meeting for receiving a customer's formal confirmation.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Sprint Review is a Scrum Event not a meeting. It happens internally in the organization. All Scrum events are designed to be transparent, and to be used for inspection, and ultimately, adaptation."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is a valid service from a Scrum Master to a Product Owner?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Help the Product Owner order the Product Backlog items in order to maximize value",
            "B": "Act as the middleman between the Product Owner and the Developers, as requested or required",
            "C": "Act as a proxy when the Product Owner is not available to the team",
            "D": "Help the Product Owner find techniques for managing the Product Backlog"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Help the Product Owner find techniques for managing the Product Backlog",
        "explanation": "It has to be coaching/training rather than doing the actual work. For example, helping the Product Owner order the backlog is not a good idea, but helping them understand how to order the backlog is a good one."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Stakeholders are only allowed to meet with the Scrum Team at Sprint Review.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Improving communications with the stakeholders is a crucial activity in Scrum, as working with them frequently ensures the team can focus on the right things to build. Although it is useful to have stakeholders not only at Sprint Review, but also maybe during Product Backlog refinement. There should be collaboration between the Developers and the stakeholder to make sure that Developers are aligned with the value needed by the customers."
    },
    {
        "question": "In this event, the Scrum Team and stakeholders talk and collaborate about what was done in the Sprint, in order to share the Sprint progress.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Sprint Review",
            "B": "Sprint Retrospective",
            "C": "All answers apply",
            "D": "Daily Scrum"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Sprint Review",
        "explanation": "The Sprint Review event is held at the end of the Sprint to inspect the Increment and adapt the Product Backlog if needed. Attendees also collaborate on the next things that could be done to optimize value."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Only the Developers are required to attend the Daily Scrum meeting.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "It is mandatory for the Developers to be there and participate. However, others could join as listeners."
    },
    {
        "question": "What topics does the Sprint Planning address?",
        "options": {
            "A": "How will the chosen work get done?",
            "B": "Who is going to work with who?",
            "C": "What can be Done this Sprint?",
            "D": "Why is this Sprint valuable?",
            "E": "Is there enough work to keep everyone busy full-time?"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "How will the chosen work get done? and What can be Done this Sprint? and Why is this Sprint valuable?",
        "explanation": "Sprint Planning has nothing to do with who is doing what. It has to do with the work for the next Sprint and has to cover these three topics. Why is this Sprint valuable? What can be Done this Sprint? and How will the chosen work get done?"
    },
    {
        "question": "The timebox of this Scrum Event should be one month or less.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Release Sprint",
            "B": "Release Planning",
            "C": "Sprint",
            "D": "None of the answers apply",
            "E": "Hardening Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Sprint",
        "explanation": "Sprints are fixed length events of one month or less to create consistency. A new Sprint starts immediately after the conclusion of the previous Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Sprint Backlog contains only pulled items from Product Backlog.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Of course, the Sprint Backlog contains the selected Product Backlog items but not just that. It also contains the tasks for the current Sprint which have agreed in the Sprint Planning for the delivery plan. (non-functional items, like testing etc.)"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is not a Developer responsibility?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Estimate the work needed for Sprint Backlog items",
            "B": "All answers apply",
            "C": "Measuring the performance of the Sprint",
            "D": "Ordering the Product Backlog items",
            "E": "Deal with internal team conflicts",
            "F": "None of the answers apply"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Ordering the Product Backlog items",
        "explanation": "Remember that Developers are self-managed. Therefore, It is team’ responsibility to measure its own productivity and performance throughout the Sprint, figure out its own process, plan, estimate and optimize the work required for items and the Sprint Goal, and to resolve their own conflicts."
    },
    {
        "question": "Peter is a new Product Owner on a newly formed Scrum Team. Peter has projected a product completion date based on an estimated velocity of 21 completed points per Sprint. After the first 3 Sprints, the Developers have determined that their maximum velocity is 15 points and they are unable to create shippable Increments at the end of each Sprint. What is the best way to proceed?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Inform Peter that the projected completion date is not correct. The Developers would estimate the remaining work to produce a shippable Increment and suggest completing it (make it meet the Definition of Done). Based on empirical data, Peter can adjust the completion date and decide how to continue",
            "B": "Extend the Sprint in order to complete the Sprint Backlog items",
            "C": "The Scrum Master would coach the team on improving their estimations and commitment to completing the Sprint Backlog",
            "D": "The Sprints have failed to produce shippable Increments therefore opportunities to inspect and adapt are lost. The Scrum Master would encourage the organization to add more team members in order to increase the team’s capacity"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Inform Peter that the projected completion date is not correct. The Developers would estimate the remaining work to produce a shippable Increment and suggest completing it (make it meet the Definition of Done). Based on empirical data, Peter can adjust the completion date and decide how to continue",
        "explanation": "This needs to be communicated with the Product Owner and provide better transparency."
    },
    {
        "question": "Why is it a good practice to include tests in the Definition of Done? (Select the best three answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Because the progress will be easier to show in burndown charts",
            "B": "Because the results are likely to be releasable",
            "C": "Because it can simplify requirement definitions",
            "D": "Because it adds transparency to final Increments"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Because the results are likely to be releasable and Because it can simplify requirement definitions and Because it adds transparency to final Increments",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Team has a common understanding of what a finished job (Done). With this purpose, we can increase Transparency when there are tests included in the Definition of Done, which will verify how close the work is to being complete and becoming a real Increment usable for final users."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is the most proper situation during the Sprint Planning considering that we have seven Scrum Teams working in a single product?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Product Owner meets only with some representatives from each team to select items from the Product Backlog. Then each representative works with his/her team to create their Sprint Backlog and dependencies are avoided for special escalation Sprints",
            "B": "All team members meet and together create one Sprint Backlog for the Sprint, in which everyone will work",
            "C": "Everyone meets at the same place at the same time, Scrum Teams can nominate a smaller number of appropriate people to represent the team on early discussions that are carried out at escalation level, the Product Owner gives information and then every dependency is discussed and coordinated by the teams. Team members can be shifted as needed and Sprint Backlogs for each Scrum Team are created"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Everyone meets at the same place at the same time, Scrum Teams can nominate a smaller number of appropriate people to represent the team on early discussions that are carried out at escalation level, the Product Owner gives information and then every dependency is discussed and coordinated by the teams. Team members can be shifted as needed and Sprint Backlogs for each Scrum Team are created",
        "explanation": "There should be only one Product Backlog and one Product Owner for one product. Each team needs to have a separate Sprint Backlog. The Developers are responsible for selecting the items from the Product Backlog, however, they can select representatives to do so. They share ownership of these though. Team members can change the composition of teams between Sprints. Even though Product Backlog items should be independent of each other, the dependencies between teams are unavoidable in scaled Scrum and they need to be handled."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Each Sprint Backlog item is owned by one Developer.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "All members of the Scrum Team share the accountability of the tasks, not specific Developers. The whole Scrum Team is cross-functional, not a single Developer."
    },
    {
        "question": "When the Developers find themselves in a situation where they don’t have the proper tools and infrastructure, what are the best actions to do? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "A Sprint Zero is created to focus on infrastructure instead of creating an Increment",
            "B": "The team must create a realistic Definition of Done under current circumstances",
            "C": "Coach the Developers to improve its skills, tools, and infrastructure over time and adjust the Definition of Done accordingly",
            "D": "The Developers can’t implement Scrum. They have to use other methods"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The team must create a realistic Definition of Done under current circumstances and Coach the Developers to improve its skills, tools, and infrastructure over time and adjust the Definition of Done accordingly",
        "explanation": "Sprint Zero does not exist in the Scrum framework and all the Sprints should be able to create an Increment of working software. The Inspections and Adaptation concepts are about making adjustments gradually through the project, this includes infrastructure and tools."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Sprint Backlog does not contain items pulled only from the Product Backlog.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "We can’t change the Sprint Goal, however, the team can talk and negotiate with the Product Owner in order to add new Sprint Backlog Items as needed or add non-functional requirements (testing, etc)."
    },
    {
        "question": "How should the members of multiple teams be composed for a single project?",
        "options": {
            "A": "All Answers apply",
            "B": "Scrum Master chooses the team members for each team",
            "C": "Management chooses the team members for each team",
            "D": "The Product Owner chooses the team members for each team",
            "E": "Developers themselves will decide the team's composition",
            "F": "Everyone together will decide on how to form the teams"
        },
        "answer": [
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Developers themselves will decide the team's composition",
        "explanation": "Developers should be self-managed and they’re responsible for team formations and composition."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Product Owner is required to be involved for the sizing of the Product Backlog items.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "The Developers who will be doing the work are responsible for the sizing. The Product Owner may influence the Developers by helping them understand and select trade-offs."
    },
    {
        "question": "Stakeholders can participate in this Scrum Event.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Sprint Review",
            "B": "Sprint Retrospective",
            "C": "Daily Scrum",
            "D": "Sprint Planning"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Sprint Review and Sprint Planning",
        "explanation": "The purpose of the Sprint Review is to inspect the outcome of the Sprint and determine future adaptations. The Scrum Team presents the results of their work to key stakeholders and progress toward the Product Goal is discussed. Stakeholders could also attend Daily Scrum, but only as listeners. In the Sprint Planning the team might invite others to give advice to it could be the Stakeholders."
    },
    {
        "question": "Bill Gates, the CEO of your organization and one of the most important customers, asked some Developers to add a new feature in the middle of the Sprint. What should they do?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Add the new feature to the Sprint Backlog",
            "B": "Replace an item in the current Sprint Backlog with the new one",
            "C": "Reject the request",
            "D": "Refer them to the Product Owner",
            "E": "Add the new feature to the Product Backlog"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Refer them to the Product Owner",
        "explanation": "One of the main responsibilities of the Product Owner is to maximize the value of the Developers' work, and he’s the only one who can add new items to the Product Backlog. Even when the Developers own the Sprint Backlog, the members can’t add items like this, the Product Owner must make sure that any new item adds value and she or he can work with proper stakeholders about it and then add it to the Product Backlog for the next Sprints. Also, the Product Owner can reject the new feature, rather than the Developers."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. All the Scrum Artifacts are designed to maximize transparency of key information.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "Scrum’s artifacts represent work or value. They are designed to maximize transparency of key information. Thus, everyone inspecting them has the same basis for adaptation."
    },
    {
        "question": "During Sprint Planning, the Scrum Team has some doubts about a few items at the top of the Product Backlog. The Product Owner, Angel, tries to contact the customer to talk to them about the meanings of the items, but all the customer representatives are in a meeting and won't be out until two hours after the planned finish of Sprint Planning. What would you advise, as the Scrum Master?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Cancel the Sprint Planning meeting, give them some time to prepare, and then hold another Sprint Planning",
            "B": "Extend the duration of Sprint Planning and ask them to discuss the items more and reach agreement",
            "C": "None of the answers apply",
            "D": "All answers apply",
            "E": "Cancel the Sprint and start the next one when the items are clear",
            "F": "Ask the Developers to come up with their best guess and don’t worry too much about their capacity"
        },
        "answer": [
            "F"
        ],
        "answers": "Ask the Developers to come up with their best guess and don’t worry too much about their capacity",
        "explanation": "Sprint Planning has a timebox that can't change and Scrum events are mandatory, nobody can cancel one of them(Sprint Planning or Sprint). The Developers should go with the best guess, if they need to bring more tickets, they will do it later in the Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "What amount of work should the Developers do to a selected Product Backlog item to complete the Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "As much as needed in adherence to the definition of “Done’",
            "B": "Requirements analysis, design, implementation, testing, documentation and some maintenance",
            "C": "All the needed work including some improvements",
            "D": "As much as they can do in the Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "As much as needed in adherence to the definition of “Done’",
        "explanation": "The agreed Definition of Done for the Scrum Team, is used to assess when work is complete on the product Increment in order to deliver an Increments of potentially releasable functionality."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are true about Scrum? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Simple to understand and difficult to master",
            "B": "Scrum is a methodology for managing complex projects",
            "C": "Scrum is a framework within which people can address complex adaptive problems",
            "D": "Sprints maximum length is six weeks"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Simple to understand and difficult to master and Scrum is a framework within which people can address complex adaptive problems",
        "explanation": "Scrum is not a methodology or body of knowledge, it is a framework that helps people, teams and organizations generate value through adaptive solutions for complex problems."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are true about the Scrum Master? (Select the best three answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Serves the Scrum Team in several ways",
            "B": "Is responsible for updating the burndown chart",
            "C": "Is the sole person responsible for managing the Product Backlog",
            "D": "It’s a management position",
            "E": "Coaching the Developers in self-management and cross functionality"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "D",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Serves the Scrum Team in several ways and It’s a management position and Coaching the Developers in self-management and cross functionality",
        "explanation": "Despite the Scrum Master not managing people, he manages the processes. That’s why it’s considered management accountability. The Scrum Team is self-managed, the Scrum Master can coach and help but the Developers handle the progress and performance of the Sprints. Finally, It is the Product Owner who owns the Product Backlog."
    },
    {
        "question": "Scaled Scrum is one that conforms to Scrum and uses more than one team for one or more Sprints.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "Scaled Scrum conforms to Scrum, it's compatible with Scrum. It's called scaled Scrum when there is more than one team. However, it's not necessary to have more than one team in all Sprints, it can be for some of them."
    },
    {
        "question": "When should the Scrum Team hold the Sprint Retrospective meeting?",
        "options": {
            "A": "At the end of each project",
            "B": "When the Product Owner and the Scrum Master determine that is needed",
            "C": "At the end of each Release",
            "D": "At the end of each Sprint",
            "E": "At the beginning of each Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "At the end of each Sprint",
        "explanation": "The Sprint Retrospective occurs always after the Sprint Review and prior to the next Sprint Planning."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are the best approaches that a Scrum Master could take when a Scrum Team doesn’t have the proper infrastructure to do the work needed to complete the selected Product Backlog items? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Suspend the project",
            "B": "Suspend the Sprint",
            "C": "Help the Scrum Team to create proper Sprint Goal and Definition of Done accordingly under current circumstances",
            "D": "Coach the Developers to improve infrastructure while adjusting the Definition of Done properly",
            "E": "Create a special Sprint to get infrastructure instead of creating an Increment"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Help the Scrum Team to create proper Sprint Goal and Definition of Done accordingly under current circumstances and Coach the Developers to improve infrastructure while adjusting the Definition of Done properly",
        "explanation": "The infrastructure and tools are prepared gradually throughout the project, and the Sprint Goal and Definition of Done should be realistic and created accordingly."
    },
    {
        "question": "How much of the Sprint Backlog needs to be defined throughout the Sprint Planning meeting?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Just enough for the Product Owner to be able to assign tasks to Developers",
            "B": "None of the answers apply",
            "C": "All answers apply",
            "D": "Absolutely all the work",
            "E": "Just enough to create the baseline for the whole project",
            "F": "Just enough, so that the Developers can estimate what they can do and to start the work on the first days of the Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "F"
        ],
        "answers": "Just enough, so that the Developers can estimate what they can do and to start the work on the first days of the Sprint",
        "explanation": "Scrum does not do upfront planning, only a few tasks broken down from the items are created in the Sprint Planning. The Developers are self-managed, their members decide who does what and there is no baseline for a Scrum project."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Developers cannot forecast how much work they can do in the upcoming Sprint, because of uncertainties in the Product Backlog that the Product Owner is not able to overcome. What of the following actions should the Scrum Master recommend? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Ask the Developers to come up with their best guess and do not worry too much about their capacity",
            "B": "Extend the duration of Sprint Planning and ask them to discuss the items more and get into agreement",
            "C": "Invite everyone to discuss this problem in the next Sprint Retrospective and try to find a solution",
            "D": "Cancel the Sprint Planning meeting, give them some time to prepare, and then hold another Sprint Planning",
            "E": "Cancel the Sprint and start the next one when the items are clear"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Ask the Developers to come up with their best guess and do not worry too much about their capacity and Invite everyone to discuss this problem in the next Sprint Retrospective and try to find a solution",
        "explanation": "Sprints are canceled when the Sprint Goal becomes obsolete and this can only happen from the PO, not for reasons such as this. What happens is that you will start the next Sprint and the next Sprint Planning right away. Remember, Sprints start one after the other, and we don't do anything outside the Sprints. Sprint Planning is timeboxed, we can't extend it. Developers should pick a number of items (best guess). If it's not enough, you can pick more later. If it's too many, you will just deliver as many as you can. Nothing bad happens if you don't deliver all items in the Sprint Backlog. The goal is to generate value, not to develop all items in the backlog."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The structure of the Daily Scrum is set by the Developers.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "The Developers own the Daily Scrum meetings, they can be conducted in different ways but always focus on progress toward the Sprint Goal."
    },
    {
        "question": "A Scrum Team found out in the Sprint Retrospective that their main issue is that they do not focus on the most valuable items during their Sprint. What Scrum Values? Which Scrum Values are demonstrated by focusing on the most valuable items first? (Select the best three answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Transparency",
            "B": "Respect",
            "C": "Inspection",
            "D": "Focus",
            "E": "Self-management",
            "F": "Courage"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "D",
            "F"
        ],
        "answers": "Respect and Focus and Courage",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Values are Commitment, Courage, Focus, Openness, and Respect. Make sure you are not confusing them with the Scrum Pillars (transparency, inspection, and adaptation)."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Developers and the Product Owner are not working together at all. What should the Scrum Master do?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Coach the Product Owner and the Developers about Scrum values and Incremental delivery",
            "B": "Restart the Sprint",
            "C": "Send everybody to a Scrum capacitation course and restart the project",
            "D": "Report the Product Owner to her/his manager"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Coach the Product Owner and the Developers about Scrum values and Incremental delivery",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Master must coach the whole Scrum Team members in organizational environments in which Scrum is not yet fully adopted and understood to practice agility. The Scrum Master must help them to effectively communicate with each other, but be careful, don’t act as a go-between for them."
    },
    {
        "question": "During Sprint Planning, the Product Backlog items are often decomposed into smaller work items. Ideally, how long should these smaller items take to be completed?",
        "options": {
            "A": "One day or less",
            "B": "One Sprint",
            "C": "One week or less",
            "D": "One month or less"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "One day or less",
        "explanation": "For each selected Product Backlog item, the Developers plan the work necessary to create an Increment that meets the Definition of Done. This is often done by decomposing Product Backlog items into smaller work items of one day or less."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is responsible for getting buy-in from stakeholders?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Developers",
            "B": "The Scrum Master",
            "C": "The Product Owner",
            "D": "The Project Manager"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Owner",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is responsible for getting buy-in, understanding the stakeholders’ concerns and goals. The Product Owner communicates and represents the desires of the customer."
    },
    {
        "question": "How often should the composition of the team change?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Every Sprint, to encourage creativity and openness",
            "B": "Never, because it reduces productivity",
            "C": "As needed, without a need to be concerned about changes in productivity",
            "D": "As needed, considering that it will have a short-term reduction in productivity"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "As needed, considering that it will have a short-term reduction in productivity",
        "explanation": "In the beginning other team members have to help to bring new members up to speed so a small reduction in productivity is expected."
    },
    {
        "question": "A few members of the Scrum Team discuss work that is not being done. A few Developers support that it is part of the Definition of Done, others say it isn't. What are the best actions for the Scrum Master to take in such a situation?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Organize a meeting with the people involved aside. Ask them to resolve this outside of the team and maybe involve their line managers",
            "B": "Remind the Scrum Team of the Scrum Values",
            "C": "Defuse the prevailing conflict. Teach the Developers how to interpret the Definition of Done. This will help the team to autonomously decide whether the debated work is or is not part of it",
            "D": "Remind the team that conflicting ideas are natural but making it personal should be avoided",
            "E": "Decide by yourself if work is part of Definition of Done",
            "F": "Organize a session and coach the team. Help the entire team resolve the conflict by themselves and create a uniform Definition of Done"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Remind the Scrum Team of the Scrum Values and Remind the team that conflicting ideas are natural but making it personal should be avoided",
        "explanation": "Conflict is not bad for a team, but members must have respect for each other. Instead of arguing, both the team members must express their point of view and have a constructive discussion. When a Product Backlog item or an Increment is described as “Done”, everyone must have a common understanding of what “Done” means. Although this may vary significantly per Scrum Team, members must have a shared understanding of what it means for work to be complete, to ensure transparency. This is the Definition of Done for the Scrum Team and is used to assess when work is complete on the product Increment. In self-managed teams creativity thrives, conflicts can be resolved, and new possibilities are explored."
    },
    {
        "question": "A Stakeholder requests from the Product Owner to push forward a specific Product Backlog item, but the Product Owner knows that it is not that valuable and decides not to build it anytime soon. Which Scrum Values are the Product Owner showing? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Maximize value",
            "B": "Adaptation",
            "C": "Passion",
            "D": "Transparency",
            "E": "Courage",
            "F": "Focus"
        },
        "answer": [
            "E",
            "F"
        ],
        "answers": "Courage and Focus",
        "explanation": "Successful use of Scrum depends on people becoming more proficient in living five values: Commitment, Focus, Openness, Respect, and Courage."
    },
    {
        "question": "A Scrum Team of 6 members is working on building a new application to support Payroll processes in their organization. Darren is a new Developer and he added an additional feature in the Increment which is not part of the Product Backlog. He did it because he was approached directly by one of the business stakeholders and only took him 30 min to implement the requirements. This was discovered just before the Sprint Review by other Developers. What should the Developers do? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Developers should retain the feature in the Increment but do not present it to the stakeholders",
            "B": "Darren should ask the Product Owner to add this feature to the Product Backlog because it is already part of the Increment",
            "C": "The Developers should remove the feature from the Increment",
            "D": "The Developers should inform the Scrum Master about the request and remove Darren from the Team",
            "E": "They should discuss the issue in the Sprint Retrospective"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "The Developers should remove the feature from the Increment and They should discuss the issue in the Sprint Retrospective",
        "explanation": "As per the Scrum Guide, \"The Product Backlog is an ordered list of what is needed to improve the product. It is the single source of work undertaken by the Scrum Team. Since the requirement did not originate from Product Backlog, it must be removed from the Increment. The team should also discuss this matter in the Sprint Retrospective so that everyone is aware of this rule. It is not justifiable to add this requirement in the Product Backlog just because it is already part of the Increment. Scrum Teams must follow the Scrum Values. Everything the team does should be transparent. Hiding the information from the Product Owner is not a good approach. Scrum Master does not remove individuals from the team for these kinds of mistakes. Scrum Master understands that mistakes are expected but the Team should learn from it."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which element is not an attribute of Product Backlog items?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Estimate",
            "B": "Owner",
            "C": "Order",
            "D": "Description"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Owner",
        "explanation": "Product Backlog refinement is the act of breaking down and further defining Product Backlog items into smaller more precise items. This is an ongoing activity to add details, such as a description, order, and size. Attributes often vary with the domain of work."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Lower positioned, Product Backlog items, are usually larger and less clear than those on the top.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "When Product Backlog is created, items are added to it. They have different sizes and eventually are ordered on their business value. The most valued items will be on the top and usually, these items would be broken down into smaller ones. We don’t do this with those items on the bottom. That’s why usually larger and less clear items are on the bottom of the Product Backlog."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Sprint Backlog includes _______________",
        "options": {
            "A": "Tasks",
            "B": "Tests",
            "C": "Use Cases",
            "D": "All answers apply, since are a decomposition of the selected Product Backlog items",
            "E": "None of the answers apply",
            "F": "User Stories"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "The Sprint Backlog includes All answers apply, since are a decomposition of the selected Product Backlog items",
        "explanation": "User Stories, Use Cases, Tests, Tasks and even other elements which help to define and clarify the work can be part of the Sprint Backlog."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. When multiple teams are working on the same product, one person can be a Developer of more than one Scrum Team.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "None of the Scrum accountabilities are necessarily full-time, and a single person can occupy more than one accountability or the same one in more than one team e.g., there may be a special expertise that is needed in multiple teams, but it's not needed on a full-time basis. So, one person can provide that special type of expertise to multiple teams. However, it's not recommended to have a person switching between projects, it's not productive."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or not. The Product Owner decides how many Product Backlog items should be selected for the next Sprint.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Correct, based on the agreements with the customer",
            "B": "False",
            "C": "Incorrect, the PMO decides that",
            "D": "Incorrect, the Scrum master decides that",
            "E": "Correct"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner sets the objective that the Sprint should achieve although can be influenced by the Developers. However, only Developers create the Increment, that’s why only they pull the Product Backlog items in order to accomplish Sprint Goal."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. It is required to use Acceptance Criteria in the Product Backlog items.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "It's a good idea to use Acceptance Criteria to capture the requirements, but it's not mandatory."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who must express clearly the Product Backlog items?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Project Manager",
            "B": "The Product Owner",
            "C": "The Scrum Master",
            "D": "The Developers"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Owner",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner owns the Product Backlog and is the sole person responsible for it. The Product Owner does Product Backlog management, like ensuring that the Product Backlog is transparent, visible and understood."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. When we have more risk we need longer Sprints.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "When we have shorter Sprints, there are more opportunities to show progress, and receive feedback, validate our knowledge and therefore Adapt. The longer the Sprint, the higher the risk."
    },
    {
        "question": "What’s the main responsibility of the Project Manager?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Create a project charter",
            "B": "Help the team to implement good practices",
            "C": "There’s no Project Manager accountability in Scrum",
            "D": "Constantly verify the programmers’ results"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "There’s no Project Manager accountability in Scrum",
        "explanation": "In Scrum we have only three accounts: the Product Owner, the Scrum Master and the Developers. It’s not permitted to define new accountabilities."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Every Increment should be released.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Every Increment should be potentially releasable and completed based on the Definition of Done. However, Increment doesn’t have to be actually released. The Product Owner decides if it makes sense to release or not."
    },
    {
        "question": "What's the normal timeboxed duration of Sprint Planning when there are 6 Developers in the team and Sprints are two weeks long?",
        "options": {
            "A": "8 hours",
            "B": "4 hours",
            "C": "3 hours",
            "D": "12 hours"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "4 hours",
        "explanation": "The timeboxed duration for Sprint Planning is 8 hours in a one-month Sprint, and normally shorter for shorter Sprints. If you have a shorter Sprint, it's not mandatory to shorten the timeboxed durations proportionally, but it's the normal thing to do. The key is the word \"normal\", we expect it to be shorter. if it was a \"must\" it would be 8 hours. Note that the duration of events is not dependent on the number of Developers."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the right criteria to order the Product Backlog?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Items are randomly arranged",
            "B": "Safer items are at the top, and riskier items are at the bottom",
            "C": "Whatever is deemed most appropriate by the Product Owner",
            "D": "The customer always decides"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Whatever is deemed most appropriate by the Product Owner",
        "explanation": "The decision on the order of items can be influenced by a committee, the customer, or any other stakeholder, but only the Product Owner decides what makes the most sense to optimize the value of the work being done by the Developers. The PO has the final word."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are the results of the Sprint Planning? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Sprint Backlog",
            "B": "Sprint Goal",
            "C": "Complete Sprint Acceptance Criteria",
            "D": "Complete Sprint Documentation"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Sprint Backlog and Sprint Goal",
        "explanation": "The Sprint Goal and Sprint Backlog are created during the Sprint Planning meeting. The rest could change as more is learnt."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Developers should prepare a complete infrastructure and set of tools for the project during the first Sprint.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "The Developers neither analyze, design nor describe the complete architecture and infrastructure, beforehand for the whole project. Agile processes are characterized by frequent short bursts of design, just enough to reach the Sprint Goal."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the Scrum accountability who knows the most about the project performance?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Product Owner",
            "B": "The Scrum Master",
            "C": "The Product Manager",
            "D": "The Developers",
            "E": "The Scrum Team"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Owner",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is responsible for measuring project performance. The Developers only measure the performance of the current Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Scrum Master should not allow the Sprint Planning meeting to start when the Sprint Goal is not ready.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "The Sprint Goal is prepared during the Sprint Planning meeting. Also, Scrum Masters don't order people, they teach and convince people to do the right thing."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Only Product Backlog items that have been refined enough can be selected for the Sprint Backlog.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "If they are not Refined enough, the Developers should go with the best guess. Items that are not ready will be refined during the Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following can be reasons for the Scrum Master to attend the Daily Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "To tell Developers what to do",
            "B": "It’s not necessary for the Scrum Master to be in the meeting",
            "C": "The Developers have asked the Scrum Master to facilitate their Daily Scrum",
            "D": "To participate as a Scrum Team member",
            "E": "To get a report on progress of the Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "It’s not necessary for the Scrum Master to be in the meeting and The Developers have asked the Scrum Master to facilitate their Daily Scrum",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Master facilitates the meetings as requested or required. Daily Scrum is not for the Scrum Team, it's for the Developers (however anyone can join as a listener)."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best describe the purpose of having a Definition of Done? (Select the best three answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "As the Developers are doing the work, they provide guidance on the remaining work needed to create the potentially shippable Increment by the end of the Sprint",
            "B": "It helps the Scrum Team decide how much time is needed before the Sprint can end",
            "C": "It creates transparency and provides a common understanding of the ‘done’ state of the Increment at the Sprint Review",
            "D": "It helps the Developers defer any pending work to subsequent Sprints",
            "E": "It provides guidance to the Developers when they are forecasting their Sprint Backlog during the Sprint Planning",
            "F": "It is a checklist to monitor the Developers’ progress on a task"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "As the Developers are doing the work, they provide guidance on the remaining work needed to create the potentially shippable Increment by the end of the Sprint and It creates transparency and provides a common understanding of the ‘done’ state of the Increment at the Sprint Review and It provides guidance to the Developers when they are forecasting their Sprint Backlog during the Sprint Planning",
        "explanation": "When a Product Backlog item or an Increment is described as Done, everyone must understand what Done means. Scrum Team members must have a shared understanding of what it means for work to be complete, to ensure transparency and is used to assess when work is complete on the product Increment. This Definition of Done provides the team guidance on what it takes to make the Increment shippable."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who can remove and replace Sprint Backlog items during the Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Product Owner",
            "B": "The Developers and the Product Owner",
            "C": "The Developers",
            "D": "The Scrum Master",
            "E": "The Scrum Team",
            "F": "No one"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The Developers",
        "explanation": "Only the Developers can modify the Sprint Backlog throughout the Sprint, can’t modify the Sprint objective though. If there is time and the Developers have completed all the items, the team will pull the next item from the top of the Product Backlog."
    },
    {
        "question": "What should the Scrum Team do during the Hardening Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Prepare for the next Sprint",
            "B": "There is no such thing as a Hardening Sprint",
            "C": "Code refactoring",
            "D": "Release the Increment",
            "E": "Work on technical debt"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "There is no such thing as a Hardening Sprint",
        "explanation": "There’s no such thing as a Sprint Hardening Sprint. If the stories are correctly prioritized, the Definition of Done is unambiguous, and the Product Backlog is regularly refined based on business priorities, the teams should be able to complete the development tasks."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statements are not correct about Daily Scrums?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Developers must answer the 3 standard questions during the meeting",
            "B": "Stakeholders can watch it",
            "C": "Only the Developers participate in the meeting",
            "D": "It’s always a 15-minute time boxed event, no matter how many Developers there are, or how long the Sprint is",
            "E": "It’s held at the same time and place every day"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Developers must answer the 3 standard questions during the meeting",
        "explanation": "It's common to go through the three standard questions, but it's not mandatory. It should be underlined that only the Developers articipate (talk). However others can join as listeners."
    },
    {
        "question": "A programmer is not working properly and is blocking the progress of the team and their activities constantly. Who should decide about the future of this person as a member of the team?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The management",
            "B": "The Product Owner",
            "C": "The Developers",
            "D": "The Scrum Master"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The Developers",
        "explanation": "The Developers are self-managed, therefore this is a decision and responsibility of its members. Of course, the Scrum Master must address and support this decision since it is also an impediment."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is the most productive way for the Scrum Master to improve the Developers' communications with the Product Owner?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Suggest effective communication tools and techniques to the Product Owner",
            "B": "Act as a go-between for them",
            "C": "Teach them how to effectively communicate",
            "D": "Monitor their communication performance"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Suggest effective communication tools and techniques to the Product Owner and Teach them how to effectively communicate and Monitor their communication performance",
        "explanation": "Acting as a go-between is not a sustainable solution. They should be self-managed. Make sure you have noticed the word \"most\" in the question."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are not pillars of empirical process control?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Respect for people, Eliminating Waste",
            "B": "Planning, Demonstration, Retrospective",
            "C": "Transparency, Eliminating Waste",
            "D": "Inspection, Transparency, Adaptation"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Respect for people, Eliminating Waste and Planning, Demonstration, Retrospective and Transparency, Eliminating Waste",
        "explanation": "According to Scrum Theory Scrum combines four formal events for inspection and adaptation within a containing event, the Sprint. These events work because they implement the empirical Scrum pillars of transparency, inspection, and adaptation."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Hardening Sprints are needed every few Sprints, to resolve dependencies and reduce technical debt.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "There’s no Hardening Sprint. There’s just one type of Sprint, and its goal is to create an Increment of potentially releasable valuable features."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Sprint Review is a formal meeting.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "it's a formal event but not a formal meeting, it is for the company internally not the customers. The Scrum Guide states the word formal in two different ways. First, all events are formal opportunities for inspecting and adapting, which basically means a serious opportunity. The second usage is formal meeting, which means a meeting where people approve something and exchange signatures. In that sense, none of the events are formal meetings. In the Sprint Review meeting, for example, the goal is creating feedback and adapting, not contract negotiations and exchanging signatures. The Scrum Guide states this detail: \"Events are used in Scrum to create regularity and to minimize the need for meetings not defined in Scrum.\""
    },
    {
        "question": "Who estimates the work during the Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Developers",
            "B": "The Scrum Master",
            "C": "The Scrum Team",
            "D": "The Developers and the Product Owner",
            "E": "No one",
            "F": "The Product Owner"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "The Developers",
        "explanation": "Developers do the work and they are the ones who best know what is needed to complete specific tasks, so they can only estimate them. Remember different teams might provide different estimates."
    },
    {
        "question": "How much time should a Product Owner spend with the Developers?",
        "options": {
            "A": "At least 30% of their time",
            "B": "About 10% of their time",
            "C": "As much as needed",
            "D": "All of their time"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "As much as needed",
        "explanation": "Product Owners should be there when needed, it can be any amount of time."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Scrum Teams are allowed to use burn-up charts instead of burn-down charts.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "There are different things that can help them in this forecast, but they are all guesses and the Product Owner has to consider everything and adjust the forecast before presenting it to the stakeholders. It's very common to use burn-down charts in Agile, but it's up to the Product Owner to decide how they want to measure and visualize performance of the project, and up to the Developers to decide how they want to do it for Sprints."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which accountability is the equivalent of Project Manager in Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Developers",
            "B": "Product Owner",
            "C": "Scrum Master",
            "D": "None of them",
            "E": "Team Leader"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "None of them",
        "explanation": "There's no project manager accountability in Scrum, and it's not allowed to add new accountability to the existing three. Project management activities are distributed among all of them in the Scrum Team. This is only about the project level, you can always have higher management levels (e.g. program management), and those \"can\" be compatible with what you do in your Scrum projects. The Scrum Master is considered a role that manages people, but not a Project Manager."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which two of the following are Scrum Master responsibilities?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Leads Scrum adoption",
            "B": "Ensure the Product Owner attends all Scrum events",
            "C": "Assign tasks to the Developers",
            "D": "Causing the removal of impediments",
            "E": "Do monitoring and controlling for the progress of the Developers"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Leads Scrum adoption and Causing the removal of impediments",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Master serves the organization in several ways, including leading and coaching the organization in its Scrum adoption, planning Scrum implementations within the organization, also the Scrum Master serves the Developers in several ways, including, causing the removal of impediments to their progress."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the most effective way to sort the Product Backlog?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Size",
            "B": "Whatever the Product Owner decides",
            "C": "Complexity",
            "D": "Whatever the Developers decide",
            "E": "Risk"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Whatever the Product Owner decides",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner manages the Product Backlog, so it's up to her/him to decide the order. She/He should do it based on the value of the Items, remember the PO is also known as value maximizer."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements should be considered in setting the timeboxed duration of Sprints? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "It’s better to have shorter Sprints when the project is riskier",
            "B": "It should be shorter when there are more Developers",
            "C": "It should be longer in bigger projects",
            "D": "It shouldn’t be longer than one month",
            "E": "It shouldn’t be longer than 6 weeks"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "It’s better to have shorter Sprints when the project is riskier and It shouldn’t be longer than one month",
        "explanation": "Shorter Sprints provide more adaptation opportunities, which reduces risks. The Scrum Guide states one month as the maximum."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. During the Sprint Review, the Product Owner demonstrates the work that the Scrum Team has completed and answers questions about the Increment.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "As stated in the Scrum Guide: The purpose of the Sprint Review is to inspect the outcome of the Sprint and determine future adaptations. The Scrum Team presents the results of their work to key stakeholders and progress toward the Product Goal is discussed."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The Scrum Master should cancel the Sprint if the Product Owner has not created the Sprint Goal before Sprint Planning.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Team created the Sprint Goal during the Sprint Planning meeting, not the Product Owner. The Scrum Master can't cancel the Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "When is the Sprint over? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "When the Scrum Master announces the end of the Sprint",
            "B": "When the Sprint Backlog tasks are done",
            "C": "When the Product Owner cancels the Sprint",
            "D": "When the timeboxed duration is over",
            "E": "When all Sprint Backlog items are done"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "When the Product Owner cancels the Sprint and When the timeboxed duration is over",
        "explanation": "The timebox determines the length of the Sprint and the Product Owner is the only one who has the authority to cancel a Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "Eva, the Product Owner, has been giving positive recognition to individual Developers who have moved their work to Done during the Daily Scrum. Eva wants to ensure the team is adhering to the ideal guideline on the burndown chart. What would be valid actions for Steven, the Scrum Master, to take? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Steven coaches Eva on best practices for updating the burndown chart as it provides accurate information on how well the team is performing",
            "B": "Steven coaches the Scrum Team about the purpose of the Daily Scrum",
            "C": "Steven talks with Eva about concerns of how her behavior might impact the team members and requests that she stop attending for now",
            "D": "Nothing. Steven is optional at the Daily Scrum and it is the responsibility of the team to decide how to best run it"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Steven coaches the Scrum Team about the purpose of the Daily Scrum and Steven talks with Eva about concerns of how her behavior might impact the team members and requests that she stop attending for now",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Master is responsible for promoting and supporting Scrum as defined in the Scrum Guide. Scrum Masters do this by helping everyone understand Scrum Theory, practices, rules, and values. The Scrum Master serves the Scrum Team in several ways. The Scrum Master helps the Scrum Team understand which of their interactions are helpful and which aren’t. The Scrum Master helps everyone change these interactions to maximize the value created by the Scrum Team."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which output of Sprint Planning provides an overall objective for the Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "All answers apply",
            "B": "Tasks",
            "C": "Sprint Goal",
            "D": "Release Plan",
            "E": "None of the answers apply",
            "F": "Product Goal"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Sprint Goal",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Team creates the Sprint Goal during the Sprint Planning meeting, it's a high-level objective for the Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. If an organization is doing scaled Scrum they can have a committee to represent the Product Owner.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner is one person, not a committee. The Product Owner may represent the needs of many stakeholders in the Product Backlog. Those wanting to change the Product Backlog can do so by trying to convince the Product Owner."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Sprint Goal is not one of the inputs of a Sprint Planning meeting.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "The input of the Sprint Planning is the Product Backlog, the latest product Increment, projected capacity of the Developers during the Sprint, and past performance of the Developers(velocity). Make sure you have noticed the word \"not\" in the question."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following may not be done in the Sprint Retrospective meeting? (Select the best three answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Discuss the way Product Backlog refinement is done during the Sprints",
            "B": "Discuss the way Daily Scrum is done during the Sprint",
            "C": "Refining the Product Backlog",
            "D": "Discuss the Product Backlog items for the next Sprint",
            "E": "Calculate Velocity"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C",
            "D",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Refining the Product Backlog and Discuss the Product Backlog items for the next Sprint and Calculate Velocity",
        "explanation": "In general, Sprint Retrospective is about the context, not the content. For example, we talk about the way Product Backlog is refined, but we won't refine the Product Backlog in the Sprint Retrospective meeting. Make sure you have noticed the \"not\" in the question."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are reasons Scrum promotes self-managed teams? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Because they improve their self-accountability",
            "B": "Because they improve their regulations compliance",
            "C": "Because they improve their commitment",
            "D": "Because they improve their predictability"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Because they improve their self-accountability and Because they improve their commitment",
        "explanation": "Being self-managed implies that the team follows its very own process, rather than receiving orders. When it’s so, the members of the team tend to commit themselves and increase their accountability, and creativity."
    },
    {
        "question": "Hatzis is a Product Owner of a seven member Scrum Team and he believes that the current velocity will not be sustainable. What could be wrong?",
        "options": {
            "A": "High technical debt",
            "B": "Having only low value items remaining in the Product Backlog",
            "C": "The possibility of having major changes in the future",
            "D": "The possibility of adding more items to the Product Backlog"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "High technical debt",
        "explanation": "When you have technical debt, you will run into problems in the future, which will slow down your velocity."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which events are timeboxed according to the Scrum Guide?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Sprint Testing",
            "B": "Daily Scrum",
            "C": "Release Retrospective",
            "D": "Release Testing",
            "E": "The Sprint",
            "F": "Sprint Review"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "E",
            "F"
        ],
        "answers": "Daily Scrum and The Sprint and Sprint Review",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Guide states that all Scrum Events are timeboxed. The Sprint to 1 month or less, Sprint Planning to maximum 8 hours for a one-month Sprint, Daily Scrum to 15-minutes, Sprint Review to maximum 4 hours for a one-month Sprint, and the Sprint Retrospective to maximum 3 hours for a one-month Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who ensures that attendees of the Sprint Planning are prepared to discuss the most important Product Backlog items?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Product Owner",
            "B": "The Scrum Master",
            "C": "The Scrum Team",
            "D": "The Developers"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Owner",
        "explanation": "As stated in the Scrum Guide \"The Product Owner ensures that attendees are prepared to discuss the most important Product Backlog items and how they map to the Product Goal. The Scrum Team may also invite other people to attend Sprint Planning to provide advice.\""
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements can be used to reduce technical debt? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Hardening Sprints",
            "B": "Hiring external specialists",
            "C": "Refactoring the code",
            "D": "Improve the Definition of Done"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Refactoring the code and Improve the Definition of Done",
        "explanation": "Refactoring can improve the code without changing its external behavior. The better the Definition of Done the less the technical debt"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct about an item that is in-progress at the end of the Sprint? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Move it back to the Product Backlog",
            "B": "Do not include it in the Increment",
            "C": "If the Product Owner is happy with it it can be part of the Increment",
            "D": "The Sprint will be extended until we complete the item",
            "E": "It can be added to the Increment if the user acceptance tests are done"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Move it back to the Product Backlog and Do not include it in the Increment",
        "explanation": "It should only be presented as the Increment in the Sprint Review. The Increment should meet the Definition of Done. If an item is not done, we won't include it in the Increment and send it back to the Product Backlog for the Product Owner to decide. Sprints are timeboxed, meaning that we don't extend their duration."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are typical things that a Product Owner does between Sprint Planning and Sprint Review? (Select the best three answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Create reports on resource utilization",
            "B": "Product Backlog Refinement",
            "C": "Collaborate with stakeholders",
            "D": "Measure the Sprint performance",
            "E": "Answer questions from the Developers about items"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Product Backlog Refinement and Collaborate with stakeholders and Answer questions from the Developers about items",
        "explanation": "Product Backlog Refinement happens continuously. Regarding the Product Backlog items in the Sprint Backlog. If you have doubts, as a Developer, you always ask the Product Owner what is expected from the item. Collaboration with stakeholders is the key to make sure the Product Backlog is aligned and valuable."
    },
    {
        "question": "The timebox of this Scrum Event should be no more than 15 minutes for one week Sprints.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Sprint Review",
            "B": "Release Sprint",
            "C": "Sprint",
            "D": "Sprint Retrospective",
            "E": "Daily Scrum",
            "F": "Sprint Planning"
        },
        "answer": [
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Daily Scrum",
        "explanation": "The Daily Scrum is a 15-minute event for the Developers of the Scrum Team. To reduce complexity, it is held at the same time and place every working day of the Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Velocity is one of the inputs of a Sprint Planning meeting.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "The input of the Sprint Planning is the Product Backlog, the latest product Increment, projected capacity of the Developers during the Sprint, and past performance of the Developers(velocity)."
    },
    {
        "question": "Stuart is a Scrum Master of a team with 7 Developers. The Developers have realized that they have over committed themselves for the Sprint. What's the best for the Developers to do? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "They can make any adjustments themselves, because they own the Sprint Backlog",
            "B": "They can review and adjust the technical work of the items themselves",
            "C": "They shouldn’t make any changes to the Sprint Backlog",
            "D": "They can get help from the Product Owner to adjust the Sprint Backlog",
            "E": "They should ask the Product Owner to cancel the Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "They can review and adjust the technical work of the items themselves and They can get help from the Product Owner to adjust the Sprint Backlog",
        "explanation": "They can't cancel the Sprint, only the Product Owner can do that. They are not allowed to adjust everything by themselves, they need to talk to the Product Owner for the functional tasks. If it is a technical task, then yes they can do it by themselves, as they know more, but that shouldn't impact functional requirements."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. An increment can only be released after the Sprint Review.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Multiple Increments may be created within a Sprint. The sum of the Increments is presented at the Sprint Review thus supporting empiricism. However, an Increment may be delivered to stakeholders prior to the end of the Sprint. The Sprint Review should never be considered a gate to releasing value."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is right about the Product Goal? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Product Owner is also accountable for developing and explicitly communicating the Product Goal",
            "B": "The Developers should focus on their Sprint Backlog and not the Product Goal",
            "C": "The Scrum Master serves the Product Owner in finding techniques for effective Product Goal definition",
            "D": "The Scrum Team has the right to determine the Product Goal"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The Product Owner is also accountable for developing and explicitly communicating the Product Goal and The Scrum Master serves the Product Owner in finding techniques for effective Product Goal definition",
        "explanation": "As stated in the Scrum Guide the Product Owner is also accountable for developing and explicitly communicating the Product Goal. and the Scrum Master serves the Product Owner in finding techniques for effective Product Goal definition. Sprint Backlog should be built in a way towards the Product Goal."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. It is Developers' responsibility to create valuable increments.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "The entire Scrum Team is accountable for creating a valuable, useful Increment every Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "How much time do we need between a Sprint Retrospective and the next Sprint Planning to prepare the Product Backlog?",
        "options": {
            "A": "As much as the Product Owner finds necessary",
            "B": "None",
            "C": "As much as the Scrum Team finds necessary to complete Product Backlog refinement",
            "D": "As much as needed"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "None",
        "explanation": "Each Sprint starts immediately after the previous one; there's nothing between the two."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Scrum Master can participate in Daily Scrum.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Daily Scrum is for Developers they should only participate, others can join as listeners."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Only the Developers are allowed to attend the Sprint Retrospective.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Team is allowed to attend the Sprint Retrospective. This includes the Scrum Master and the Product Owner."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is a benefit of self-managing?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Increased predictability",
            "B": "Increased respect",
            "C": "Increased cross-functionality",
            "D": "Increased buy-in"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Increased buy-in",
        "explanation": "Self-management means that they make decisions instead of receiving orders passively. When people are self-managed, meaning that they make their own decisions instead of receiving orders, they take the decision-making process more seriously and will be more committed to the decision, which means creativity and dedication."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Only the Developers are allowed to determine the Definition of Done.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Team should be responsible for defining and adjusting the Definition of Done."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements best describes the Scrum Pillar of Transparency.",
        "options": {
            "A": "None of the answers apply",
            "B": "The emergent process and work must be visible to those performing the work as well as those receiving the work",
            "C": "The Scrum artifacts and the progress toward agreed goals must be inspected frequently and diligently to detect potentially undesirable variances or problems",
            "D": "If any aspects of a process deviate outside acceptable limits or if the resulting product is unacceptable, the process being applied or the materials being produced must be adjusted"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "The emergent process and work must be visible to those performing the work as well as those receiving the work",
        "explanation": "As stated in the Scrum Guide: \"The emergent process and work must be visible to those performing the work as well as those receiving the work. With Scrum, important decisions are based on the perceived state of its three formal artifacts. Artifacts that have low transparency can lead to decisions that diminish value and increase risk.\""
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. A Scrum Team is allowed to have two Scrum Masters if it is too large.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "The fundamental unit of Scrum is a small team of people, a Scrum Team. The Scrum Team consists of one Scrum Master, one Product Owner, and Developers."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following roles is the equivalent of Project Manager in Scrum?",
        "options": {
            "A": "None",
            "B": "Product Owner",
            "C": "Scrum Master",
            "D": "Team Leader",
            "E": "Developers"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "None",
        "explanation": "There is no PM role in Scrum, it's only Scrum Master, Product Owner and Developers."
    },
    {
        "question": "It's generally better to have shorter Sprints when the project is riskier.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "Shorter Sprints provide more opportunities for adaptation and thus reduce risks."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which statement is true when Developers are in the middle of a Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Sprint Backlog would be frozen",
            "B": "The scope may be clarified as more is learned",
            "C": "The scope will stay fixed until the end of the Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "The scope may be clarified as more is learned",
        "explanation": "Spring Backlog has Sprint Goal, Product Backlog Items that can also be splitted as part of the refinement. The longer we work on these items, the more we learn about them."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following can be a reason for expecting lower velocity in the future?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Having only low-value items remaining in the Product Backlog",
            "B": "The possibility of having more items added to the Product Backlog",
            "C": "The possibility of having extreme changes in the future",
            "D": "High technical debt"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "High technical debt",
        "explanation": "When you have technical debt, you will run into problems in the future, which will slow down your rate of development."
    },
    {
        "question": "How would you know whether a Scrum Team is cross-functional?",
        "options": {
            "A": "They can do Test Driven Development if they decide to",
            "B": "They can do Pair-Programming if they decide to",
            "C": "Each Developer is expert in all technical layers of the system",
            "D": "They can create releasable Increments each Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "They can create releasable Increments each Sprint",
        "explanation": "Cross-functional Developers must have all skills needed to create a releasable Increments every Sprint. A cross-functional Scrum Team is one that has all types of expertise that is required to develop the product. Note that the whole Scrum Team should be cross-functional, not individual team members. e.g. in this scenario here we could assume that Product Owner and Scrum Master are Developers as well."
    },
    {
        "question": "Select two purposes of having a Definition of Done.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Helps to know what Backlog items should be pulled for the Sprint",
            "B": "Is another name for Definition of Ready",
            "C": "Helps the Scrum Master to measure the productivity of the Developers",
            "D": "Helps to create a shared understanding of what is the Backlog items scope in order to know when this is completed",
            "E": "Ensure transparency"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Helps to create a shared understanding of what is the Backlog items scope in order to know when this is completed and Ensure transparency",
        "explanation": "Everyone in the Scrum Team must understand what Definition of Done means. Although this may vary significantly per Scrum Team, members must have a shared understanding of what it means for work to be complete, to ensure transparency. It is used to assess when work is complete on the product Increment."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements relate technical debt with velocity? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "They are not related because technical debt should be resolved by the DevOps team",
            "B": "Velocity may unexpectedly drop when Developers run into",
            "C": "technical debt while attempting to complete new Product Backlog items",
            "D": "A Development Team can artificially increase its velocity by incurring technical debt",
            "E": "Adding new items for technical debt to the Product Backlog can guarantee predictability"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Velocity may unexpectedly drop when Developers run into and technical debt while attempting to complete new Product Backlog items",
        "explanation": "When you have technical debt, you will run into problems in the future, which will slow down your velocity."
    },
    {
        "question": "How does the Developers determine the number of items for the Sprint Backlog?",
        "options": {
            "A": "They don’t do it",
            "B": "Based on what the Scrum Master and the Product Owner agree",
            "C": "Based on velocity",
            "D": "Based on a combination of velocity and team capacity",
            "E": "In a way that maximizes the value of the Increment",
            "F": "Based on the Product Owner’s preferences"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C",
            "D",
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "Based on velocity and Based on a combination of velocity and team capacity and In a way that maximizes the value of the Increment",
        "explanation": "It's only up to the self-managing Developers to decide how many items they will select for the Sprint Backlog. The Sprint Backlog is a plan by and for the Developers. It is a highly visible, real-time picture of the work that the Developers plan to accomplish during the Sprint in order to achieve the Sprint Goal."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements can be used by the Product Owner to understand the progress of the Sprint? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Ask the Scrum Master for daily briefs",
            "B": "Attend the Daily Scrum",
            "C": "Check the Sprint Backlog",
            "D": "Ask the team leader for daily briefs"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Attend the Daily Scrum and Check the Sprint Backlog",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner can attend as a listener the Daily Scrum to understand the progress. Sprint Backlog should also reflect Developers' progress."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. It is mandatory to use burndown charts in Scrum.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "It is not mandatory to use it, however many Scrum Teams do it."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is expected to be involved in a Product Backlog refinement?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Product Owner",
            "B": "Product Owner and Stakeholders",
            "C": "Product Owner and Developers"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Product Owner and Developers",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner because she/he knows more about the Product Backlog items and the Developers because they will work on those."
    },
    {
        "question": "When is user acceptance testing done?",
        "options": {
            "A": "During Hardening Sprints",
            "B": "Before the release",
            "C": "During the Sprint Review meeting",
            "D": "During the Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "During the Sprint",
        "explanation": "Everything should happen within the Sprint, there are no Hardening Sprints or special events, as releases."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following are inputs to the Sprint Planning meeting?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Previous Increment",
            "B": "Sprint Goal",
            "C": "Product Backlog items"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "Previous Increment and Product Backlog items",
        "explanation": "The input of the Sprint Planning is the Product Backlog, the latest product Increment, projected capacity of the Developers during the Sprint, and past performance of the Developers(velocity). Sprint Goal is output."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is responsible for making sure that the Developers' work is built according to the Definition of Done?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Product Owner",
            "B": "The Software Architect",
            "C": "The Developers",
            "D": "The Team Leader",
            "E": "The Scrum Master"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The Developers",
        "explanation": "Developers should deliver an Increment of product functionality according to the Definition of Done."
    },
    {
        "question": "There is a project in an organization that is supposed to have two releases. The first one in the middle of the project and the second one at the end of the project. Which of the following statements are correct about this project?",
        "options": {
            "A": "All the Increments that are created before each release should be releasable",
            "B": "Increments are created for investigation and adaptation, they don’t have to be releasable",
            "C": "Having releasable Increments depends on the preference of the DevOps",
            "D": "All increments should be releasable"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "All increments should be releasable",
        "explanation": "All Increments must be potentially releasable to enable usable feedback, regardless of the actual releases we may have."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements explain how Scrum promotes self-management? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "By being a simple and lightweight framework",
            "B": "By not allowing extensive documentation",
            "C": "By preventing stakeholders from contacting the Developers during the Sprint",
            "D": "By allowing the Developers to decide what to do during the Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "By being a simple and lightweight framework and By allowing the Developers to decide what to do during the Sprint",
        "explanation": "Scrum is a lightweight framework that helps people, teams and organizations generate value through adaptive solutions for complex problems. Developers are self-managed so they can decide what to do during the Sprint."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Developers of a Scrum Team decided to skip the Sprint Review for a couple of Sprints. Who is responsible for making sure that the meeting happens every Sprint?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Scrum Master",
            "B": "The Developers",
            "C": "The Development Manager",
            "D": "The Product Owner",
            "E": "The Stakeholders",
            "F": "The Scrum Team"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "The Scrum Master",
        "explanation": "The Scrum Master is responsible for making sure that Scrum is properly applied in the organization. The Scrum Master should make sure that all events take place."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements are correct about the Scrum Team members? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "They are accountable for ordering the Product Backlog items",
            "B": "They set the timeboxed duration of Sprints",
            "C": "They measure the progress of the project",
            "D": "They compose the Sprint Goal",
            "E": "They decide about engineering and development methods"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "They set the timeboxed duration of Sprints and They compose the Sprint Goal",
        "explanation": "The Product Owner orders the Product Backlog items. Sprint Goal and Sprint duration is something that the team decides. Developers are responsible for the technical decisions and the Product Owner for the progress of the project."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The UI designer is on holidays, so the Developers decided to build a mockup by themselves. This is part of the self-managing team, so they are allowed to do this.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "Developers should be able to manage their own work and remove any impediments if they can."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Scrum is a methodology which describes detailed steps to get working and releasable software.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Scrum doesn’t describe any detailed step, and rather than a methodology is a framework."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. The higher the velocity of a Scrum Team. the higher the value delivered.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "There's no direct relationship between velocity and value. Different teams have different velocities as well, so we can't compare them. If a Scrum Team works faster on less valuable items, velocity will be higher, but value may be the same, higher, or lower."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Eventually, the Scrum Master becomes unnecessary when the Developers mature through the project.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "If a project does not include Scrum Master or Product Owner accountabilities, this project is not doing Scrum. Both accountabilities can be part-time but always are performed in a Scrum project. One of the most important Scrum Master activities is causing the removal of impediments, and it doesn’t matter how mature the Developers are, its members will always benefit when someone takes care of these issues."
    },
    {
        "question": "The Developers have difficulty understanding some of the requirements of the items in the Sprint Backlog. What would you do as a Product Owner?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Ask the Scrum Master to facilitate the communication between you and the Developers",
            "B": "Attend the Daily Scrums and answer their questions",
            "C": "Attend the Daily Scrums and remove their impediments",
            "D": "Spend as much time with them as needed, explaining the items and answering questions"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Spend as much time with them as needed, explaining the items and answering questions",
        "explanation": "Attending the Daily Scrum is only for the Developers, not for the Product Owner, it's not the wrong way to approach this but spending time with the Developers is the most appropriate way. The Scrum Master is not needed in this case as there is no conflict between them, it's just a matter of answering some questions, not facilitating the communication between them."
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the best ways to address performance concerns? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "Have special Sprints that ensure those concerns",
            "B": "Dedicate a certain portion of the team capacity to working on those concerns",
            "C": "Add them to the Product Backlog",
            "D": "Add them to the Definition of Done"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C",
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "Add them to the Product Backlog and Add them to the Definition of Done",
        "explanation": "If it's something that applies to many items and determines the way functional features work, it would be great to add them in the DoD. If it's about the performance of an existing function, adding them in the Product Backlog is reasonable, so you don't allow technical debt to grow. There are no \"special\" Sprints such as hardening Sprints or integration Sprints."
    },
    {
        "question": "A Scrum Team has delivered 80 story points in the fourth Sprint and 90 story points in the sixth Sprint. Which one has delivered more value?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Fourth Sprint",
            "B": "They are the same",
            "C": "It depends",
            "D": "Sixth Sprint"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "It depends",
        "explanation": "There's no direct relationship between velocity and value. Different teams have different velocities as well, so we can't compare them."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who owns the Sprint Backlog?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The Stakeholders",
            "B": "The Scrum Team",
            "C": "The Product Owner",
            "D": "The Scrum Master",
            "E": "The Developers"
        },
        "answer": [
            "E"
        ],
        "answers": "The Developers",
        "explanation": "The Sprint Backlog is a plan by and for the Developers. It is a highly visible, real-time picture of the work that the Developers plan to accomplish during the Sprint in order to achieve the Sprint Goal."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Scrum can be used for sustaining complex products.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "A"
        ],
        "answers": "Yes",
        "explanation": "Scrum is a lightweight framework, not a methodology, process, techniques, etc. that helps people, teams and organizations generate value through adaptive solutions for complex problems."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Once the Sprint started, Developers can't add new items to the Sprint Backlog.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Only the Developers can change the Sprint Backlog during a Sprint as they learn more or they might add non-functional requirements."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. A Product Owner should have a complete Product Backlog before the first Sprint can start.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Product Backlog is never complete, it evolves to reflect continuous changes."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one of the following is wrong about the Scrum Master accountability?",
        "options": {
            "A": "They make sure that the Developers have Daily Scrums",
            "B": "They facilitate the meetings as required or requested",
            "C": "They participate in Daily Scrums",
            "D": "None of the answers apply",
            "E": "They participate in the Sprint Planning meetings",
            "F": "All answers apply"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "They participate in Daily Scrums",
        "explanation": "Daily Scrum is for Developers they should only participate, others can join as listeners. Note that the person who's doing the Scrum Master role may also do the role of a Developer, in which case, that person would participate in the Daily Scrum Meeting as a Developer."
    },
    {
        "question": "What does it mean to say that an event has a timebox?",
        "options": {
            "A": "The event must happen by a given time",
            "B": "All answers apply",
            "C": "The event can take no more than a maximum amount of time",
            "D": "The event must take at least a minimum amount of time",
            "E": "The event must happen at a set time",
            "F": "None of the answers apply"
        },
        "answer": [
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "The event can take no more than a maximum amount of time",
        "explanation": "Timeboxed events are events that have a maximum duration."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. Scrum is a process for developing complex products.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "Scrum is \"considered\" a framework, not a methodology, process, techniques, etc. It can be used to develop new products or maintain/sustain existing ones."
    },
    {
        "question": "What's the recommended way to estimate items, if you want to apply Scrum properly.",
        "options": {
            "A": "Planning poker",
            "B": "Story points",
            "C": "Both of the above",
            "D": "None of the above"
        },
        "answer": [
            "D"
        ],
        "answers": "None of the above",
        "explanation": "There is no recommended way for estimates in the Scrum Guide. They are free to use whatever is the best for them."
    },
    {
        "question": "True or False. When multiple Scrum Teams are working on the same product and each one on different areas of the product, they should have a different Product Goal.",
        "options": {
            "A": "True",
            "B": "False"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "No",
        "explanation": "The Product Goal describes a future state of the product which can serve as a target for the Scrum Team to plan against. The Product Goal is in the Product Backlog. The rest of the Product Backlog emerges to define “what” will fulfill the Product Goal, this is about the whole product."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements describe benefits of having a Product Goal? (Select the best two answers)",
        "options": {
            "A": "It helps identify the best time for releasing the product",
            "B": "It makes it easier to inspect the incremental progress of the product",
            "C": "It gives an overall objective to all Sprints",
            "D": "It helps identify when the complete Product Backlog should be finished",
            "E": "It’s a traditional concept, and there are no benefits to having it"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B",
            "C"
        ],
        "answers": "It makes it easier to inspect the incremental progress of the product and It gives an overall objective to all Sprints",
        "explanation": "The Product Goal describes a future state of the product which can serve as a target for the Scrum Team to plan against. The Product Goal is in the Product Backlog. The rest of the Product Backlog emerges to define “what” will fulfill the Product Goal."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which artifact contains a plan for making visible the Product Goal?",
        "options": {
            "A": "Sprint Backlog",
            "B": "Product Backlog",
            "C": "Increment"
        },
        "answer": [
            "B"
        ],
        "answers": "Product Backlog",
        "explanation": "The Product Backlog is composed of the Product Goal. Product Goal is commitment. The Product Goal describes a future state of the product."
    }
]